<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: algorithms | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/algorithms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-20T11:22:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Dictionary of Lists in Unity C#]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/create-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-c-sharp/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T11:16:28-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/create-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-c-sharp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript/">Last week</a>, I published an article about creating a Dictionary of Lists in Unity using Unity&rsquo;s JavaScript.  Some of the syntax is changed in C#, but the overall algorithm is exactly the same.  I&rsquo;ve already mentioned the underlying motive, so I&rsquo;ll dive right in.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&rsquo;s how to create a Dictionary of Lists in C# for Unity.</p>

<p>```csharp
Dictionary&lt;string, List<int>> table = new Dictionary&lt;string, List<int>>();</p>

<p>void Start() {</p>

<pre><code>// Fill our table with Lists containing ints using Arrays to intialize
// the Lists.
table["a"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){1};
table["b"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){2};
table["c"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){3};

foreach(string str in table.Keys) {
    // Get the value for our Key.
    List&lt;int&gt; value = table[str];

    // If the Key is the desired Key, append to its list.
    if(str == "c") {
        value.Add(4);
    }

    // print the first item in each of the Lists.
    Debug.Log(value[0]);
}

// Print the appended item to see that it worked.
Debug.Log(table["c"][1]);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>These are the main differences between the Unity JavaScript and C# code.  Take a look at the full file in a <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/e3882aa5ffd5dd614c9a">gist on github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Dictionary of Lists in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-13T11:14:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ran into a few problems trying to create a <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DWhich_Kind_Of_Array_Or_Collection_Should_I_Use%253F#Generic_Dictionary">Dictionary</a> of <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DWhich_Kind_Of_Array_Or_Collection_Should_I_Use%253F#Generic_List">Lists</a> in Unity JavaScript.  So I thought I&rsquo;d share some of the tips I learned here.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;m interested in creating a Dictionary to hold <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Markov_text_generators">Markov Chain information</a> in order to generate text.  So I&rsquo;d like to be able to create a Dictionary holding a variable length of items for each of its Keys.  I&rsquo;d also like to be able to update the mapping at runtime.</p>

<p>It would look something like this:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Key1:</strong> Item1, Item2, Item3</li>
<li><strong>Key2:</strong> Item4</li>
</ul>


<p>At runtime, I&rsquo;d like to be able to say: &ldquo;Append <code>Item5</code> to <code>Key2</code>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what I came up with in Unity JavaScript.  I started out by initializing a <code>table</code> in my script prior to the <code>Start</code> function. The var <code>table</code> holds our mapping of Keys of type <code>String</code> to Values of type <code>List.&lt;int&gt;</code>, or Lists of integers.</p>

<p><code>javascript
import System.Collections.Generic;
// White space matters.
var table:Dictionary.&lt;String,List.&lt;int&gt; &gt; = new Dictionary.&lt;String,List.&lt;int&gt; &gt;();
</code></p>

<p>The first hiccup I ran into is that <a href="http://forum.unity3d.com/threads/80227-Creating-a-Dictionary-of-Lists-in-Javascript?p%3D513471&amp;viewfull%3D1#post513471">white space matters</a> when creating Generics in Unity JavaScript.  The compiler will throw an error if it sees two <code>&gt;&gt;</code> in a row.</p>

<p>Then I fill the table with our test mappings.</p>

<p><code>javascript
// Fill our table with Lists containing ints using Arrays to intialize
// the Lists.
table["a"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([1]);
table["b"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([2]);
table["c"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([3]);
</code></p>

<p>As you can see, you can <a href="http://answers.unity3d.com/questions/221476/javascript-array-to-generic-list.html">construct a List from an Array</a>.  Cool.</p>

<p>In the <code>Start</code> function, I iterate over the Keys in the Dictionary, Add the item <code>4</code> to the Value of Key <code>c</code>, and print out the first item of each of the <code>values</code>.  Finally, we check to see whether <code>4</code> was appended to the desired entry.</p>

<p>```javascript
function Start () {</p>

<pre><code>// Iterate over the Keys in our Dictionary.
for(var str:String in table.Keys) {
    // Get the value for our Key.
    var value:List.&lt;int&gt; = table[str];

    // If the Key is our desired Key, append to its list.
    if (str == "c") {
        value.Add(4);
    }

    // Print the first item in each of the Lists.
    print(value[0]);
}

// Print the appended item to see that it worked.
print(table["c"][1]);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Then I attach this script to the Main Camera of a fresh Scene for testing purposes.  Bada bing, bada boom.</p>

<p>Attaching the script to any old object in the scene would work.  I just chose the Main Camera because the camera object is there by default.</p>

<p>This was all relatively straightforward, after I understood some of the quirks of Unity&rsquo;s JavaScript syntax.  You can find an example script using this code <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/f13eb62bf7bd57799db6">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Skytorn Raycast Lighting Algorithm Details]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T11:10:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn/">Last week</a> I covered the lighting algorithm <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB">@NoelFB</a> is implementing for <a href="http://skytorngame.com/">Skytorn</a>.  Noel was nice enough to correct my mistaken assumptions about the inner workings of the lighting algorithm.</p>

<p>Looks like I kind of inverted the polarity of the raycasting with regard to the player and the level geometry.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The algorithm</h2>

<p>The algorithm doesn&rsquo;t raycast in the full 360° circle around player&#x2013;that would be too costly.  Instead, it takes advantage of the fact that the level&rsquo;s ground collision geometry is stored in a grid.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Given the player&rsquo;s location, there is a small list of collision geometry in the 8 or so grid cells surrounding the player.</p></li>
<li><p>The lighting algorithm raycasts from the corners of the level geometry to the player, instead of from the player out to the geometry.</p></li>
<li><p>Then, to prevent the lighting from looking too triangular, the algorithm adds a few more raycasts out from the player to the geometry in between the other raycasts.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>That&rsquo;s actually all there is to it</h2>

<p>The algorithm I originally envisioned was naive and costly.  But, it&rsquo;s nice to hear that I wasn&rsquo;t far off&#x2013;I simply inverted the solution.  It was also nice to learn about a benefit of storing level geometry in a grid that I previously failed to appreciate.</p>

<p>Heaping thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/">@NoelFB</a> for helping explain the algorithm, instead of getting bent out of shape about my lame attempt to reverse engineer the inner workings of <a href="http://skytorn-game.com/">Skytorn</a> from a screenshot.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raycast Lighting in Skytorn]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-09T09:21:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/">@NoelFB</a> posted a <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/status/543586120731074561/photo/1">screenshot</a> showing how dynamic lighting works in <a href="http://skytorn-game.com/">Skytorn</a>.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The algorithm</h2>

<p>From what I can tell, the algorithm looks something like this:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Raycast out for 360° around the light source, starting in a clockwise direction.  If the rays encounter a collidable object, add it to the list of pink lines defining the polygonal shape of the lit area.  If the ray exceeds the distance of the light gradient, clamp the triangle edge defining the pink line at that distance.</p></li>
<li><p>For each of the collidable objects encountered, extend a ray past their vertices until it hits another collidable to create the obscured lighting effect visible to down and to the right of the light source.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally construct a set of triangles by starting from the closest edge in the list defining the pink lines to form the polygon.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>That&rsquo;s all</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week.  Let me know if you have any insight into this or other lighting algorithms in the comments or on the tweets.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>After some feedback from @NoelFB, I&rsquo;ve updated the algorithm in the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details/">following post</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sharing Philosophy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/27/sharing-philosophy/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-27T08:01:01-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/27/sharing-philosophy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.imperica.com/en/in-conversation-with/meta-ex-the-music-of-code">this interview</a> with <a href="https://twitter.com/samaaron">Sam Aaron</a>.  Aaron talks about sharing software to create music, but it applies just as well to games.</p>

<blockquote><p>We believe that most value in the world comes through sharing, and that music is no exception. One of the benefits of sharing is that it makes learning much easier. For example, we often hear amazing sounds on albums and wonder how they were made. However, musicians rarely share their production methods. We release all the software we write, which includes our synthesiser designs, interaction abstractions, and compositional structures, under an open source license, and we distribute it to everyone through GitHub. This makes it free and easy for anybody to copy and recreate any aspect of our work. For example, when one of our fans is interested in the sound of one of the synths we&rsquo;re using, they can go to GitHub and download the synth design as text. They can email it to their friends, read it, study it, copy it, modify it and run it to recreate the exact sound.</p></blockquote>

<p>&#x2013;Sam Aaron</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
