<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: version control | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/version-control/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-08T08:36:51-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Text encoding: further improvements to using git for Unity projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/text-encoding-further-improvements-to-using-git-for-unity-projects/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T09:51:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/text-encoding-further-improvements-to-using-git-for-unity-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brief note here.  Following a Summer of travel and visitors, posts should be returning to a more regular schedule soon.  It&rsquo;s great when I can post here regularly, but I&rsquo;m not going to get bent out of shape when I have other commitments.  So, if there are unannounced, prolonged absences, you can assume that it has something to do with spending my weekends traveling or socializing, which is undoubtedly a good thing.</p>

<p>I recently came across <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/18225126/how-to-use-git-for-unity3d-source-control">this stackoverflow answer</a> introducing git for version control in Unity projects.  Note, the question specifically refers to Unity3D, but this will work for Unity2D as well.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/dot-gitignore-for-unity-projects/">already written</a> about setting up a <code>.gitignore</code> file.  Here are some steps you can take to optimize the way Unity stores information, so git can track it.</p>

<p>Git was built to work by <code>diffing</code> large files containing text, specifically code.  Git works just fine with binary files, but it defaults to a less efficient method to <code>diff</code> those files, which can result in bloated git repositories.  Nobody wants a bloated git repository.</p>

<p>Here I&rsquo;ll summarize two of the steps from the answer that I found helpful, using Unity v4.5+.  It&rsquo;s worth noting that these steps will increase the size of your project&mdash;although I&rsquo;m unsure whether they affect the size of any deployed binaries.</p>

<p>So if the size of the project on your development machine is a critical issue, you may want to think about keeping the default settings.  The project I tried the steps on went from 86.7 MB on disk (including its bloated git repository) to 86.9 MB, so it&rsquo;s probably not going to create an appreciable change in most projects.</p>

<h2>Switch to Visible Meta Files</h2>

<p>Switch to <code>Visible Meta Files</code> in the Edit → Project Settings → Editor → Version Control Mode Menu.</p>

<p>If the <code>Visible Meta Files</code> option is turned on, the <code>.meta</code> files associated with parts of your project will have textual information rather than binary.</p>

<h2>Switch to Force Text</h2>

<p>Switch to <code>Force Text</code> in the Edit → Project Settings → Editor → Version Control Menu.</p>

<p>If you choose <code>Force Text</code> this will cause Unity to use text to serialize assets that it would normally store as binary files.</p>

<h2>Save</h2>

<p>Save the Scene and project for these changes to take effect.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[.gitignore for Unity projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/dot-gitignore-for-unity-projects/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T11:48:06-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/dot-gitignore-for-unity-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found a solution on the <a href="http://answers.unity3d.com/questions/369755/unity-on-github.html">Unity website</a> that pointed me toward <a href="http://t-machine.org/index.php/2012/07/03/unity-git-source-control-a-basic-gitignore/">this blogpost</a>.  But a better solution is out there.  The Double Fine Game Club&rsquo;s Bad Golf Community Edition <a href="https://github.com/Double-Fine-Game-Club/bad-golf-community-edition/blob/master/.gitignore">.gitignore</a> looks like this:</p>

<p>```sh
[Ll]ibrary/
[Tt]emp/
[Oo]bj/
build_Data/</p>

<h1>Autogenerated VS/MD solution and project files</h1>

<p><em>.csproj
</em>.unityproj
<em>.sln
</em>.exe
*.userprefs</p>

<h1>OS generated files</h1>

<h6>#</h6>

<p>.DS_Store
.DS_Store?
._<em>
.[Ss]potlight-V100
.[Tt]rashes
[Ee]hthumbs.db
[Tt]humbs.db
</em>~
<em>#</em>
```</p>

<p>This is the <code>.gitignore</code> I&rsquo;m currently using in my projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
