<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Unity3d | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/unity3d/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-07T10:26:53-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Dictionary with multiple keys in Unity C#]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T11:03:42-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to create a lookup table for comparing a player choice and an enemy choice.  Each pair of choices can lead to a variety of outcomes.  So, in order to map the relationship between choice pair and outcome, I&rsquo;ve decided to use a Dictionary with choice pairs as keys and outcomes as values.</p>

<p>To me, the obvious way to do this is by using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuple">tuples</a> to encode the choice pairs.  I&rsquo;ve already enumerated the choices so it&rsquo;s simple enough to pair them off in tuples for use as keys for the Dictionary.  This approach worked, however, I ran into a couple of problems along the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Unity&rsquo;s C# doesn&rsquo;t have Tuples</h2>

<p>Unity&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mono_%2528software%2529">Mono framework</a> includes a C# compiler, runtime, and lots of libraries.  The version of Mono included with version <code>4.6.1f1</code> of Unity is <code>2.6.5 (tarball)</code>.  Mono recreates some of the features of .NET, but apparently not a <code>Tuple</code> type.  The <code>Tuple</code> type got added to .NET in version <code>4.0</code>.  Looks like Mono version <code>2.8</code> may support it, but I&rsquo;ll have to wait for the folks at Unity to update Mono.</p>

<p>I checked the version of Mono using the following code:</p>

<p>``` csharp Check Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono
using System;
using System.Reflection;</p>

<p>Type type = Type.GetType(&ldquo;Mono.Runtime&rdquo;);
if (type != null) {</p>

<pre><code>MethodInfo displayName = type.GetMethod("GetDisplayName",
                                        BindingFlags.NonPublic | BindingFlags.Static);
if (displayName != null)
  Debug.Log(displayName.Invoke(null, null));
</code></pre>

<p> }
```</p>

<p>Since Mono <code>2.8</code> was released 5 years ago, it seems like Unity is in no rush to update their Mono version.  So it looks like I&rsquo;ll have to roll my own tuple class.</p>

<h2>Implementing a Pairs class</h2>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m only concerned with pairs of choices, I decided to implement the simplest possible solution.  I followed the implementation of a <code>Pair</code> class from <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/569903/multi-value-dictionary">this Stack Overflow question regarding encoding multiple values in Dictionaries</a>.  The trick is that the tuple implemented here can be used to encode keys as well.</p>

<p>The critically important part of the <code>Pair</code> class is that it inherits from <code>IEquatable</code> and implements methods for determining equality and hashing.  The fundamental thing a Dictionary needs is to test whether keys are equal in order to store or retrieve the correct values and it typically does so by hashing the key.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t bother reproducing the code for the <code>Pair</code> class here.  You can <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/569920">check it out for yourself</a>.</p>

<h2>How I wish I could use it</h2>

<p>Once I implemented the <code>Pair</code> class in its own file <code>Pair.cs</code>, I had to import it in the file where I wanted to create the Dictionary.  Also note that I&rsquo;m <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb531208.aspx">using literal syntax to construct the Dictionary when I define it</a>.  And yes, unlike most uses of curly braces in C#, that <code>;</code> is necessary to end the line after the literal.</p>

<p>``` csharp
using Pair;</p>

<p>// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> {
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceOne), Outcome.Win},
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceTwo), Outcome.Lose},
};</p>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Pair(ChoiceOne, ChoiceOne)];</p>

<p>// Compiler throws an error
```</p>

<p>But alas, I run into this error: <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code>.  I can&rsquo;t seem to find any documentation detailing what I&rsquo;m doing wrong.  Maybe it&rsquo;s just a problem with Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono .NET runtime.</p>

<h2>The workaround: A Dictionary of Dictionaries</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found a workaround.  It is, in my humble opinion, way less elegant, but it gets the job done.</p>

<p>``` csharp
// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Choice, Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome>> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {
  {Choice.ChoiceOne, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Win},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Lose}
}},
</code></pre>

<p>  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Lose},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Win}
}}};
</code></pre>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Choice.ChoiceOne][Choice.ChoiceOne];</p>

<p>// Will return Outcome.Win
```</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I find the tuple key code way more readable than the Dictionary of Dictionaries code.  You can imagine how the legibility of the Dictionary of Dictionaries approach decreases with additional keys but the tuple key code legibility remains the same no matter how many keys you add.  This is probably a moot point for using two keys, as I have in this example, but I hope you can appreciate why I think the tuple approach is more elegant.</p>

<p>If you have any insight into how to solve the <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code> error I encountered using the <code>Pair</code> class, please let me know in the comments below or on <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Mind-reading Machine in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T14:38:20-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ported a cool toy from <a href="http://alastaira.wordpress.com/2014/03/15/a-simple-mind-reading-machine/">Alastair Aitchison&rsquo;s blog</a> to Unity JavaScript.  The toy implements a simple &lsquo;mind-reading&rsquo; algorithm that attempts to guess whether the player will choose Left (by pressing the left arrow key) or Right (by pressing the right arrow key).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How does it work?</h2>

<p>Aitchison&rsquo;s blog post describes how it works:</p>

<blockquote><p>How does it work? Not by mind-reading, obviously, but by exploiting
the fact that humans do not behave as &ldquo;randomly&rdquo; as they think they
do. The computer maintains a very simple memory that records the
pattern of results of the last two rounds – whether the player won or
lost, whether they switched strategy, and then whether they then won
or last the following round. The computer then uses this to choose its
own best strategy based on the way the player behaved last time the
current pattern occurred. If the computer loses twice in a row using
the current strategy, it picks a random response in the next round.</p></blockquote>

<p>The original idea came from some AI work by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Shannon">Claude Shannon</a> and D. W. Hagelbarger. <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/people/eroberts/courses/soco/projects/1999-00/information-theory/ai.html">They describe the internal memory of the toy mind-reader</a> that we will model using a multidimensional array <code>v</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>There are 8 possible situations and two things the player can do at each one:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, loses. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<h2>Why port it?</h2>

<p>Why not just take a straightforward approach, running the code myself? First, I wanted to fully understand the algorithm the hard way, by coding it line for line myself. And second, I wanted to better familiarize myself with Unity JavaScript, including its differences from C#.</p>

<p>The port was relatively simple, except for two small hiccups.  First, as far as I know, Unity JavaScript doesn&rsquo;t allow for initializing a multidimensional array.  So I looped over the cells in the array, filling them that way.  I have a hunch that the cells are initialized to the <code>int</code> <code>0</code> by default, but I wanted to be explicit.  Please let me know in the comments or <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">via twitter</a> if I&rsquo;m way off base.</p>

<pre><code>var v : int[2, 2, 2];
for(var cell in v) {
    cell = 0;
}
</code></pre>

<p>I also encountered some unfamiliar syntax: the sonorously named Elvis operator, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_operator">?:</a>.  It&rsquo;s also called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternary_operation">ternary operator</a>, when it&rsquo;s used with 3 arguments, as I&rsquo;ve used it here.  In C-like languages it allows for succinctly stating these kinds of conditional expressions. The example below illustrates how it&rsquo;s used.</p>

<pre><code>// Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
// choice?
//
// if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
//     sameChoice = True;
// else
//     sameChoice = False;
//
// Using ternary operator:
v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
</code></pre>

<h2>The code</h2>

<p>The ported code for the mind-reader is reproduced below.</p>

<pre><code>#pragma strict
import System.Collections.Generic;

// Used to record play history
var v: int[,,];
var lw1: int;
var lw2: int;
var losingStreak: int;

// The prediction of the player's next turn
var prediction: int;

// Keep track of scores
var cpuScore: int;
var playerScore: int;

var outText: String;

function Start () {
    // Initialize matrix to track state of play history

    v = new int[2, 2, 2];

    for(var cell in v) {
        cell = 0;
    }

    // No prior knowledge, so set inital prediction based on random chance.
    prediction = flip();

    // Set scores to 0
    cpuScore = 0;
    playerScore = 0;

    // Initialize previous play and play before last win-lost trackers
    lw1 = 0;
    lw2 = 0;

    // Output
    outText = "";
}

function TakeTurn(playerChoice: int) {
    // Display player and computer's choices
    var outTextString: String = "You pressed " + playerChoice + ", " + "I guessed " + prediction + "\n";

    // Computer guessed correctly
    if (playerChoice == prediction) {
        cpuScore++;
        losingStreak = 0;
        outTextString += " I WIN!\n";
    }
    else {
        playerScore++;
        losingStreak++;
        outTextString += " YOU WIN!\n";
    }

    outText = outTextString;

    // Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
    // choice?
    //
    // if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
    //     sameChoice = True;
    // else
    //     sameChoice = False;
    //
    // Using ternary operator:
    v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
    v[lw2, lw1, 0] = playerChoice;
    lw2 = lw1;
    lw1 = playerChoice;

    // If lost more than twice in present state, choose random
    // strategy.  Otherwise keep the same strategy.
    prediction = v[lw2, lw1, 1] == 1 &amp;&amp; losingStreak &lt; 2 ? v[lw2, lw1, 0] : flip();
}

function flip() : int {
    // Simulate a coin flip to produce 50:50 chance of [0, 1]
    return Random.Range(0, 2);
}


function Update () {
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.LeftArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(0);
    }
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.RightArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(1);
    }
}

function OnGUI() {
    var style : GUIStyle = new GUIStyle();
    style.fontSize = 36;

    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 0, Screen.width, 100), outText, style);
    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 100, Screen.width, 200), "Player: " + playerScore + " CPU: " + cpuScore, style);
}
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
