<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Unity | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/unity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-28T17:22:56-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Dictionary with multiple keys in Unity C#]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T11:03:42-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to create a lookup table for comparing a player choice and an enemy choice.  Each pair of choices can lead to a variety of outcomes.  So, in order to map the relationship between choice pair and outcome, I&rsquo;ve decided to use a Dictionary with choice pairs as keys and outcomes as values.</p>

<p>To me, the obvious way to do this is by using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuple">tuples</a> to encode the choice pairs.  I&rsquo;ve already enumerated the choices so it&rsquo;s simple enough to pair them off in tuples for use as keys for the Dictionary.  This approach worked, however, I ran into a couple of problems along the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Unity&rsquo;s C# doesn&rsquo;t have Tuples</h2>

<p>Unity&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mono_%2528software%2529">Mono framework</a> includes a C# compiler, runtime, and lots of libraries.  The version of Mono included with version <code>4.6.1f1</code> of Unity is <code>2.6.5 (tarball)</code>.  Mono recreates some of the features of .NET, but apparently not a <code>Tuple</code> type.  The <code>Tuple</code> type got added to .NET in version <code>4.0</code>.  Looks like Mono version <code>2.8</code> may support it, but I&rsquo;ll have to wait for the folks at Unity to update Mono.</p>

<p>I checked the version of Mono using the following code:</p>

<p>``` csharp Check Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono
using System;
using System.Reflection;</p>

<p>Type type = Type.GetType(&ldquo;Mono.Runtime&rdquo;);
if (type != null) {</p>

<pre><code>MethodInfo displayName = type.GetMethod("GetDisplayName",
                                        BindingFlags.NonPublic | BindingFlags.Static);
if (displayName != null)
  Debug.Log(displayName.Invoke(null, null));
</code></pre>

<p> }
```</p>

<p>Since Mono <code>2.8</code> was released 5 years ago, it seems like Unity is in no rush to update their Mono version.  So it looks like I&rsquo;ll have to roll my own tuple class.</p>

<h2>Implementing a Pairs class</h2>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m only concerned with pairs of choices, I decided to implement the simplest possible solution.  I followed the implementation of a <code>Pair</code> class from <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/569903/multi-value-dictionary">this Stack Overflow question regarding encoding multiple values in Dictionaries</a>.  The trick is that the tuple implemented here can be used to encode keys as well.</p>

<p>The critically important part of the <code>Pair</code> class is that it inherits from <code>IEquatable</code> and implements methods for determining equality and hashing.  The fundamental thing a Dictionary needs is to test whether keys are equal in order to store or retrieve the correct values and it typically does so by hashing the key.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t bother reproducing the code for the <code>Pair</code> class here.  You can <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/569920">check it out for yourself</a>.</p>

<h2>How I wish I could use it</h2>

<p>Once I implemented the <code>Pair</code> class in its own file <code>Pair.cs</code>, I had to import it in the file where I wanted to create the Dictionary.  Also note that I&rsquo;m <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb531208.aspx">using literal syntax to construct the Dictionary when I define it</a>.  And yes, unlike most uses of curly braces in C#, that <code>;</code> is necessary to end the line after the literal.</p>

<p>``` csharp
using Pair;</p>

<p>// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> {
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceOne), Outcome.Win},
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceTwo), Outcome.Lose},
};</p>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Pair(ChoiceOne, ChoiceOne)];</p>

<p>// Compiler throws an error
```</p>

<p>But alas, I run into this error: <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code>.  I can&rsquo;t seem to find any documentation detailing what I&rsquo;m doing wrong.  Maybe it&rsquo;s just a problem with Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono .NET runtime.</p>

<h2>The workaround: A Dictionary of Dictionaries</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found a workaround.  It is, in my humble opinion, way less elegant, but it gets the job done.</p>

<p>``` csharp
// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Choice, Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome>> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {
  {Choice.ChoiceOne, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Win},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Lose}
}},
</code></pre>

<p>  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Lose},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Win}
}}};
</code></pre>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Choice.ChoiceOne][Choice.ChoiceOne];</p>

<p>// Will return Outcome.Win
```</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I find the tuple key code way more readable than the Dictionary of Dictionaries code.  You can imagine how the legibility of the Dictionary of Dictionaries approach decreases with additional keys but the tuple key code legibility remains the same no matter how many keys you add.  This is probably a moot point for using two keys, as I have in this example, but I hope you can appreciate why I think the tuple approach is more elegant.</p>

<p>If you have any insight into how to solve the <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code> error I encountered using the <code>Pair</code> class, please let me know in the comments below or on <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Mind-reading Machine in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T14:38:20-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ported a cool toy from <a href="http://alastaira.wordpress.com/2014/03/15/a-simple-mind-reading-machine/">Alastair Aitchison&rsquo;s blog</a> to Unity JavaScript.  The toy implements a simple &lsquo;mind-reading&rsquo; algorithm that attempts to guess whether the player will choose Left (by pressing the left arrow key) or Right (by pressing the right arrow key).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How does it work?</h2>

<p>Aitchison&rsquo;s blog post describes how it works:</p>

<blockquote><p>How does it work? Not by mind-reading, obviously, but by exploiting
the fact that humans do not behave as &ldquo;randomly&rdquo; as they think they
do. The computer maintains a very simple memory that records the
pattern of results of the last two rounds – whether the player won or
lost, whether they switched strategy, and then whether they then won
or last the following round. The computer then uses this to choose its
own best strategy based on the way the player behaved last time the
current pattern occurred. If the computer loses twice in a row using
the current strategy, it picks a random response in the next round.</p></blockquote>

<p>The original idea came from some AI work by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Shannon">Claude Shannon</a> and D. W. Hagelbarger. <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/people/eroberts/courses/soco/projects/1999-00/information-theory/ai.html">They describe the internal memory of the toy mind-reader</a> that we will model using a multidimensional array <code>v</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>There are 8 possible situations and two things the player can do at each one:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, loses. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<h2>Why port it?</h2>

<p>Why not just take a straightforward approach, running the code myself? First, I wanted to fully understand the algorithm the hard way, by coding it line for line myself. And second, I wanted to better familiarize myself with Unity JavaScript, including its differences from C#.</p>

<p>The port was relatively simple, except for two small hiccups.  First, as far as I know, Unity JavaScript doesn&rsquo;t allow for initializing a multidimensional array.  So I looped over the cells in the array, filling them that way.  I have a hunch that the cells are initialized to the <code>int</code> <code>0</code> by default, but I wanted to be explicit.  Please let me know in the comments or <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">via twitter</a> if I&rsquo;m way off base.</p>

<pre><code>var v : int[2, 2, 2];
for(var cell in v) {
    cell = 0;
}
</code></pre>

<p>I also encountered some unfamiliar syntax: the sonorously named Elvis operator, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_operator">?:</a>.  It&rsquo;s also called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternary_operation">ternary operator</a>, when it&rsquo;s used with 3 arguments, as I&rsquo;ve used it here.  In C-like languages it allows for succinctly stating these kinds of conditional expressions. The example below illustrates how it&rsquo;s used.</p>

<pre><code>// Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
// choice?
//
// if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
//     sameChoice = True;
// else
//     sameChoice = False;
//
// Using ternary operator:
v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
</code></pre>

<h2>The code</h2>

<p>The ported code for the mind-reader is reproduced below.</p>

<pre><code>#pragma strict
import System.Collections.Generic;

// Used to record play history
var v: int[,,];
var lw1: int;
var lw2: int;
var losingStreak: int;

// The prediction of the player's next turn
var prediction: int;

// Keep track of scores
var cpuScore: int;
var playerScore: int;

var outText: String;

function Start () {
    // Initialize matrix to track state of play history

    v = new int[2, 2, 2];

    for(var cell in v) {
        cell = 0;
    }

    // No prior knowledge, so set inital prediction based on random chance.
    prediction = flip();

    // Set scores to 0
    cpuScore = 0;
    playerScore = 0;

    // Initialize previous play and play before last win-lost trackers
    lw1 = 0;
    lw2 = 0;

    // Output
    outText = "";
}

function TakeTurn(playerChoice: int) {
    // Display player and computer's choices
    var outTextString: String = "You pressed " + playerChoice + ", " + "I guessed " + prediction + "\n";

    // Computer guessed correctly
    if (playerChoice == prediction) {
        cpuScore++;
        losingStreak = 0;
        outTextString += " I WIN!\n";
    }
    else {
        playerScore++;
        losingStreak++;
        outTextString += " YOU WIN!\n";
    }

    outText = outTextString;

    // Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
    // choice?
    //
    // if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
    //     sameChoice = True;
    // else
    //     sameChoice = False;
    //
    // Using ternary operator:
    v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
    v[lw2, lw1, 0] = playerChoice;
    lw2 = lw1;
    lw1 = playerChoice;

    // If lost more than twice in present state, choose random
    // strategy.  Otherwise keep the same strategy.
    prediction = v[lw2, lw1, 1] == 1 &amp;&amp; losingStreak &lt; 2 ? v[lw2, lw1, 0] : flip();
}

function flip() : int {
    // Simulate a coin flip to produce 50:50 chance of [0, 1]
    return Random.Range(0, 2);
}


function Update () {
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.LeftArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(0);
    }
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.RightArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(1);
    }
}

function OnGUI() {
    var style : GUIStyle = new GUIStyle();
    style.fontSize = 36;

    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 0, Screen.width, 100), outText, style);
    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 100, Screen.width, 200), "Player: " + playerScore + " CPU: " + cpuScore, style);
}
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Text encoding: further improvements to using git for Unity projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/text-encoding-further-improvements-to-using-git-for-unity-projects/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-27T09:51:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/09/27/text-encoding-further-improvements-to-using-git-for-unity-projects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brief note here.  Following a Summer of travel and visitors, posts should be returning to a more regular schedule soon.  It&rsquo;s great when I can post here regularly, but I&rsquo;m not going to get bent out of shape when I have other commitments.  So, if there are unannounced, prolonged absences, you can assume that it has something to do with spending my weekends traveling or socializing, which is undoubtedly a good thing.</p>

<p>I recently came across <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/18225126/how-to-use-git-for-unity3d-source-control">this stackoverflow answer</a> introducing git for version control in Unity projects.  Note, the question specifically refers to Unity3D, but this will work for Unity2D as well.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/17/dot-gitignore-for-unity-projects/">already written</a> about setting up a <code>.gitignore</code> file.  Here are some steps you can take to optimize the way Unity stores information, so git can track it.</p>

<p>Git was built to work by <code>diffing</code> large files containing text, specifically code.  Git works just fine with binary files, but it defaults to a less efficient method to <code>diff</code> those files, which can result in bloated git repositories.  Nobody wants a bloated git repository.</p>

<p>Here I&rsquo;ll summarize two of the steps from the answer that I found helpful, using Unity v4.5+.  It&rsquo;s worth noting that these steps will increase the size of your project&mdash;although I&rsquo;m unsure whether they affect the size of any deployed binaries.</p>

<p>So if the size of the project on your development machine is a critical issue, you may want to think about keeping the default settings.  The project I tried the steps on went from 86.7 MB on disk (including its bloated git repository) to 86.9 MB, so it&rsquo;s probably not going to create an appreciable change in most projects.</p>

<h2>Switch to Visible Meta Files</h2>

<p>Switch to <code>Visible Meta Files</code> in the Edit → Project Settings → Editor → Version Control Mode Menu.</p>

<p>If the <code>Visible Meta Files</code> option is turned on, the <code>.meta</code> files associated with parts of your project will have textual information rather than binary.</p>

<h2>Switch to Force Text</h2>

<p>Switch to <code>Force Text</code> in the Edit → Project Settings → Editor → Version Control Menu.</p>

<p>If you choose <code>Force Text</code> this will cause Unity to use text to serialize assets that it would normally store as binary files.</p>

<h2>Save</h2>

<p>Save the Scene and project for these changes to take effect.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Persistent Data in Unity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/persistent-data-in-unity/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T11:09:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/persistent-data-in-unity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m interested in having some data remain available, even though I&rsquo;m switching Scenes in Unity.  In other words, I want this data to remain persistent.  As you&rsquo;ll see below I was tempted to use <code>PlayerPrefs</code> to store the data, but, according to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3DJ6FfcJpbPXE">this Unity Live Training on Data Persistence</a>, <code>PlayerPrefs</code> is not the best way to make data persist over multiple Scenes.  <code>PlayerPrefs</code> is an okay place to store non-critical data, like the audio volume, window size, full-screen state&#x2013;you know preferences.  I&rsquo;ll go ahead and show what I believe to be the correct way to store persistent data before talking about <code>PlayerPrefs</code> later.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Persistent data</h2>

<p>To safely and reliably store persistent data, the Unity tutorials suggest that you need to assign a &ldquo;kinda&rdquo; Singleton design patterny script to an empty <code>GameObject</code> that will persist across Scenes.</p>

<pre><code>using UnityEngine;
using System.Collections;

public class GameControl: MonoBehaviour {
  public static GameControl control;

  public float health;
  public float experience;

  void Awake() {
    if(control == null){
      DontDestroyOnLoad(gameObject);
      control = this;
    } else if(control != this) {
      // There can be only one!
      Destroy(gameObject);
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>static</code> reference means that we can just access the values in the <code>GameControl</code> script.</p>

<h2>How to access data in the GameController.</h2>

<pre><code>GameController.control.health = 100;
</code></pre>

<h2>Writing persistent data to a binary file</h2>

<p>The persistent data that&rsquo;s under the control of the <code>GameController</code> is perfectly happy hanging out when your application is running.  It will persist between Scenes when other data is wiped out by Unity&rsquo;s garbage collection.  But what if you want to maintain persistent data when the application is closed.</p>

<p>Ah hah!  Finally, an answer to my nagging question about writing persistent data to plain text files, like <code>PlayerPrefs</code> or simply a file in a local directory.  Wouldn&rsquo;t a player be able to modify the data?</p>

<p>Enter the binary format:</p>

<pre><code>// Add two more libraries
using System;
using System.Runtime.Serialzation.Formatters.Binary;
</code></pre>

<p>Where do we save it?  The persistent data path: <code>Application.persistentDataPath</code>.  We&rsquo;ll need one more library to do some input and output to files:</p>

<pre><code>// Requires one more library and we're ready to get cooking with some
// methods
using System.IO;

public void Save() {
  BinaryFormatter bf = new BinaryFormatter();
  FileStream file = File.Open(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat",
                              FileMode.Open);

  PlayerData data = new PlayerData();
  data.experiencePoints = experiencePoints;
  data.playerLevel = playerLevel;

  bf.Serialize(file, data);
  file.Close();
}

public void Load() {
  if(File.Exists(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat")) {
    BinaryFormatter bf = new BinaryFormatter();
    FileStream file = File.Open(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat",
                                FileMode.Open);
    PlayerData data = (PlayerData)bf.Deserialize(file);
    file.Close();

    experiencePoints = data.experiencePoints;
    playerLevel = data.playerLevel;
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we need to make the <code>PlayerData</code> class that we will tag with <code>[Serializable]</code> so Unity will know that we want to write this to a binary file at some point in the future.  This affects how Unity stores the data internally, but it doesn&rsquo;t really change how we interact with it.</p>

<pre><code>[Serializable]
class PlayerData {
  // TODO: see about making gets and sets.
  // TODO: automate the generation of this data structure.  See:
  // http://forums.devx.com/showthread.php?170650-How-to-dynamically-add-property-to

  // Add new variables for loading and saving here.
  public int experiencePoints;
  public int playerLevel;
}
</code></pre>

<p>After writing up this article, I came across an older, possibly better article on Unity Gems.  Please check out that write-up and all of the great content on the site.  <a href="http://unitygems.com/saving-data-1-remember-me/">http://unitygems.com/saving-data-1-remember-me/</a></p>

<p>My full <code>GameController</code> data persistence Singleton script is available in <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/6f6e811b27761d287ea5">this gist</a>.</p>

<p>So, that&rsquo;s the best solution I&rsquo;ve found to date for having persistent data across scenes and play sessions.  I&rsquo;ve included my rough first stabs at the problem below.  Keep in mind that anything following this point is just included just to make my notes available, and it&rsquo;s not meant to be a guide.</p>

<h2>Old notes: PlayerPrefs</h2>

<p>In order to have persistent data between Scenes, I was previously going to make use of Unity&rsquo;s <code>PlayerPrefs</code>, a class that implements persistent data storage for <code>ints</code>, <code>floats</code>, and <code>strings</code>.  Notably absent are useful data types like <code>Vector3</code> to maintain, for example, <code>transform</code> data between Scenes.  Some of the solutions I found may still be helpful for more storing complex data types in <code>PlayerPrefs</code>.</p>

<p>One potential solution is to simply set a <code>GameObject</code>&rsquo;s <code>transform.position</code> to some constant <code>Vector3</code> value in the freshly loaded Scene.  While this is possible in some applications, I&rsquo;m going to assume that eventually you&rsquo;ll want to transfer some dynamic position information between Scenes.</p>

<p>Here are two potentially helpful sources to achieve this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theappguruz.com/tutorial/store-vector3-data-easily-using-json-parsing-possible-using-playerprefs/">http://www.theappguruz.com/tutorial/store-vector3-data-easily-using-json-parsing-possible-using-playerprefs/</a>, based on work by Mehta Dakshil.  While JSON parsing looks interesting, it requires an external <code>.dll</code>, <code>JsonFx.Json.dll</code>.  And I&rsquo;m not interested in external dependencies here.  It may work great for you.</p>

<p><a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DArrayPrefs">&lt;http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title=ArrayPrefs></a>, based on work by Mario Madureiera Fontes and Daniel P. Rossi.  (Note: since <code>GetVector3</code> depends on <code>GetFloatArray</code>, there could be some error due to <code>GetFloatArray</code> casting strings to floats.  But the error introduce in the resulting <code>Vector3</code> is unlikely to be noticeable.)</p>

<p>Actually, see a more updated version here: <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php/ArrayPrefs2">http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php/ArrayPrefs2</a>, which is based on work by Eric Haines.</p>

<p>According to the text, the script should be placed in the <code>Standard Assets</code> directory, so that it can be accessed from both <code>C#</code> and <code>Boo</code> scripts.</p>

<p>To see a faster implementation for mobile devices, where the data to be saved in PlayerPrefs is cached in memory, see: <a href="http://www.previewlabs.com/writing-playerprefs-fast/">http://www.previewlabs.com/writing-playerprefs-fast/</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Static and Dynamic Colliders in Unity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/static-and-dynamic-colliders-in-unity/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-02T12:54:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/02/static-and-dynamic-colliders-in-unity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to the <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/70344/unity-2d-tutorial-physics-and-screen-sizes">Ray Wenderlich Unity 2D tutorial</a> by <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/u/clapollo">Christopher LaPollo</a>, Unity&rsquo;s physics engine builds a simulation based on the <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Manual/CollidersOverview.html">Colliders</a> present in a scene.  If some those <code>Colliders</code> are declared to be <code>static</code>, then the entire simulation is rebuilt when those colliders move.  Of course, rebuilding a physics simulation when it&rsquo;s unnecessary is inefficient.  By declaring objects to have <code>dynamic</code> <code>Colliders</code>, the physics engine does not have to rebuild the simulation at runtime, that is to say when the game is running.</p>

<p>As with a lot of things in Unity, it is not immediately apparent how you should go about declaring a collider to be <code>static</code> or <code>dynamic</code>.  It would be great if there were just a checkbox in the <code>Collider</code> component.  But there isn&rsquo;t.  It appears that there are some complex things going on under the hood that preclude a simple declaration.</p>

<p>By default a <code>GameObject</code> with a <code>Collider</code> component attached is treated as <code>static</code> by Unity&rsquo;s physics engine.  This would work for a non-moving wall or impassable bit of scenery, but for moving objects like enemies we need to mark them as <code>dynamic</code>.  In order for a <code>GameObject</code>&rsquo;s <code>Collider</code> to qualify as <code>dynamic</code> it requires a <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Manual/class-Rigidbody.html"><code>Rigidbody</code> component</a>.  If you don&rsquo;t want the normal features of the <code>Rigidbody</code>, i.e. conferring control of the <code>GameObject</code>&rsquo;s position to the physics system, then you can check the <code>Is Kinematic</code> checkbox.  A kinematic object&rsquo;s position is under the control of the attached scripts, rather than the physics system.</p>

<p>One other trick from the <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/70344/unity-2d-tutorial-physics-and-screen-sizes">tutorial</a> is to set the <code>Collider</code> component&rsquo;s <code>isTrigger</code> property to <code>true</code>.  This prevents the <code>Collider</code> from being treated as a solid object in the physics simulation, which could lead to unintended bumping and pushing among various <code>Colliders</code> in a scene.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://twitter.com/involvingsalmon">@InvolvingSalmon</a> points out that the instructions here depend on the version of Unity that you are using.  This article was written for Unity version <code>4.5.2f1</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
