<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Unity | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/unity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-04T15:22:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Probabilistic Entity Spawning in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/07/04/probabilistic-entity-spawning-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-04T09:56:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/07/04/probabilistic-entity-spawning-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Unity documentation has an example showing how to generate random indexes satisfying a distribution of probabilities (see: <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Manual/RandomNumbers.html">Choosing Items with Different Probabilities</a>).  In this post I&rsquo;ll show how to use a similar approach to generate random items with specific probabilities dictated by the environment.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I want to be able to generate an item code, say <code>Red</code>, <code>Green</code>, or <code>Black</code>, given a list of floating point probabilities dictated by the current environmental area in my game, say for example <code>desert</code> or <code>grassland</code>.</p>

<p>Varying the probability of encountering items will give each area a unique flavor.  If the player needs a <code>Red</code> item, the player will need to seek out areas in which the probability for encountering <code>Red</code> items is high.  I hope this will drive player exploration and investigation.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll start by defining an array of possible item types.  (According to <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php/Head_First_into_Unity_with_UnityScript#Use_enum">this introduction to Unity JavaScript</a>, I should prefer <code>enum</code>.)</p>

<p><code>javascript
var ents : String[] = ["Red", "Green", "Black", "Orange"];
</code></p>

<p>Since this is a small example, I&rsquo;ll forego the efficiency and security that <code>enum</code>s provide for the convenience of using a simple <code>String</code> array.  I&rsquo;ll note that this is a good spot to do some refactoring in a real project where a variety of systems may have to interact with the item types.</p>

<p>I then define a Dictionary <code>areas</code> of Lists of floating point probabilities.  These areas correspond to terrains that contain unique distributions of items. The <code>areas</code> Dictionary accepts <code>String</code>s specifying the desired terrain.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to note that the order of the probabilities correspond to the order of the item types in <code>ent</code>s.</p>

<p><code>javascript
var areas = new Dictionary.&lt;String, List.&lt;float&gt; &gt;();
areas["desert"] = new List.&lt;float&gt;([0.1, 0.05, 0.425, 0.425]);
areas["grassland"] = new List.&lt;float&gt;([0.3, 0.35, 0.1, 0.25]);
</code></p>

<p>So, in the <code>grassland</code> area, there will be a 30% chance of choosing a <code>Red</code> item.</p>

<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve defined the data, I need a function to choose the appropriate index given a List of probabilities.  This function is lifted with minor modifications from the <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Documentation/Manual/RandomNumbers.html">Unity Documentation</a>.  Take a look at that documentation for a better visualization of the algorithm than I could do with words.  Really, do it!</p>

<p>``` javascript
function Choose(probs : List.<float>) : int {</p>

<pre><code>// Returns the index of a probabilistically determined random
// entity, given by the probability distributions in probs.
// e.g.:
// probs : List.&lt;float&gt;([0.5, 0.2, 0.1, 0.2]);
// entity = entities[Choose(probs)];
//
// See http://docs.unity3d.com/Documentation/Manual/RandomNumbers.html

// Watch out!  If you fail to specify total's type as float, it
// will add the probs using integer addition.  This will floor
// each of the probs to 0.
var total : float = 0;

for (x in probs) {
    total += x;
}

var randomPoint = Random.value * total;

for(var i = 0; i &lt; probs.Count; i++) {
    if (randomPoint &lt; probs[i])
        return i;
    else
        // Shift the strip down, adjusting the random point's
        // value to see whether it falls within the next prob.
        randomPoint -= probs[i];
}
// Take care of possibility that randomPoint is 1.0 or 100% by
// returning the last element of probs.  Avoids allowing Choose to
// return a 0 probability event (which would be possible using the
// &lt;= test).
return probs.Count - 1;
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Now to choose an item:</p>

<p><code>javascript
var item = ents[Choose(areas["grassland"])];
Debug.Log(item);
</code></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all there is to it. I&rsquo;ve put an <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/ProbEntitySpawnExample">example Unity project with this code on github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Dictionary of Lists in Unity C#]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/create-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-c-sharp/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T11:16:28-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/create-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-c-sharp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript/">Last week</a>, I published an article about creating a Dictionary of Lists in Unity using Unity&rsquo;s JavaScript.  Some of the syntax is changed in C#, but the overall algorithm is exactly the same.  I&rsquo;ve already mentioned the underlying motive, so I&rsquo;ll dive right in.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&rsquo;s how to create a Dictionary of Lists in C# for Unity.</p>

<p>```csharp
Dictionary&lt;string, List<int>> table = new Dictionary&lt;string, List<int>>();</p>

<p>void Start() {</p>

<pre><code>// Fill our table with Lists containing ints using Arrays to intialize
// the Lists.
table["a"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){1};
table["b"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){2};
table["c"] = new List&lt;int&gt;(){3};

foreach(string str in table.Keys) {
    // Get the value for our Key.
    List&lt;int&gt; value = table[str];

    // If the Key is the desired Key, append to its list.
    if(str == "c") {
        value.Add(4);
    }

    // print the first item in each of the Lists.
    Debug.Log(value[0]);
}

// Print the appended item to see that it worked.
Debug.Log(table["c"][1]);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>These are the main differences between the Unity JavaScript and C# code.  Take a look at the full file in a <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/e3882aa5ffd5dd614c9a">gist on github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a Dictionary of Lists in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-13T11:14:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/06/13/creating-a-dictionary-of-lists-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ran into a few problems trying to create a <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DWhich_Kind_Of_Array_Or_Collection_Should_I_Use%253F#Generic_Dictionary">Dictionary</a> of <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DWhich_Kind_Of_Array_Or_Collection_Should_I_Use%253F#Generic_List">Lists</a> in Unity JavaScript.  So I thought I&rsquo;d share some of the tips I learned here.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;m interested in creating a Dictionary to hold <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Markov_text_generators">Markov Chain information</a> in order to generate text.  So I&rsquo;d like to be able to create a Dictionary holding a variable length of items for each of its Keys.  I&rsquo;d also like to be able to update the mapping at runtime.</p>

<p>It would look something like this:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Key1:</strong> Item1, Item2, Item3</li>
<li><strong>Key2:</strong> Item4</li>
</ul>


<p>At runtime, I&rsquo;d like to be able to say: &ldquo;Append <code>Item5</code> to <code>Key2</code>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what I came up with in Unity JavaScript.  I started out by initializing a <code>table</code> in my script prior to the <code>Start</code> function. The var <code>table</code> holds our mapping of Keys of type <code>String</code> to Values of type <code>List.&lt;int&gt;</code>, or Lists of integers.</p>

<p><code>javascript
import System.Collections.Generic;
// White space matters.
var table:Dictionary.&lt;String,List.&lt;int&gt; &gt; = new Dictionary.&lt;String,List.&lt;int&gt; &gt;();
</code></p>

<p>The first hiccup I ran into is that <a href="http://forum.unity3d.com/threads/80227-Creating-a-Dictionary-of-Lists-in-Javascript?p%3D513471&amp;viewfull%3D1#post513471">white space matters</a> when creating Generics in Unity JavaScript.  The compiler will throw an error if it sees two <code>&gt;&gt;</code> in a row.</p>

<p>Then I fill the table with our test mappings.</p>

<p><code>javascript
// Fill our table with Lists containing ints using Arrays to intialize
// the Lists.
table["a"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([1]);
table["b"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([2]);
table["c"] = new List.&lt;int&gt;([3]);
</code></p>

<p>As you can see, you can <a href="http://answers.unity3d.com/questions/221476/javascript-array-to-generic-list.html">construct a List from an Array</a>.  Cool.</p>

<p>In the <code>Start</code> function, I iterate over the Keys in the Dictionary, Add the item <code>4</code> to the Value of Key <code>c</code>, and print out the first item of each of the <code>values</code>.  Finally, we check to see whether <code>4</code> was appended to the desired entry.</p>

<p>```javascript
function Start () {</p>

<pre><code>// Iterate over the Keys in our Dictionary.
for(var str:String in table.Keys) {
    // Get the value for our Key.
    var value:List.&lt;int&gt; = table[str];

    // If the Key is our desired Key, append to its list.
    if (str == "c") {
        value.Add(4);
    }

    // Print the first item in each of the Lists.
    print(value[0]);
}

// Print the appended item to see that it worked.
print(table["c"][1]);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Then I attach this script to the Main Camera of a fresh Scene for testing purposes.  Bada bing, bada boom.</p>

<p>Attaching the script to any old object in the scene would work.  I just chose the Main Camera because the camera object is there by default.</p>

<p>This was all relatively straightforward, after I understood some of the quirks of Unity&rsquo;s JavaScript syntax.  You can find an example script using this code <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/f13eb62bf7bd57799db6">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prototyping Rectangles in Unity 2D for Dummy]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/30/prototyping-rectangles-in-unity-2d-for-dummy/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-30T09:57:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/30/prototyping-rectangles-in-unity-2d-for-dummy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Who&rsquo;s &ldquo;Dummy&rdquo;? I&rsquo;m the dummy.  Prototyping with 2d boxes in Unity JavaScript has proven surprisingly hard.  I think the difficulty I&rsquo;m having is that I&rsquo;m not exactly sure what I&rsquo;m trying to do.  What follows is an example of <strong>one</strong> way (notice that I didn&rsquo;t say THE <strong>RIGHT</strong> WAY) to prototype with 2d rectangles in Unity.  I&rsquo;m still too much of a noob to have strong opinions on the right way to go about doing this.  Expect more posts on this topic as I develop my expertise.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Discoverability">Discoverability</a> is something I prize in programming languages and environments, especially when I&rsquo;m learning them.  While Unity&rsquo;s documentation is thorough, the lack of congruence between the GUI environment and coding leads to poor discoverability.  There&rsquo;s not a one-to-one correspondence between the labels for <code>Components</code> in the GUI inspector and their names and attributes in code.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Most of the time, Google is my method for discovering new functionality in Unity.  The problem with this method, and even the documentation, is that I&rsquo;m never quite sure if the solution I&rsquo;ve found is the best solution, the only way to do something, or the wrong way to do something.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m trying to get simple rectangular boxes to work in Unity 2d for prototyping movement, hitboxes for attacks, etc.  The information I can find either deals with real-deal-Holyfield sprites or <code>GUIBoxes</code>.</p>

<p>It will be nice to work with <code>Sprites</code> eventually, but I just want to get a box that can walk around and jump, at this point.  <code>GUIBoxes</code> seem like the wrong type of boxes, if I want to prototype something that will eventually be a <code>Sprite</code>.</p>

<p>As near as I can tell, the <code>Sprite</code> is a (relatively) new way of making a flat 2D <code>Plane</code> in Unity.  I couldn&rsquo;t seem to find anything dealing with <code>Sprites</code> without creating them in the Unity GUI interface.</p>

<p>So, I started out following a Unity Answers question <a href="http://answers.unity3d.com/questions/139808/creating-a-plane-mesh-directly-from-code.html">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Getting the Mesh to gel</h2>

<p>First, I created a brand-spankin new Unity 2D project.  I had to create an empty <code>GameObject</code> to host my <code>PlaneTest.js</code> script <code>Component</code>.  I included a variable <code>size</code> to control the size of the box, so you can play around with that in the Editor interface.</p>

<p>Next, I had to create a <code>Mesh</code> that would be the actual geometry of the plane.  Now, the <code>Mesh</code> I&rsquo;m making differs from the stock Unity <code>Plane</code> <code>GameObject</code>.  <a href="http://www.third-helix.com/2012/02/making-2d-games-with-unity/">This blog post</a> shows that Unity&rsquo;s <code>Plane</code> defaults to a 10 x 10 quad mesh with a couple hundred triangles.  A quad is just a square made of two triangle faces, <a href="http://blog.nobel-joergensen.com/2010/12/25/procedural-generated-mesh-in-unity/">this blog post</a> goes into more detail.</p>

<p>Here we <a href="http://i.eho.st/pgtxqdii.gif">do it live</a> by defining a <code>name</code> <code>String</code>, an <code>array</code> of <code>Vector3</code> <code>vertices</code>, an <code>array</code> of <code>uv</code> texture coordinates, and an <code>array</code> of <code>triangles</code> faces.</p>

<p>``` js
var m: Mesh = new Mesh();
m.name = &ldquo;Scripted_Plane_New_Mesh&rdquo;;
m.vertices = [Vector3(-size, -size, 0.01),</p>

<pre><code>          Vector3(size, -size, 0.01),
          Vector3(size, size, 0.01),
          Vector3(-size, size, 0.01)];
</code></pre>

<p>m.uv = [Vector2(0, 0),</p>

<pre><code>    Vector2(0, 1),
    Vector2(1, 1),
    Vector2(1, 0)];
</code></pre>

<p>m.triangles = [0, 1, 2,</p>

<pre><code>           0, 2, 3];
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h2>Who you calling normal?</h2>

<p>At one point I thought I had to <code>RecalculateNormals</code>, according to the Unity Answers example above.  But it doesn&rsquo;t seem to make a difference.  Here&rsquo;s a great example of the Unity discoverability problem.  Since it doesn&rsquo;t <em>seem</em> to make a difference, I don&rsquo;t know whether to trust the Unity Answers that received 5 upvotes or to go with parsimony.</p>

<p>A little more digging <a href="http://forum.unity3d.com/threads/210399-4-3-Sprites-and-Lighting">reveals</a> that normal maps are particularly important for lighting.  Since the <code>Sprite Shader</code> I intend to use doesn&rsquo;t use normal maps, we can leave it out.</p>

<h2>OBJECTION!!</h2>

<p>Time to create the <code>GameObject</code> that will hold a <code>MeshRenderer</code>, <code>MeshFilter</code>, and <code>MeshCollider</code>.  According to the <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Documentation/Components/class-MeshFilter.html">docs</a>, a <code>MeshFilter</code> takes a mesh, like the one we created above, and passes it to the <code>MeshRenderer</code> for rendering to the screen.  Not sure what it&rsquo;s <em>filtering</em> or why there&rsquo;s an intermediate <code>Component</code>, but there you go.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Documentation/Components/class-MeshRenderer.html">docs</a> say the <code>MeshRenderer</code> then takes the geometry from the <code>MeshFilter</code> and renders it on the screen at the position defined by the <code>GameObject</code>&rsquo;s <code>Transform</code>.</p>

<p>``` js
var obj: GameObject = new GameObject(&ldquo;New_Plane_From_Script&rdquo;,</p>

<pre><code>                                 MeshRenderer,
                                 MeshFilter,
                                 MeshCollider);
</code></pre>

<p>obj.GetComponent(MeshFilter).mesh = m;
```</p>

<h2>Time for texture</h2>

<p>Next we create a <code>Texture2D</code> to hold the color information, to really give the box some panache.  The <code>Texture2D</code> goes into the <code>MeshRenderer</code>&rsquo;s <code>mainTexture</code> slot.</p>

<p><code>js
var texture: Texture2D;
texture = new Texture2D(size, size, TextureFormat.ARGB4444, false);
obj.renderer.material.mainTexture = texture;
</code></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know too much about how <code>Texture2D</code> works right now, but there&rsquo;s plenty to read in the <a href="http://docs.unity3d.com/Documentation/ScriptReference/Texture2D.html">docs</a>.</p>

<h2>A splash of color</h2>

<p>Here we generate some random RGB values, normalize them for Unity&rsquo;s <code>0.0-1.0</code> colorspace and make a <code>Color</code> to put into the <code>MeshRenderer</code>&rsquo;s color slot.</p>

<p><code>js
var red: float = Random.Range(63, 255) / 255f;
var green: float = Random.Range(63, 255) / 255f;
var blue: float = Random.Range(63, 255) / 255f;
var color = Color(red, green, blue);
obj.renderer.material.color = color;
</code></p>

<h2>The crucial shader</h2>

<p>At this point, I tested my code and got no errors. However, to my surprise I didn&rsquo;t see anything rendered on the screen.</p>

<p>I learned that I needed to use a <code>Sprite Shader</code> to get the colored mesh to render properly.  Here&rsquo;s how I did it:</p>

<p><code>js
var spriteShader: Shader = Shader.Find("Sprites/Default");
obj.renderer.material.shader = spriteShader;
</code></p>

<h2>Boxes for dummy</h2>

<p>I don&rsquo;t feel so dumb anymore because this was a complex process.  And it wasn&rsquo;t until the very last crucial step that I saw anything remotely box-like.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve posted the code to a gist <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/743cf797112d62978bec">here</a> so you can clone the script for yourself, to give it a whirl.  I found that setting <code>size</code> to 2 is a nice place to start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Dictionary with multiple keys in Unity C#]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T11:03:42-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/create-a-dictionary-with-multiple-keys-in-unity-c-number</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to create a lookup table for comparing a player choice and an enemy choice.  Each pair of choices can lead to a variety of outcomes.  So, in order to map the relationship between choice pair and outcome, I&rsquo;ve decided to use a Dictionary with choice pairs as keys and outcomes as values.</p>

<p>To me, the obvious way to do this is by using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuple">tuples</a> to encode the choice pairs.  I&rsquo;ve already enumerated the choices so it&rsquo;s simple enough to pair them off in tuples for use as keys for the Dictionary.  This approach worked, however, I ran into a couple of problems along the way.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Unity&rsquo;s C# doesn&rsquo;t have Tuples</h2>

<p>Unity&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mono_%2528software%2529">Mono framework</a> includes a C# compiler, runtime, and lots of libraries.  The version of Mono included with version <code>4.6.1f1</code> of Unity is <code>2.6.5 (tarball)</code>.  Mono recreates some of the features of .NET, but apparently not a <code>Tuple</code> type.  The <code>Tuple</code> type got added to .NET in version <code>4.0</code>.  Looks like Mono version <code>2.8</code> may support it, but I&rsquo;ll have to wait for the folks at Unity to update Mono.</p>

<p>I checked the version of Mono using the following code:</p>

<p>``` csharp Check Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono
using System;
using System.Reflection;</p>

<p>Type type = Type.GetType(&ldquo;Mono.Runtime&rdquo;);
if (type != null) {</p>

<pre><code>MethodInfo displayName = type.GetMethod("GetDisplayName",
                                        BindingFlags.NonPublic | BindingFlags.Static);
if (displayName != null)
  Debug.Log(displayName.Invoke(null, null));
</code></pre>

<p> }
```</p>

<p>Since Mono <code>2.8</code> was released 5 years ago, it seems like Unity is in no rush to update their Mono version.  So it looks like I&rsquo;ll have to roll my own tuple class.</p>

<h2>Implementing a Pairs class</h2>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m only concerned with pairs of choices, I decided to implement the simplest possible solution.  I followed the implementation of a <code>Pair</code> class from <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/569903/multi-value-dictionary">this Stack Overflow question regarding encoding multiple values in Dictionaries</a>.  The trick is that the tuple implemented here can be used to encode keys as well.</p>

<p>The critically important part of the <code>Pair</code> class is that it inherits from <code>IEquatable</code> and implements methods for determining equality and hashing.  The fundamental thing a Dictionary needs is to test whether keys are equal in order to store or retrieve the correct values and it typically does so by hashing the key.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t bother reproducing the code for the <code>Pair</code> class here.  You can <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/569920">check it out for yourself</a>.</p>

<h2>How I wish I could use it</h2>

<p>Once I implemented the <code>Pair</code> class in its own file <code>Pair.cs</code>, I had to import it in the file where I wanted to create the Dictionary.  Also note that I&rsquo;m <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb531208.aspx">using literal syntax to construct the Dictionary when I define it</a>.  And yes, unlike most uses of curly braces in C#, that <code>;</code> is necessary to end the line after the literal.</p>

<p>``` csharp
using Pair;</p>

<p>// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Pair&lt;Choice, Choice>, Outcome> {
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceOne), Outcome.Win},
  {Pair(Choice.ChoiceOne, Choice.ChoiceTwo), Outcome.Lose},
};</p>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Pair(ChoiceOne, ChoiceOne)];</p>

<p>// Compiler throws an error
```</p>

<p>But alas, I run into this error: <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code>.  I can&rsquo;t seem to find any documentation detailing what I&rsquo;m doing wrong.  Maybe it&rsquo;s just a problem with Unity&rsquo;s version of Mono .NET runtime.</p>

<h2>The workaround: A Dictionary of Dictionaries</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found a workaround.  It is, in my humble opinion, way less elegant, but it gets the job done.</p>

<p>``` csharp
// Not shown: lots of enums&hellip;</p>

<p>Dictionary&lt;Choice, Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome>> lookup = new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {
  {Choice.ChoiceOne, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Win},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Lose}
}},
</code></pre>

<p>  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, new Dictionary&lt;Choice, Outcome> {</p>

<pre><code>  {Choice.ChoiceOne, Outcome.Lose},
  {Choice.ChoiceTwo, Outcome.Win}
}}};
</code></pre>

<p>Outcome outcome = lookup[Choice.ChoiceOne][Choice.ChoiceOne];</p>

<p>// Will return Outcome.Win
```</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I find the tuple key code way more readable than the Dictionary of Dictionaries code.  You can imagine how the legibility of the Dictionary of Dictionaries approach decreases with additional keys but the tuple key code legibility remains the same no matter how many keys you add.  This is probably a moot point for using two keys, as I have in this example, but I hope you can appreciate why I think the tuple approach is more elegant.</p>

<p>If you have any insight into how to solve the <code>Using the generic type `Pair&lt;TFirst,TSecond&gt;' requires `2' type argument(s)</code> error I encountered using the <code>Pair</code> class, please let me know in the comments below or on <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
