<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Super Smash Bros. | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/super-smash-bros/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-02T09:59:53-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play balance for party vs in-depth fighting games]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/play-balance-for-party-vs-in-depth-fighting-games/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T08:33:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/play-balance-for-party-vs-in-depth-fighting-games</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here I&rsquo;m drawing a comparison between games that are subjectively perceived as party games and games that are more in-depth.  I&rsquo;m avoiding using loaded terms like casual and hardcore, but I think the distinction is likely the same.  Both types of games can be complex, but subtle balancing issues can affect the subjective sense of fun when playing these games.</p>

<p>For discussion I&rsquo;m going to focus on relatively advanced moves in <em><a href="http://www.smashbros.com">Super Smash Bros.</a></em> and <em><a href="http://www.towerfall-game.com/">TowerFall</a></em>: L-canceling and dodge canceling, respectively.  I was inspired to examine this balance issue by a recent tweet by <em>TowerFall</em> creator, and, in the interest of full disclosure, my close personal 3DS friend, <a href="https://twitter.com/MattThorson">@MattThorson</a>.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Thorson previously pointed out an interesting <a href="https://twitter.com/DamianSommer/status/519537228582633473">discussion</a> on the mechanic of L-canceling by <a href="https://twitter.com/DamianSommer/status/519537228582633473">@DamianSommer</a> among others. Sommer wants to focus on how the L-canceling mechanic reflects the design intent of the creators of <em>Super Smash Bros.</em></p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Sonic9jct">@Sonic9jct</a> highlights the dichotomy that I am exploring here.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p><a href="http://supersmashbros.wikia.com/wiki/L-canceling">L-canceling</a> requires extremely precise timing of inputs when the character is in a particular state.  You must press L within 6 frames of landing on the ground while performing an <a href="http://supersmashbros.wikia.com/wiki/Aerial_attack">aerial attack</a>.  Since <em>Super Smash Bros.</em> runs at 60 frames per second, this requires you to press the button within 100 milliseconds of hitting the ground.  To put this in perspective, the average human reaction time is about 250 milliseconds.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/whatisian">@whatisian</a> brilliantly captures the distinction in design that makes this a more difficult, in-depth, technically demanding mechanic.  If there is no drawback, then the execution of the L-cancel is practically mandatory at high levels of play.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at how this differs from <a href="http://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id%3D250779585">dodge canceling</a> in <em>TowerFall</em> a game that Thorson intentionally designed to be welcoming to new players, while still keeping them competitive with skilled players.</p>

<p>Dodge canceling requires similarly herculean inputs to pull off, to perform a dodge cancel you must press the dodge button a second time after initiating a dodge maneuver.  The dodge lasts 367 milliseconds or 22 frames at 60 fps.  This seems like a lot of time to perform the dodge cancel compared to the scant 6 frames for an L-cancel, but there&rsquo;s a catch.  In order to get the most momentum, to carry the most speed through the dodge cancel, you must perform the move on exactly the right frame.</p>

<p>Sounds pretty tough, right?  If you think this would require some impressive technical skills to pull it off, you&rsquo;re right.  But there&rsquo;s a catch, turning or firing from the dodge cancel reduces the character&rsquo;s speed, making the character an easier target.</p>

<p>Thorson&rsquo;s mechanic provides a similar advantage to L-canceling with the addition of the risk of failure.  Dodge cancels could allow the player to zing around the level at will, firing arrows every which way, but Thorson decided to introduce drawbacks for imprecise play that create risks for more advanced players to put them closer to parity with less skilled players.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>These are just my thoughts on this interesting discussion.  I&rsquo;m not a high-level player of either of these games, so I may have missed some of the subtleties to which Thorson or others refer.  If you think I&rsquo;m off the mark, or you just want to weigh in on the merits of designing for &ldquo;party&rdquo; vs. &ldquo;fighting&rdquo; games, drop me a line in the comments or on <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Betting in Super Smash Bros. spectator mode]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/11/betting-in-super-smash-bros-spectator-mode/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T06:51:13-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/11/betting-in-super-smash-bros-spectator-mode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&rsquo;d like to look at how to bet in the spectator mode of <em>Super Smash Bros. on 3DS</em>.  I&rsquo;m surprised by how much I enjoy /Super Smash Bros.&lsquo;/ spectator mode.  It adds the thrill of a horse race alongside an already great game.</p>

<p>Here are some of the betting strategies I&rsquo;ve found useful:</p>

<ul>
<li>Always bet the full amount</li>
<li>Always bet your earnings</li>
<li>Bet the odds</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to take your money and run</li>
<li>Know the metagame</li>
<li>Know the good players, you may see them again.</li>
<li>Set limits</li>
<li>Trust your judgment</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<h2>Always bet the full amount</h2>

<p>Any winnings will offset your losses from betting the full amount.  You stand to multiply your winnings, if you bet your earnings.  And the larger your initial bet, the larger your potential winnings will be at the end of three rounds.</p>

<h2>Always bet your earnings</h2>

<p>Betting your earnings allows you to place a bet that is larger than the normal cap of 100 gold.  Keep in mind that you only stand to lose your initial 100 gold bet from your gold reserve, so this is a pretty good deal.</p>

<p>I tend to play the odds more conservatively when betting my earnings, but I&rsquo;m not sure it&rsquo;s completely necessary.  Again, you only stand to lose 100 from your cash reserves, so there&rsquo;s little risk associated with these bets.</p>

<h2>Bet the odds</h2>

<p>The payout odds shown next to a gold coin above the character portraits are there for a reason.  The odds vary from 2.0 to 10.0, meaning that you will receive 200 to 1000 gold payout for a 100 gold bet.  The favored player, that is to say the player with the lowest payout multiplier, is likely to win a given match, according to the game&rsquo;s algorithm.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t be afraid to take your money and run</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to bet your earnings, but you shouldn&rsquo;t let that persuade you to make a bad bet.  If you&rsquo;re on a winning streak and you come across a match with no obvious good bet, hit <code>B</code> to take your money and run.  You can always bet on a different match.  It&rsquo;s not worth risking all of the winnings from a streak on a relatively even match.  I&rsquo;ve lost a lot of gold this way, not from my reserve gold, mind you, but still a lot of winnings.</p>

<h2>Know the metagame</h2>

<p>The game just came out, so the metagame is likely still forming.  But there is still useful information available.</p>

<p>For example consider Conquest, the in-game periodic match up between characters recording the win-loss record of nearly everyone who plays them.  Character choice may trump the odds of there is a significant influence of the meta game. In other words, some characters are just OP especially relative to specific other characters.  The Conquest match ups are good indicators that certain characters are OP compared to others.</p>

<p>For the record, Duck Hunt seems pretty OP.</p>

<h3>Know the good players, you may see them again</h3>

<p>Pay attention to the names of the players in the matches you bet on.  You may see the same player, and even the same match ups, popping up again and again.  If a player seems to be highly skilled, go with that player on subsequent matches.</p>

<h2>Set limits</h2>

<p>Set a loss floor and a win ceiling.  Take breaks when you reach those limits.  <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21915653">Fatigue can affect your judgment</a>.  (Don&rsquo;t worry, I don&rsquo;t have access to the Journal of Gambling Studies either&mdash;the abstract sums up what you need to know).  And anyway, it&rsquo;s good to keep a nestegg so you have a bankroll for your future bets.</p>

<h2>Trust your judgment</h2>

<p>If you have a hunch that goes against the odds that the game presents you go for it.  If you&rsquo;re following the rule of setting limits, your judgment should be fresh and not fatigued, and you will not go too deep into the hole when taking risks.  The only time when I would not advocate risky bets is when continuing bets&mdash;there&rsquo;s too much to lose on a risky bet.  (Yes I know this goes against what I said before.  I&rsquo;m a hypocrite.)</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>These are just my thoughts on betting strategy in <em>Super Smash Bros. for 3DS</em>.  These strategies have worked for me, but of course, your mileage may vary.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m interested in starting a dialog about these and other strategies because I find the spectator mode deeply compelling.  So if you agree, disagree, or have other strategies that work for you, feel free to contact me either by leaving a comment on the post or hitting me up on twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
