<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mechanics | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/mechanics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-25T09:31:49-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Skytorn Raycast Lighting Algorithm Details]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-16T11:10:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn/">Last week</a> I covered the lighting algorithm <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB">@NoelFB</a> is implementing for <a href="http://skytorngame.com/">Skytorn</a>.  Noel was nice enough to correct my mistaken assumptions about the inner workings of the lighting algorithm.</p>

<p>Looks like I kind of inverted the polarity of the raycasting with regard to the player and the level geometry.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The algorithm</h2>

<p>The algorithm doesn&rsquo;t raycast in the full 360° circle around player&#x2013;that would be too costly.  Instead, it takes advantage of the fact that the level&rsquo;s ground collision geometry is stored in a grid.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Given the player&rsquo;s location, there is a small list of collision geometry in the 8 or so grid cells surrounding the player.</p></li>
<li><p>The lighting algorithm raycasts from the corners of the level geometry to the player, instead of from the player out to the geometry.</p></li>
<li><p>Then, to prevent the lighting from looking too triangular, the algorithm adds a few more raycasts out from the player to the geometry in between the other raycasts.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>That&rsquo;s actually all there is to it</h2>

<p>The algorithm I originally envisioned was naive and costly.  But, it&rsquo;s nice to hear that I wasn&rsquo;t far off&#x2013;I simply inverted the solution.  It was also nice to learn about a benefit of storing level geometry in a grid that I previously failed to appreciate.</p>

<p>Heaping thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/">@NoelFB</a> for helping explain the algorithm, instead of getting bent out of shape about my lame attempt to reverse engineer the inner workings of <a href="http://skytorn-game.com/">Skytorn</a> from a screenshot.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raycast Lighting in Skytorn]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-09T09:21:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/09/raycast-lighting-in-skytorn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/">@NoelFB</a> posted a <a href="https://twitter.com/NoelFB/status/543586120731074561/photo/1">screenshot</a> showing how dynamic lighting works in <a href="http://skytorn-game.com/">Skytorn</a>.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The algorithm</h2>

<p>From what I can tell, the algorithm looks something like this:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Raycast out for 360° around the light source, starting in a clockwise direction.  If the rays encounter a collidable object, add it to the list of pink lines defining the polygonal shape of the lit area.  If the ray exceeds the distance of the light gradient, clamp the triangle edge defining the pink line at that distance.</p></li>
<li><p>For each of the collidable objects encountered, extend a ray past their vertices until it hits another collidable to create the obscured lighting effect visible to down and to the right of the light source.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally construct a set of triangles by starting from the closest edge in the list defining the pink lines to form the polygon.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>That&rsquo;s all</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week.  Let me know if you have any insight into this or other lighting algorithms in the comments or on the tweets.</p>

<h2>Update</h2>

<p>After some feedback from @NoelFB, I&rsquo;ve updated the algorithm in the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/16/more-skytorn-raycast-lighting-algorithm-details/">following post</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math Team Hearts]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-14T14:14:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Math Team Hearts is a speedy modification to Hearts that ironically involves less math than the vanilla game.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From <a href="http://www.crcpress.com/product/isbn/9781482217162">Game Design Workshop</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/kinojabber">Tracy Fullerton</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>One good way to train yourself in the design of game mechanics is to challenge yourself with controlled design exercises in which you take an existing game system, set a new player experience goal, and make changes to the system to meet that goal.</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Goal</h2>

<p>We needed a game that played quickly, without a defined endpoint (e.g. when one player reaches 100 points in normal <em>Hearts</em>) because this game was played in free time waiting for school to start or waiting for the bus.  There was no time to spend tallying up scores, counting hearts and doing awkward math.</p>

<p>The rules also modify the risk-reward value of shooting the moon to make it more attractive.  We found the game to be more interesting when multiple parties were invested in shooting the moon with less drawback from accumulating hearts.</p>

<h2>The Rules</h2>

<p>The game plays like normal <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hearts">Hearts</a></em>, except taking <strong>hearts</strong> no longer gives you points.</p>

<ul>
<li>Taking any number of <strong>hearts</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you 0 points.</li>
<li>Taking no <strong>hearts</strong> in a round gives you 1 point.</li>
<li><strong>Shooting the moon</strong> gives you 2 points.</li>
<li>Taking the <strong>queen of spades</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you -1 point.</li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>player</strong> with the most points at the end of play wins.</p>

<p>For more variety, use <strong>dealer</strong>&rsquo;s choice drafting rules.  Each round, the <strong>dealer</strong> decides on how players will pass cards prior to play.
<strong>Players</strong> take turns dealing.</p>

<h2>Tweaks</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m working from memory, so I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve got the point values exactly right.  Perhaps there should be more of a penalty for taking the Queen without shooting the moon.  That would create a more exciting risk-reward trade-off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple Mind-reading Machine in Unity JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T14:38:20-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/13/simple-mind-reading-machine-in-unity-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I ported a cool toy from <a href="http://alastaira.wordpress.com/2014/03/15/a-simple-mind-reading-machine/">Alastair Aitchison&rsquo;s blog</a> to Unity JavaScript.  The toy implements a simple &lsquo;mind-reading&rsquo; algorithm that attempts to guess whether the player will choose Left (by pressing the left arrow key) or Right (by pressing the right arrow key).</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>How does it work?</h2>

<p>Aitchison&rsquo;s blog post describes how it works:</p>

<blockquote><p>How does it work? Not by mind-reading, obviously, but by exploiting
the fact that humans do not behave as &ldquo;randomly&rdquo; as they think they
do. The computer maintains a very simple memory that records the
pattern of results of the last two rounds – whether the player won or
lost, whether they switched strategy, and then whether they then won
or last the following round. The computer then uses this to choose its
own best strategy based on the way the player behaved last time the
current pattern occurred. If the computer loses twice in a row using
the current strategy, it picks a random response in the next round.</p></blockquote>

<p>The original idea came from some AI work by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_Shannon">Claude Shannon</a> and D. W. Hagelbarger. <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/people/eroberts/courses/soco/projects/1999-00/information-theory/ai.html">They describe the internal memory of the toy mind-reader</a> that we will model using a multidimensional array <code>v</code>:</p>

<blockquote><p>There are 8 possible situations and two things the player can do at each one:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays same, loses. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, wins. Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player wins, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays same, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, wins.Then same or differently.</p></li>
<li><p>player loses, plays differently, loses.Then same or differently.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<h2>Why port it?</h2>

<p>Why not just take a straightforward approach, running the code myself? First, I wanted to fully understand the algorithm the hard way, by coding it line for line myself. And second, I wanted to better familiarize myself with Unity JavaScript, including its differences from C#.</p>

<p>The port was relatively simple, except for two small hiccups.  First, as far as I know, Unity JavaScript doesn&rsquo;t allow for initializing a multidimensional array.  So I looped over the cells in the array, filling them that way.  I have a hunch that the cells are initialized to the <code>int</code> <code>0</code> by default, but I wanted to be explicit.  Please let me know in the comments or <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">via twitter</a> if I&rsquo;m way off base.</p>

<pre><code>var v : int[2, 2, 2];
for(var cell in v) {
    cell = 0;
}
</code></pre>

<p>I also encountered some unfamiliar syntax: the sonorously named Elvis operator, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_operator">?:</a>.  It&rsquo;s also called the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternary_operation">ternary operator</a>, when it&rsquo;s used with 3 arguments, as I&rsquo;ve used it here.  In C-like languages it allows for succinctly stating these kinds of conditional expressions. The example below illustrates how it&rsquo;s used.</p>

<pre><code>// Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
// choice?
//
// if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
//     sameChoice = True;
// else
//     sameChoice = False;
//
// Using ternary operator:
v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
</code></pre>

<h2>The code</h2>

<p>The ported code for the mind-reader is reproduced below.</p>

<pre><code>#pragma strict
import System.Collections.Generic;

// Used to record play history
var v: int[,,];
var lw1: int;
var lw2: int;
var losingStreak: int;

// The prediction of the player's next turn
var prediction: int;

// Keep track of scores
var cpuScore: int;
var playerScore: int;

var outText: String;

function Start () {
    // Initialize matrix to track state of play history

    v = new int[2, 2, 2];

    for(var cell in v) {
        cell = 0;
    }

    // No prior knowledge, so set inital prediction based on random chance.
    prediction = flip();

    // Set scores to 0
    cpuScore = 0;
    playerScore = 0;

    // Initialize previous play and play before last win-lost trackers
    lw1 = 0;
    lw2 = 0;

    // Output
    outText = "";
}

function TakeTurn(playerChoice: int) {
    // Display player and computer's choices
    var outTextString: String = "You pressed " + playerChoice + ", " + "I guessed " + prediction + "\n";

    // Computer guessed correctly
    if (playerChoice == prediction) {
        cpuScore++;
        losingStreak = 0;
        outTextString += " I WIN!\n";
    }
    else {
        playerScore++;
        losingStreak++;
        outTextString += " YOU WIN!\n";
    }

    outText = outTextString;

    // Is the current player's choice the same as the previous player's
    // choice?
    //
    // if (playerChoice == lastChoice)
    //     sameChoice = True;
    // else
    //     sameChoice = False;
    //
    // Using ternary operator:
    v[lw2, lw1, 1] = (v[lw2, lw1, 0] == playerChoice ? 1 : 0);
    v[lw2, lw1, 0] = playerChoice;
    lw2 = lw1;
    lw1 = playerChoice;

    // If lost more than twice in present state, choose random
    // strategy.  Otherwise keep the same strategy.
    prediction = v[lw2, lw1, 1] == 1 &amp;&amp; losingStreak &lt; 2 ? v[lw2, lw1, 0] : flip();
}

function flip() : int {
    // Simulate a coin flip to produce 50:50 chance of [0, 1]
    return Random.Range(0, 2);
}


function Update () {
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.LeftArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(0);
    }
    if (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.RightArrow)) {
        TakeTurn(1);
    }
}

function OnGUI() {
    var style : GUIStyle = new GUIStyle();
    style.fontSize = 36;

    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 0, Screen.width, 100), outText, style);
    GUI.Label(new Rect(0, 100, Screen.width, 200), "Player: " + playerScore + " CPU: " + cpuScore, style);
}
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Procjam review]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T09:33:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking through the entries, I could only spend a minute or two with each entry.  It helped if the game ran in my browser, so HTML and Unity were big.  Here are some of the games that caught my eye.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The top two</h2>

<h2>JET/LAG</h2>

<p>Simple instructions: &ldquo;Click to move. Kill enemies by bashing them.&rdquo;  There may be little to <em><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a></em>, but its excellent stylish visuals set this entry apart for me.  A CRT-like distortion bends the corners of the screen complete with scrolling scan lines, while multi-colored text oscillates above a simple square.  The simple square is your character battering your way through procedurally generated maze-like levels.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no fancy art in this game, all the characters are made from simple shapes.  But that doesn&rsquo;t stop the graphics from impressing.  It&rsquo;s clear that <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> turned the juice up to 11, and it works.  The game feels great.</p>

<p>As a &ldquo;rogue-like like like&rdquo; you may expect it to be deviously hard, and you&rsquo;d be right.  But the controls are responsive and the enemies telegraph their moves, so you feel like you are learning something with each death.  <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> clearly understands some fundamentals of engaging game design and I&rsquo;m excited to see what&rsquo;s coming up next.</p>

<h2>DUNGEN [star]</h2>

<p>A multi-jam entry for <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam</a>, <a href="http://itch.io/jam/paper-jam-1">#paperjam</a>, and <a href="http://7dfps.com/">#7dfps</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a>, this first person shooter uses shuffling to generate a dynamic dungeon with each play-through.  I like the simplicity of the mechanics <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a> has designed.  Stats on a 1-10 scale can be just as interesting as stats in the thousands.  There are even multiple skin options for the protagonist&rsquo;s hand.  That&rsquo;s more advanced than all three <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_%2528series%2529">DOOM</a></em>s.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;m most interested in the literal realization of the procedural generation algorithm.  By shuffling the cards the procedural generation of the dungeon is clear both to designer and player, and this type of randomization has been used for many years in many games with standard and nonstandard sets of cards.  I&rsquo;m interested in seeing how this shuffling mechanic, both literal and metaphorical, can be leveraged to encourage new avenues of play in the future.  I can imagine tuning some aspects of a proc gen algorithm by exposing the contents to the player as a deck of cards, both literally as is typical in CCGs and other tabletop games and as a metaphor for abstraction of systems in a video game.</p>

<h2>Favorite games</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a>

<ul>
<li>Bump or get bumped.  Excellent style and great graphics.  Very
juicy!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://lissar.itch.io/peregrin">Peregrin</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://entropyphi.itch.io/nauticalith">Nauticalith</a>

<ul>
<li>Simple, but really conveys a sense of scale.  Adding some mechanic
like dynamic wind that affects sailing could put this over the
top.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tfurmanskigmailcom.itch.io/forska-web-version">Forska</a>

<ul>
<li>Great shader.  Generate some <em><a href="http://wikipedia.com/wiki/Myst">Myst</a></em>-like puzzles and you&rsquo;ve got a game, here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://8-bit-ape.itch.io/infinity-explorer">Infinity Explorer</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_Carpet_%28video_game%29">Magic Carpet</a></em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN star</a>

<ul>
<li>Print and play games are great.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Favorite generators</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer">http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer</a>

<ul>
<li>Interesting.  Will have to look more into it.  Now that I think
about it, this one deserves an honorable mention for favorite tool
of the jam.  I will revisit it in depth in a later post because the
generation algorithm looks like an idea I&rsquo;ve batted around in my
head.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/">http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful and cool!  Check out <a href="http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora">http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora</a>
for some more background on this space colony generator.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics">http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics</a>

<ul>
<li>Clever tiling textures using diagonal lines that really break up
the patterns to make it more pleasing to the eye.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters">http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters</a>

<ul>
<li>Artistic style.  Simple color palette still allow for a variety of
expressive monsters. Interested in following up on the
procedural tree generation–looks great!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia">https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful world generator with some source code worth digging
into.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla">http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla</a>

<ul>
<li>Really think there&rsquo;s something to explore in pixels-as-stitches
graphics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch">http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch</a>

<ul>
<li>The pet rock generator I always wanted!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator">http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer">http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer</a>

<ul>
<li>Weird hybrid between an AI and a text adventure, but very
  creative and very cool.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026">http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026</a>

<ul>
<li>Great concept, but I need remedial lessons or a tutorial.  One to
revisit when I can really dig into it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cool looking Windows games I couldn&rsquo;t play</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist">http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wonderful_101">Wonderful 101</a></em>–a game I haven&rsquo;t played, but probably should.  Something about the aesthetic of dozens of little flocking characters appeals to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://caseportman.itch.io/riser">http://caseportman.itch.io/riser</a>

<ul>
<li>Looks like it controls well</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
