<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mechanics | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/mechanics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-26T09:17:51-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Space Is Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-26T09:08:44-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The cinematically inspired <a href="http://tdlk.itch.io/space-is-red">Space Is Red</a> is not so much a game as it is a visual novel.  Out of the games I tried from the <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">#spacecowboygamejam</a>, it&rsquo;s one that sticks with me.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>On the spectrum of play, these sorts of games are loosely analogous to Choose Your Own Adventure books.  Just as a Choose Your Own Adventure book expects the player to turn to a given page according to the rules laid out at the bottom of the pages to proceed in a consistent, logical fashion, the tropes of a visual novel require the player to interact with the game in order for the story to proceed.  A novel will proceed with the only &lsquo;player&rsquo; interaction consisting of turning to the next page.  I&rsquo;m oversimplifying the difference between <em>real choices</em>, as I would argue, Choose Your Own Adventure Books allow, and <em>mere interactivity</em>, like turning the page of a novel, but you get what I mean.</p>

<p>Visual novels can have real choices and interactivity.  In this case, I&rsquo;d argue that Space Is Red is only interactive.  There are no real choices, short of figuring out the next bit to tap on in order to move the story along.  For me, it&rsquo;s the music that makes the experience gel as something more than an animated e-book.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to be presumptuous in my analysis of Space Is Red&rsquo;s gameplay, don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  I&rsquo;m not interested in arguments about merit simply based on A <strong>is</strong> a game but B <strong>isn&rsquo;t</strong>, so A is better.  I just think it&rsquo;s important to think about these sorts of things when considering the underlying design.</p>

<p>I left the game looping <a href="https://soundcloud.com/postpre">PostPre&rsquo;s</a> driving soundtrack for 15 minutes, even though my first play-through lasted only 2 or 3.  Maybe that&rsquo;s the benefit of interactivity and choices, to extend and prolong the mindshare of some experience or product with the player.  I don&rsquo;t necessarily mean that in a cynical way, although the typical model of play can be subverted for more manipulative means (and, of course, it is!).</p>

<p>For me, Space Is Red hit all the right notes and left me with something to think about.  That is what I call a successful gamejam game.  You can see Space Is Red and the other #spacecowboygamejam entries <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">here</a>.  If you&rsquo;re interested in learning more about Space Is Red&rsquo;s creator <a href="http://toddluke.com/">Todd Luke</a>, you can find an interview <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/TalhaKaya/20140711/220825/Finding_Beauty_in_Imperfection_Interview_with_Todd_Luke.php">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why you should start simple]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T11:58:34-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/hobbygamedev">@HobbyGameDev&rsquo;s</a> long-read <a href="http://www.hobbygamedev.com/beg/incremental-learning/">&ldquo;Reasons for Modest First Projects and Incremental Learning&rdquo;</a> tells the tragic tale of overambitious novice developers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In a response to a doubting tweeter, HGD advocates starting modestly to slowly build skills, so that you can tackle more complicated projects later on.  Avoiding overambitious projects that are way outside of your comfort zone is one of the stumbling points for novice and hobby game developers, like myself.</p>

<p>In the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">previous post about Hammock Driven Creativity</a>, I highlighted Rich Hickey&rsquo;s suggestion to keep multiple projects going in order to avoid stagnation.  While I agree with this, it&rsquo;s important to judge the scope of those projects with a critical eye.</p>

<p>Far too often, my ideas start, at least in my mind, with ambitious artwork, animation, and multiple complex combinations of mechanics.  I am neither talented nor skilled enough to pull these projects off.  So it&rsquo;s easy to get stuck.</p>

<p>I often find myself implementing some ad-hoc animation system, spending time reinventing the frame-based or skeletal wheel, as it were.  Animation shouldn&rsquo;t take priority, especially considering that my best artwork is derivative and possibly one step above programmer art.  I should focus on creating compelling prototypes, and worry about polish later.</p>

<p>To build your skillset, HGD suggests starting out by remaking historical games.  By implementing tried-and-true mechanics that are necessarily simple in scope given their ancient hardware, you can confront the problems involved in creating a full game rather than a half-finished proof-of-concept.</p>

<p>By half-finished, I&rsquo;m thinking of a time where I completely abandoned a concept because I was hung-up on optimizing a tile-based room system.  Rather than making the actual gameplay fun and complete, I was focusing all of my time figuring out how to make walls.  Walls are nice in a finished game, and you could make the case that they are required constraints to achieve good gameplay, but they are not where the fun is.  As HGD and my previous post point out, you can keep trying to work on these overly ambitious projects, but your productivity will suffer.</p>

<p>Best to reap the rewards that come from continued productivity and, as HGD says, pick a fight you can win.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[styx_ebooks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T12:05:03-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And now for something completely different: a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Markov_text_generators">markov chain text generation</a> twitter bot.  Styx_ebooks tweets random text generated from a corpus of Bangsian fantasy novels.  Its name comes from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Kendrick_Bangs">John Kendrick Bangs</a>&lsquo; novel <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_House-Boat_on_the_Styx">A House-boat on the Styx</a></em> and the general <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/horse_ebooks">twitter ebooks meme</a>.</p>

<p>I forked it from an earlier project by <a href="https://github.com/jiko">@jiko</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jiko/lovecraft_ebooks">lovecraft_ebooks</a>.  There were some minor implementation hurdles, mainly related to Twitter&rsquo;s API and oauth.  Reading the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/twitter">python <code>twitter</code> package</a> <code>twitter.oauth</code> docstring set me straight.  You can check out the code in <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/styx_ebooks">my fork on github</a>.</p>

<p>This sort of text generation algorithm isn&rsquo;t just useful for making annoying twitter bots.  You could alter some of the in-game text or dialog based on a corpus fed into a markov chain text generator. Especially in the case of a Lovecraftian horror game, I can see how this text could serve a thematic purpose in the story.</p>

<p>Say you&rsquo;ve got a Lovecraftian horror game in which the player is an investigator who is trying to figure out what is happening to citizens of Innsmouth.  By interacting with NPCs, the player encounters hand written dialog, with occasional markov-generated gibberish thrown in. The amount of gibberish depends on how corrupted the individual denizens of Innsmouth are becoming.  If the player is not clever enough to determine who is corrupt, the player will be killed.  If the player determines the source of the corruption, the player wins.</p>

<p>Along the same line of reasoning, the concept I&rsquo;m describing here mimics the game <a href="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/634905">ALZ</a>, a touching short, playable in 2 or 3 minutes, which uses glitchy graphics to convey a sense of what it&rsquo;s like to live with Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease to the player.  I came across Dylan Carter&rsquo;s ALZ in a <a href="http://www.animalnewyork.com/2014/making-alz-glitch-fueled-game-alzheimers/">post on the ANIMAL blog</a>.  This approach of literally altering the player&rsquo;s experience of the game world to mimic the subjective experience of characters in the game is ripe for exploration.  I&rsquo;d love to hear about more examples.</p>

<p>You can check out my bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>, on twitter, happily tweeting the day away.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Fear Lack of Content]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/05/dont-fear-lack-of-content/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-05T07:59:37-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/05/dont-fear-lack-of-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Came across a <a href="http://www.egometry.com/gruedorf/a-penny-for-your-thoughts-a-hundred-for-your-life/">nice article</a> on <a href="http://www.egometry.com/">Ben McGraw&rsquo;s blog, Egometry</a>. Using Super Mario Bros. as a model, Ben explains why merely increasing content quantity is less desirable than increasing content substance.  The title of this post is lifted from a quote in his article.</p>

<p>Sometimes exercising a bit of restraint, keeping the focus of your content simple, can still allow for an interesting and engaging player experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An in-depth tour of Tetris]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/an-in-depth-tour-of-tetris/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T06:34:35-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/an-in-depth-tour-of-tetris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/a/ae/Tetris_NES_play.png">http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/a/ae/Tetris_NES_play.png</a>"></p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> Image from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris">wikipedia.org</a>.</p>

<p>This week I&rsquo;ve spent quite some time reading
<a href="http://meatfighter.com/nintendotetrisai/">this article</a> on
<a href="http://meatfighter.com/">MeatFighter.com</a>.  The article reverse
engineers the inner-workings of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris#NES">NES Tetris</a>.  With superb
visual aids, the author, o__1<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> , surveys the mechanics and data
structures used to implement Tetris on the NES.  Then o__1 designs
and implements an AI script to play Tetris with super-human speed and
precision.  o__1 even describes how to try it at home, providing
instructions and the necessary Lua scripts to run the AI on your own
copy of Tetris.</p>

<p>I hope to see more articles looking back on classic games with this
tremendous attention to detail.  An older
<a href="http://home.comcast.net/~jpittman2/pacman/pacmandossier.html">article looking at Pac-man AI</a>
shows similar obsessive depth.  Articles like these help supplement
our appreciation of these games as works of art by documenting the
essential technical complexities underlying these games.  I think
that&rsquo;s a good thing for everyone from hobby developers to professional
developers, as well as designers and fans.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I&rsquo;m referring to the author by the contact email listed on the website.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
