<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mechanics | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/mechanics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-26T10:14:22-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[styx_ebooks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T14:05:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And now for something completely different: a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Markov_text_generators">markov chain text generation</a> twitter bot.  Styx_ebooks tweets random text generated from a corpus of Bangsian fantasy novels.  Its name comes from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Kendrick_Bangs">John Kendrick Bangs</a>&lsquo; novel <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_House-Boat_on_the_Styx">A House-boat on the Styx</a></em> and the general <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/horse_ebooks">twitter ebooks meme</a>.</p>

<p>I forked it from an earlier project by <a href="https://github.com/jiko">@jiko</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jiko/lovecraft_ebooks">lovecraft_ebooks</a>.  There were some minor implementation hurdles, mainly related to Twitter&rsquo;s API and oauth.  Reading the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/twitter">python <code>twitter</code> package</a> <code>twitter.oauth</code> docstring set me straight.  You can check out the code in <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/styx_ebooks">my fork on github</a>.</p>

<p>This sort of text generation algorithm isn&rsquo;t just useful for making annoying twitter bots.  You could alter some of the in-game text or dialog based on a corpus fed into a markov chain text generator. Especially in the case of a Lovecraftian horror game, I can see how this text could serve a thematic purpose in the story.</p>

<p>Say you&rsquo;ve got a Lovecraftian horror game in which the player is an investigator who is trying to figure out what is happening to citizens of Innsmouth.  By interacting with NPCs, the player encounters hand written dialog, with occasional markov-generated gibberish thrown in. The amount of gibberish depends on how corrupted the individual denizens of Innsmouth are becoming.  If the player is not clever enough to determine who is corrupt, the player will be killed.  If the player determines the source of the corruption, the player wins.</p>

<p>Along the same line of reasoning, the concept I&rsquo;m describing here mimics the game <a href="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/634905">ALZ</a>, a touching short, playable in 2 or 3 minutes, which uses glitchy graphics to convey a sense of what it&rsquo;s like to live with Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease to the player.  I came across Dylan Carter&rsquo;s ALZ in a <a href="http://www.animalnewyork.com/2014/making-alz-glitch-fueled-game-alzheimers/">post on the ANIMAL blog</a>.  This approach of literally altering the player&rsquo;s experience of the game world to mimic the subjective experience of characters in the game is ripe for exploration.  I&rsquo;d love to hear about more examples.</p>

<p>You can check out my bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>, on twitter, happily tweeting the day away.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Fear Lack of Content]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/05/dont-fear-lack-of-content/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-05T09:59:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/05/dont-fear-lack-of-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Came across a <a href="http://www.egometry.com/gruedorf/a-penny-for-your-thoughts-a-hundred-for-your-life/">nice article</a> on <a href="http://www.egometry.com/">Ben McGraw&rsquo;s blog, Egometry</a>. Using Super Mario Bros. as a model, Ben explains why merely increasing content quantity is less desirable than increasing content substance.  The title of this post is lifted from a quote in his article.</p>

<p>Sometimes exercising a bit of restraint, keeping the focus of your content simple, can still allow for an interesting and engaging player experience.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An in-depth tour of Tetris]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/an-in-depth-tour-of-tetris/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T08:34:35-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/08/an-in-depth-tour-of-tetris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/a/ae/Tetris_NES_play.png">http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/a/ae/Tetris_NES_play.png</a>"></p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> Image from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris">wikipedia.org</a>.</p>

<p>This week I&rsquo;ve spent quite some time reading
<a href="http://meatfighter.com/nintendotetrisai/">this article</a> on
<a href="http://meatfighter.com/">MeatFighter.com</a>.  The article reverse
engineers the inner-workings of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetris#NES">NES Tetris</a>.  With superb
visual aids, the author, o__1<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> , surveys the mechanics and data
structures used to implement Tetris on the NES.  Then o__1 designs
and implements an AI script to play Tetris with super-human speed and
precision.  o__1 even describes how to try it at home, providing
instructions and the necessary Lua scripts to run the AI on your own
copy of Tetris.</p>

<p>I hope to see more articles looking back on classic games with this
tremendous attention to detail.  An older
<a href="http://home.comcast.net/~jpittman2/pacman/pacmandossier.html">article looking at Pac-man AI</a>
shows similar obsessive depth.  Articles like these help supplement
our appreciation of these games as works of art by documenting the
essential technical complexities underlying these games.  I think
that&rsquo;s a good thing for everyone from hobby developers to professional
developers, as well as designers and fans.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I&rsquo;m referring to the author by the contact email listed on the website.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some thoughts on Attack of the Friday Monsters]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/01/some-thoughts-on-attack-of-the-friday-monsters/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-01T08:32:40-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/02/01/some-thoughts-on-attack-of-the-friday-monsters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s hard to say anything new about Attack of the Friday Monsters, a
game that splashed on the scene months ago.  The work of its creator
was lovingly lauded by <a href="https://twitter.com/rdbaaa">Ray Barnholt</a>&#x2013;a noted <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boku_no_Natsuyasumi">Boku no Natsuyasumi</a></em>
fanatic&#x2013;in such a reverent way in his <a href="http://scroll.vg/issues/10">SCROLL magazine</a> that it&rsquo;s
almost sacrilegious to try to write more.  So instead of doing a
point-by-point review, I&rsquo;ll mention some details that stand out to me,
personally.</p>

<p>I played through most of Attack of the Friday Monsters on a flight the
day after I watched Miyazaki&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrietty">Secret World of Arrietty</a>.  Sure one had
beautiful water colors and amazing visual tricks mimicking real
camerawork and the other used pre-rendered backgrounds with blocky
polygonal actors on the stage, but these art styles complimented one
another.  They didn&rsquo;t clash.</p>

<p><a href="/images/assets/aotfm.JPG"><img class="center" src="/images/assets/aotfm.JPG" width="320" height="320"></a></p>

<p>I was struck by the ambient sounds that bring the pre-rendered
backgrounds and polygonal characters to life. The periodic train
sounds, presaging the arrival of an in-engine rendered train&#x2013;sort of
quirky and quaint with today&rsquo;s game engines powerful enough to render
both background and foreground objects&#x2013;remind me of a previous
exposure to Japanese culture: the first time I watched <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neon_Genesis_Evangelion">Neon Genesis
Evangelion</a> as a teenager.  There are the ubiquitous cricket or cicada
sounds that were also present in Eva, but for me, they hearken back to
a youth spent in the rural South.  The drone of cicadas in the sticky
summer heat reminds me of falling asleep in a Mississippi home, of
walking into cool woods after standing in a sunny meadow.</p>

<p>The whole game engine is full of quirks and reminders of the PS1 era
of gaming.  But one of the mechanics seems rather novel, an addition
seemingly for its own sake, with little influence on actual plot or
gameplay.  I&rsquo;m talking about the spell casting mechanic, reminiscent
of games children used to play in 70s Japan, the time in which Attack
of the Friday Monsters takes place.</p>

<p>If you win the sometimes annoying, somewhat forgettable,
rock-paper-scissors card game, fueled by collectibles strewn
throughout the world, you gain the ability to cast spells on your
buddies, knocking them down.  It has no bearing on the outcome of the
story.  The spell system is simply decoration that deepens the story
by providing a more complete world, accurately capturing what it feels
like to grow up as a child in Japan during the 70s.</p>

<p>You are allowed to pick, and reorder, the phrases of the spell your
character speaks.  This type of cosmetic customization is typical in
modern games, and in Attack of the Friday Monsters it&rsquo;s nothing more
than cosmetic, but it could have been used in surprising ways.</p>

<p>I realized the potential depth of this mechanic during a phone
conversation with my brother. As I told him about the spell casting,
he mentioned a Kickstarted pen and paper RPG called <a href="http://www.magiciansrpg.com/">Magicians</a>.</p>

<p>Magicians uses spells spoken in another language as both an impulse
toward learning the language and a mechanic for determining the
success or failure of an action. The game my brother described
involved a Harry Potter-esque international school for magicians in
Korea.</p>

<p>To use magic, the characters, and thus the players, have to correctly
speak Korean words&#x2013;at least with enough accuracy to satisfy the
voice-recognition system of an online translation service.  This sets
up the potential for a rather clever scenario in which characters'
<em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bildungsroman">Bildungsroman</a></em> stories
are echoed by the players' acquisition of the language.</p>

<p>At present, on the 3DS, the kind of voice recognition required for
this sort of is <a href="http://www.gamefaqs.com/boards/997781-/58911600">immature</a>.  But it&rsquo;s certainly possible on more
powerful platforms.</p>

<p>One way to exploit the 3DS, and other devices with touch interfaces,
involves learning written language, such as Japanese <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiragana">hiragana</a></em> or
<em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katakana">katakana</a></em>.  I can imagine a magic mechanic that involves correctly
writing scrolls, where the fidelity of the player&rsquo;s calligraphic
strokes determines the strength and efficacy of the scrolls.</p>

<p>Another possible approach is to build up language comprehension by
constructing words out of syllables.  Given several options, one would
choose the correct syllable to complete the necessary word, in order
to perform an action or cast a spell.  A similar sort of approach
would work for learning syntax, completing or building a sentence with
the appropriate words.</p>

<p>Attack of the Friday Monsters is a quick experience, but the depth of
its design has made it a memorable one.  If you&rsquo;d like to learn more
about the game and its creator, you can check out <a href="http://scroll.vg/extras/summer-vacation-confidential/#a">this interview</a> by
Ray Barnholt, which covers Attack of the Friday Monsters and other
games by creator, Kaz Ayabe.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
