<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-23T10:18:41-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improvisation vs Preparation]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/04/23/improvisation-vs-preparation/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-23T09:44:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/04/23/improvisation-vs-preparation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Or preparation as play.</em></p>

<p>This post was inspired by long set-up times eating into time-crunched
play time for busy adults.</p>

<p>As a young adult with minimal time commitment I had no problem
spending hours preparing for a gaming session among friends.  And
there was little concern for an hour or two spent setting up a
wargaming afternoon.  But in adulthood these time commitments quickly
eat-in to or completely consume any time that would otherwise be spent
having fun, gaming with your friends.</p>

<p>Certain games are suited more to the <em>preparation</em> side of things than
the <em>improvisation</em> side.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Consider the examples I mentioned above, a gamemaster driven
roleplaying game and a tabletop war game.  Certainly these are fun
pastimes but they require preparation on the part of the individual or
all parties involved.</p>

<p>Roleplaying games require, at least initially, the generation of
player characters for all involved, potentially consuming the entire
first play session.  The gamemaster is, at least ostensibly, required
to plot out a scenario for each play session, necessitating an
substantial noninteractive time investment outside of the normal play
session.</p>

<p>For war games, players must spend time constructing armies, generally
away from the interaction at the table.</p>

<p>How does this differ from say playing stickball or baseball with your
friends in an alley or a field with just a stick and a ball?  The game
starts when the minimally necessary instruments arrive, and continues
even as players come and go.  Interrupting these improvised games is
an almost heinous offense, hence the saying &ldquo;taking the ball and going
home.&rdquo;</p>

<p>To stretch this metaphor beyond the breaking point: in this syllogism,
the polar opposite of pickup baseball or basketball would be ice
hockey, something requiring potentially hours of preparation by a
Zambonist to prepare the playing surface so the players can play for a
relatively short time.</p>

<p>There are a few games that get preparation as play mechanics right,
but I think there is still room for improvement.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://glyphpress.com/talk/shock-pdf">Shock</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.evilhat.com/home/fate-core/">Fate</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.dog-eared-designs.com/primetime-adventures/">Primetime Adventures</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.lamemage.com/microscope/">Microscope</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://planet-thirteen.com/Dungeon.aspx">How to Host a Dungeon</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://bullypulpitgames.com/games/fiasco/">Fiasco</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p>These games all turn the world gen and character background into an
gameplay activity, typically performed during the first group play
session.  Shock and Fiasco even do away with the necessity of a GM,
allowing players to take turns serving as protagonists, antagonists,
or third parties.  These examples go a long way toward what I mean by
preparation as play, but I don&rsquo;t think the games have captured the
concept entirely.</p>

<p>What I would be interested in seeing is a separate <em>asynchronous</em> type
of game, where the preparation has mechanics that boil down to a solo
game.  The results of the each player&rsquo;s solo game(s) are then somehow
incorporated and allowed to influence the collaborative group play
session.  If you know of such a game, drop me a line in the comments
or on <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Original Diablo Pitch]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/04/02/the-original-diablo-pitch/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-02T09:48:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/04/02/the-original-diablo-pitch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/davidbrevik/status/711420722225106945">David Brevik</a>, one of the original developers of Diablo has released the <a href="http://graybeardgames.blogspot.com/2016/03/original-diablo-pitch-document.html">original pitch document</a>.  Check it out!</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Anatomy of Diablo&rsquo;s pitch document</h2>

<ul>
<li>Summary</li>
<li>Game Design

<ul>
<li>Overview</li>
<li>Plot and Setting</li>
<li>Gameplay</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Marketing</li>
<li>Development</li>
</ul>


<p>In addition to illuminating how to write these documents in general, I find interesting to see how the Diablo devs were planning on leveraging the success of <em>Magic: The Gathering</em>&rsquo;s business model to sell DLC.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Dungeonmans teaches diagonal movement]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/03/19/how-dungeonmans-teaches-diagonal-movement/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-19T09:25:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/03/19/how-dungeonmans-teaches-diagonal-movement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Listening to <a href="http://www.roguelikeradio.com/2016/01/episode-114-gameplay-orientated.html">Roguelike Radio</a>, I heard the creator of <a href="https://twitter.com/dungeonmans">Dungeonmans</a> talk about designing levels to teach gameplay concepts.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.dungeonmans.com/">Dungeonmans</a> has an interesting strategy to teach players to move diagonally early in the game, without requiring a wordy tutorial.</p>

<p>The first level has caves with loot inside.  Some caves are straightforward, allowing players to reach loot without needing to perform a diagonal step.</p>

<pre><code>###
#o#
#.#
</code></pre>

<p>But other caves are different, requiring diagonal movement to get the loot.</p>

<pre><code>###
#o#
##.
</code></pre>

<p>Presenting the diagonal movement mechanic this way is easy and low risk.  If you don&rsquo;t pick it up, it&rsquo;s ok.  You won&rsquo;t die, you just miss out on some loot.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also low disturbance.  There&rsquo;s no dialog popping up saying, &ldquo;Hey!  Listen!&rdquo;  The players will either get a kick out of figuring out how to get that pesky loot or simply move on and play more of the game.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a win-win situation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proportion Types]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/03/05/proportion-types/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-05T12:52:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/03/05/proportion-types</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/androidarts">Arne</a> over at <a href="http://www.androidarts.com/">Android Arts</a> <a href="http://androidarts.com/misc/proportions_types.jpg">codified a taxonomy of proportion types in character design</a>.  I&rsquo;ve kept track of a few examples I&rsquo;ve come across to share with you below.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Ninja Star</h2>

<ul>
<li>Bravely Default</li>
<li>Fire Emblem</li>
<li>Miis</li>
<li>Fez</li>
<li>Super Mario Bros.</li>
<li>Mischief Makers</li>
<li>Gunstar Heroes</li>
<li>Monument Valley</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cross</h2>

<ul>
<li>Call of Duty Advanced Warfare</li>
<li>Minecraft</li>
<li>N++</li>
<li>Gears of War</li>
<li>Warhammer</li>
<li>Last of Us</li>
<li>Uncharted</li>
</ul>


<h2>Maltese cross</h2>

<ul>
<li>Mega Man</li>
<li>Mobile Suit Gundam</li>
<li>Mazinger Z</li>
<li>Getter Robo</li>
<li>Armored Trooper Votoms</li>
<li>Practically everything from Super Robot Wars</li>
<li>Ratchet and Clank</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-27T09:28:58-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An introductory FATE Accelerated Edition (FAE) adventure in the spirit
of Ghostbusters International</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>Dramatis Personae</h1>

<h2>The Library Supervisor</h2>

<p>Has a problem the players need to solve</p>

<h2>The Librarian</h2>

<p>+2 to Poltergeistery, Attacking people with overdue books
-2 to Yelling, doing anything outside of the library</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Summoner</h2>

<p>Andrea Runyon, daughter of Poke Runyon, high priestess of Astarte</p>

<h2>Rock Lions</h2>

<p>+2 to growling
-2 to acid rain</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bat Books</h2>

<p>+2 to flapping around
-2 to preventing combustion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<p>None (first hit takes them out)</p>

<h2>The Lieutenants</h2>

<p>The players will encounter these if the pacing feels a little fast
when they approach the summoning circle in the basement.  Be careful,
because the lieutenants are tough.</p>

<p>First lieutenants of Bael&rsquo;s legion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Clan'thael</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Clancy&rdquo;
Second Lieutenant of the 23rd Legion of Spirits under Bael&rsquo;s rule</p>

<p>+2 to Slurping, phasing between walls
-2 to resisting hunger</p>

<p>Cross between a toad and Slimer.</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h1>At the shop</h1>

<p>Introduce the characters, awarding fate points / discovering aspects
about the setting as appropriate.</p>

<h1>Call to action</h1>

<p>The players get a call to investigate a disturbance at the Library.
The Library Supervisor has ordered the library evacuated because
patrons have reported a ghostly apparition.</p>

<p>The Library Supervisor says</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to help us.  There&rsquo;s no one else to call.  It was horrible.
Books were flying everywhere.  One patron was knocked out.  And those
cries from the office, &lsquo;Overdue&#x2026;. Overdue&#x2026;&rsquo;  They sounded so
menacing&#x2026; I didn&rsquo;t even get my briefcase before evacuating everyone.</p></blockquote>

<h1>Arriving at the library</h1>

<p>Two statues of lions at the front steps of the library come alive.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the players arrive at the library:</p>

<blockquote><p>You pull up at the entrance to the library. Tall marble columns cap
the staircase leading to the door. At the foot of the staircase sit
two marble statues.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players approach the entrance, the statues come to life.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the statues come to life</p>

<blockquote><p>You hear cracking and scraping as the lion statues come to life,
stepping down from their pedestals with a graceful thud. The lions
mouths open as if giving mighty roars but no sounds escape the
statues' throats.</p></blockquote>

<h1>First floor</h1>

<h2>The circulation desk</h2>

<p>The desk is full of books. In closer inspection each book has been
marked overdue. The desk also has overdue stamps all over it as well
as if someone went completely wild stamping everything in sight.</p>

<h2>The office</h2>

<p>Read the following flavor text when the players enter the office</p>

<blockquote><p>The walls are lined with books.  There is a desk with a large office
chair on the far side of the room.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players haven&rsquo;t encountered the Librarian, read this flavor
text</p>

<blockquote><p>The office chair is facing away from the doorway.  It slowly turns
around revealing the wrinkle-creased face of the Librarian.  In an
instant the Librarian&rsquo;s face morphs into a ghastly visage.  You feel
wind blowing as if the Librarian is sucking the energy from the room.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Capturing the Librarian</h3>

<h2>The Stacks</h2>

<p>The library has been evacuated.</p>

<p>If the players don&rsquo;t wander over to the stacks, the characters start
to hear books dropping.  That should entice the players to explore the
stacks.</p>

<p>When the characters arrive, they are attacked by book bats.  If the
pacing feels too fast, increase the challenge by having more books
turn into book bats.</p>

<h3>Book bats</h3>

<h1>The Basement</h1>

<h2>Stairway</h2>

<p>One of the characters becomes paralyzed by a hidden magical circle on
the staircase.  The character who gets paralyzed is left up to the
GM&rsquo;s discretion.</p>

<p>This is a trap set by the Summoner to act as a sort of alarm, alerting
the Summoner to approaching people who may intrude on the summoning.
When the trap is triggered, the Summoner gives up on the invocation
and flees the library.</p>

<p>Read the following flavor text as the characters descend the stairs.</p>

<blockquote><p>As you descend the staircase your limbs grow heavier.  It&rsquo;s as if
you&rsquo;re walking through mud.  Your eyes grow wide as your feet stick to
the floor and your arms freeze.</p></blockquote>

<p>Characters looking for traps on the staircase may notice some markings
on the stairs, but the magical circle that is the source of the
paralysis spell is only visible when you stand on it, ensuring that
the trap will be sprung.</p>

<p>The other characters may attempt to free the paralyzed character by
using some knowledge of the paranormal.</p>

<p>The characters will be released after the Summoner has fled the
Library because the Summoner is no longer able to maintain the spell.</p>

<h2>Hallway</h2>

<h3>Encounter with partially summoned ghost</h3>

<p>The partially summoned ghost slimes the first player, retreating into
the walls of the hallway. As the players move on the spirit comes out
again clinging to the slimes player. The spirit blabbers and cries,
begging for help. The spirit is lost and will be unable to survive if
left alone.</p>

<p>The spirit will become incorporeal if left too long without a human
anchor to reality.  Clancy is on the run from two other lieutenants of
Bael&rsquo;s legion. The lieutenants will kill any malformed spirit and
promote one of their vassals to fill Clancys position</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy then they encounter the lieutenants. If
they do not believe Clancy then it turns out that the spirit was Lying
and then they proceed directly to the summoning circle.</p>

<p>After sliming a character, and clinging to the character, the
partially summoned ghost will reach into any threatening character&rsquo;s
body and pull out a fate token.</p>

<blockquote><p>The toad-like spirit mutters something about being nicer to it.  It
reaches out toward your chest.  To your surprise its hand goes into
your body.  You feel a strange sensation as it pulls out a shining bit
of your energy.  You lose a fate token.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Summoning Circle</h2>

<h3>The interrupted summoning</h3>

<p>Read this flavor text when the characters arrive in the summoning
circle room</p>

<blockquote><p>There is a circle of salt on the ground here.  In the middle you can
see strange symbols that look like they were hastily brushed away,
leaving behind streaks of salt.  The far side of the circle is broken
by footprints heading toward the library&rsquo;s loading dock.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the characters search around they find small amounts of earth, wax,
primrose, and jasmine.  These are elements the summoner was using.
The characters may know purveyors of these items in town.</p>

<p>If the players have befriended Clancy, the partially summoned spirit,
Clancy can make out that the faded symbols are the marking of the
spirit&rsquo;s King, Bael.</p>

<p>The next adventure may involve tracking down where these items come
from, in order to track down the summoner.</p>

<h1>Denouement</h1>

<h2>Character advancement</h2>

<p>If the players capture the Librarian they may gain one minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players gain any information about the summoner the characers
who uncovered the information gain an additional minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy, the player who first encountered
Clancy gets to add Clancy as a free stunt.  This is a significant
milestone.  The player does not have to pay any refresh points, if the
player already has 3 stunts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
