<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-19T10:44:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Strength of the Pitch: Jodorowsky's Dune]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/the-strength-of-the-pitch-jodorowskys-dune/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T10:42:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/the-strength-of-the-pitch-jodorowskys-dune</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was fortunate enough to catch a screening of <em><a href="http://jodorowskysdune.com/">Jodorowsky&rsquo;s Dune</a></em>, the documentary about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alejandro_Jodorowsky">visionary director Alejandro Jodorowsky&rsquo;s</a> failed attempt to adapt the science fiction novel <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune_(novel">Dune</a>)</em> to the silver screen.  Having seen a similar <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0308514/">documentary about Terry Gilliam&rsquo;s attempt at adapting Don Quixote</a>, I consider myself a fan of the genre, despite its niche appeal.</p>

<p>One quick note before we go on.  It looks like <em>Jodorowsky&rsquo;s Dune</em> has hit Netflix on DVD, and seems a likely candidate to be available for streaming.  So you can check it out for yourself to see if you agree with my take.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Pitching</h2>

<p>Jodorowsky looks back, with good-natured humor, on a massively overambitious project for its time.  Aside from the amazing concept art and avant-garde stylings, I took away two messages from the documentary that I would like to share.  The first deals with the art of pitching your ideas and the second with locating oneself in close to proximity to the best and the brightest potential collaborators.</p>

<p>Jodorowsky set out to create a huge book&mdash;more of a cinder block.  It&rsquo;s probably what we could call a design bible today, which would be delivered to production companies in order to secure funding.  By creating a book of storyboards and character designs, Jodorowsky wanted to show that the project was large in scope but feasible, because it had been so intricately planned.</p>

<p>Jodorowsky reached out to a variety of concept artists to help with the design of the movie.  To visual and technical artists, Jodorowsky made impassioned pitches, claiming that they would become &ldquo;spiritual warriors&rdquo; for their collective vision, and implored them to come live and work (for little or no pay) in Paris.</p>

<p>What stands out is the strength of Jodorowsky&rsquo;s pitch.  At a time when artists like <a href="http://www.chrisfossart.com/">Chris Foss</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Giraud">Moebius</a>, and <a href="http://www.hrgiger.com/">H.R. Giger</a> were each becoming established in their own rights, Jodorowsky was able, through the sheer strength of an imagined story, to convince them to devote years of effort to the project.  That takes a lot of gumption.  It didn&rsquo;t hurt that Jodorowsky had a strong track record of visually and thematically impressive avant-garde cinema.  Even still, Jodorowsky is great at selling the idea, and that is something that game designers must do, to communicate ideas to others in order to capitalize on the individual talents and assemble a great team.</p>

<h2>Placement</h2>

<p>The second message I took away deals with putting yourself into the right place at the right time.  It&rsquo;s also about leveraging that placement to connect and collaborate.</p>

<p>The documentary showed a curious problem of the movie&rsquo;s mid-Seventies inception.  How do you find people to collaborate with, or even people at all, before the Internet?</p>

<p>The solution: go to Paris.  That&rsquo;s where all the intelligentsia congregate.  This was more or less true for several hundred years before the Internet.</p>

<p>If you want <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvador_Dal%25C3%25AD">Salvador Dali</a> in your movie, playing the <a href="http://dune.wikia.com/wiki/Padishah_Emperor">Emperor of the Known Universe</a>, go to Paris and you&rsquo;ll probably run into Dali.</p>

<p>Now we all live in our decentralized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temporary_Autonomous_Zone">temporary autonomous zones</a>.  But for as much as they can fragment, social media have the ability to connect disparate artists and thinkers.</p>

<p>I think that Twitter is a platform that serves as a modern Paris, for like-minded people to seek each other out and communicate.  Go congregate with the intelligentsia and let your ideas speak for themselves.  Hit me up on the proverbial tweets, and let me hear your ideas and pitches.  I&rsquo;m constantly working on mine&mdash;writing here, trying to refine my skills.  Maybe we are both looking for the talents that we can provide.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playable Call For Papers]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/playable-call-for-papers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T10:20:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/playable-call-for-papers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.twitter.com/mtrc">Michael Cook</a> made a &ldquo;needlessly interactive&rdquo; <a href="http://www.exag.org/playablecfp/">playable call for papers</a> for the <a href="http://www.exag.org/">Experimental AI in Games conference</a>, taking place in October in Raleigh, NC.  It&rsquo;s a minimally expressive Twine story, with really one simple interactive experience of role-playing the interaction a recipient feels upon receiving yet another CFP email, <em>click</em>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a tricky thing to get right.  While it makes sense for a game-related conference to have a text adventure announcement, I don&rsquo;t want to have to play a game of Frogger to purchase movie tickets from the automated kiosk at the movie theater.  It would be nice if the playable CFP included prominent and consistent links to exit the game, in order to read the ordinary CFP on the conference website.</p>

<p>I believe the motivating idea is sound.  Turning banal daily routine into a playful interactive experience is a worthy goal for game design.  It has the ability to startle the player into paying more attention to mundane activities, which I think is the intended goal&mdash;for a CFP to stand out from piles of other CFP emails.</p>

<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve come across games in strange places.  I don&rsquo;t mean finding a boxed copy of Mario Kart at the flea market&mdash;I mean conceptually strange places.  Hit me up on twitter if you&rsquo;ve got ideas like this to discuss, because I think this approach of creating small play experiences to &ldquo;gamify&rdquo; mundane tasks is an emerging theme of design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why you should start simple]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T13:58:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/hobbygamedev">@HobbyGameDev&rsquo;s</a> long-read <a href="http://www.hobbygamedev.com/beg/incremental-learning/">&ldquo;Reasons for Modest First Projects and Incremental Learning&rdquo;</a> tells the tragic tale of overambitious novice developers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In a response to a doubting tweeter, HGD advocates starting modestly to slowly build skills, so that you can tackle more complicated projects later on.  Avoiding overambitious projects that are way outside of your comfort zone is one of the stumbling points for novice and hobby game developers, like myself.</p>

<p>In the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">previous post about Hammock Driven Creativity</a>, I highlighted Rich Hickey&rsquo;s suggestion to keep multiple projects going in order to avoid stagnation.  While I agree with this, it&rsquo;s important to judge the scope of those projects with a critical eye.</p>

<p>Far too often, my ideas start, at least in my mind, with ambitious artwork, animation, and multiple complex combinations of mechanics.  I am neither talented nor skilled enough to pull these projects off.  So it&rsquo;s easy to get stuck.</p>

<p>I often find myself implementing some ad-hoc animation system, spending time reinventing the frame-based or skeletal wheel, as it were.  Animation shouldn&rsquo;t take priority, especially considering that my best artwork is derivative and possibly one step above programmer art.  I should focus on creating compelling prototypes, and worry about polish later.</p>

<p>To build your skillset, HGD suggests starting out by remaking historical games.  By implementing tried-and-true mechanics that are necessarily simple in scope given their ancient hardware, you can confront the problems involved in creating a full game rather than a half-finished proof-of-concept.</p>

<p>By half-finished, I&rsquo;m thinking of a time where I completely abandoned a concept because I was hung-up on optimizing a tile-based room system.  Rather than making the actual gameplay fun and complete, I was focusing all of my time figuring out how to make walls.  Walls are nice in a finished game, and you could make the case that they are required constraints to achieve good gameplay, but they are not where the fun is.  As HGD and my previous post point out, you can keep trying to work on these overly ambitious projects, but your productivity will suffer.</p>

<p>Best to reap the rewards that come from continued productivity and, as HGD says, pick a fight you can win.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hammock Driven Creativity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-31T11:28:40-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2010, <a href="https://twitter.com/richhickey">Rich Hickey</a> spoke at Clojure Conj about <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3Df84n5oFoZBc">&lsquo;Hammock Driven Development&rsquo;</a>.  Hickey was talking about the benefit of down-time for noodling about software design.  Specifically, Hickey means using down-time after considerably &lsquo;loading up&rsquo; your mind with aspects of the problem, in order to leverage background offline processes to solve those difficult problems.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Wait</h2>

<p>Hickey&rsquo;s advice is to wait for it.  Wait overnight.  Get good rest and make sure that you are sleeping well.  Then you will be able to think about the clearly on the next day.  If you are lucky perhaps you will receive inspiration from a dream and wake up with the problem solved.  This sort of inspiration is what Hickey means by leveraging background processing.</p>

<h2>Multiply</h2>

<p>Hickey mentions working on more than one project.  By having multiple projects, you avoid the problems of creative block, or writer&rsquo;s block.  You can be productive simply by working on another project.  One drawback is that frantically flitting from project to project can lead to problems finishing any single project.  I am often guilty of this.</p>

<p>Eventually, I plan on writing about properly scoping projects to make it possible to get them to a finished state.  One method that works for me is getting something to the point that I can write a blog post about it.  Even if it&rsquo;s not &lsquo;finished&rsquo; finished, I get some satisfaction with putting it out there in a relatively well thought out and complete form.</p>

<p>My solution is to <strong>record, record, record</strong>.  I keep lots of notes, both in more structured form on this blog and in more sketchy form in files on my computer.  I also draw out visual design ideas in a notebook.  Sometimes I will set up skeleton game projects simply to test out an idea.  If I have some sudden insight into a problem, then all of these ideas are available later.</p>

<h2>Switch</h2>

<p>Hickey says to avoid being stuck, switch.  That is why having multiple projects can help.  Hickey also mentions a great suggestion of talking about design hiccups and problems with other people.  Tweet about your design roadblocks.  Write a blog post about them.  Telepathically communicate about them before you go to sleep, so magical dream elves can come and solve them for you.</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<blockquote><p>Summary: There is no summary.  This is a rant.</p></blockquote>

<p>-Rich Hickey</p>

<p>Unless you are Rich Hickey or&#x2013;I dunno&#x2013;Gary Gygax, simply thinking about a problem <em>a priori</em> will not result in a great game.  There is still something to be said for getting your hands dirty and iterating on a design.  However the techniques highlighted in Hickey&rsquo;s talk can be useful when you are stuck on a design problem.</p>

<p>Hit me up in the comments or on the <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">tweet tweet</a> if you have any great Hammock Driven Design tips that I haven&rsquo;t covered here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quarries of Scred Roadmap]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/quarries-of-scred-roadmap/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-24T15:49:08-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/24/quarries-of-scred-roadmap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://darkestkale.itch.io/quarries-of-scred">Quarries of Scred</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/darkestkale">developer</a> released an image showing the overview of Scred&rsquo;s 14-day game development.  I find it informative for a couple of reasons.  First it&rsquo;s not limited to the core features of the game, Kale&rsquo;s also included public relations and marketing information.  Second, the fact that it&rsquo;s incomplete shows how Kale&rsquo;s prioritized critical elements of the game.</p>

<p>Rather than blatantly stealing the <a href="http://www.indiedb.com/games/quarries-of-scred/images/quarries-of-scred-roadmap-2013-11-28-01">roadmap for Quarries of Scred</a>, I&rsquo;ll give you a few seconds to go and capture an eidetic mental image.  Got it?  Great.  I guess all you cheaters who opened it another tab can follow along too.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Core Gameplay</h2>

<p>Looking at the presumably completed &lsquo;green light&rsquo; items, Core Gameplay is almost finished.  And it should be.  Without Core Gameplay, there&rsquo;s not much game to be played.</p>

<p>It looks like they have not included actual aspects of the core mechanic implementation on this roadmap.  However, they&rsquo;re using the roadmap as a method of cataloging oft-overlooked features that add polish to the final game.</p>

<p>They have a milestone for implementing a persistent high score system.  This hurdle is easy to imagine, since we see it in almost every game we play.  But it can be tricky to implement in a robust and efficient manner.</p>

<p>Several elements of UI are included on the roadmap.  They could be neglected in a prototype, these UI elements can make a finished game welcoming for new players and compelling enough to replay.  Info screens can clarify the world for tyros and explicitly show unique challenge states to experienced players.  Death information, like gravestones in Nethack, provides potentially entertaining feedback for the players attempting to hone their skills at the game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure whether they finished implementing rocket ship building gameplay in Quarries of Scred, but this should be a goal for every game.</p>

<h2>PR</h2>

<p>Marketing is an aspect of game development that is easy to overlook as an inexperienced indie or hobby gamedev with a few gamejams under your belt.  The pressure to simply finish a game, any shippable game, overshadows what to do with it once it&rsquo;s released.</p>

<p>Setting up an IndieDB page to track the progress is a great idea.  And, since it doesn&rsquo;t necessarily require a finished product, it can be done early on in the development process.  The priorities of creating an IndieDB Icon, Header Image, and Preview Image show Kale&rsquo;s clearly interested in branding Scred as a marketable indie title.</p>

<p>I can confirm that a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3DBrZ_POiKJO4">Trailer</a>, <a href="http://darkestkale.itch.io/quarries-of-scred">Website</a>, and <a href="http://img.itch.io/aW1hZ2UvODc0LzQ0MTIucG5n/original/Npan5L.png">Box Art</a> came along in due time.  The inclusion of Box Art in a download only indie title is particularly charming, even in an atmosphere awash with these things, the art for Scred&rsquo;s box is fun and quaint, in a good way.</p>

<h2>Further Content</h2>

<p>Further Content looks like features that would directly build on those already implemented in the game.  Rather than being classified as Fluff, these extra features would complement the content and features already implemented in the game.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to have the courage to &lsquo;kill your darlings&rsquo; in cases like this.  Some of the items under Fluff like pretty important to making a good game, but if they are too demanding to fit in the schedule allotted to create the game, they have to go.</p>

<p>One of the buildings has made it in.  And I think the second building is in the final game. Not sure whether the Rare Flower survived.</p>

<h2>Bookending</h2>

<p>The Bookending category looks like a lot of the UI improvements I talked about above.  They certainly improve players' experience, but they may not be absolutely necessary to get the game out the door.</p>

<p>I can only speculate that configurable keys are highlighted in gray because it would be silly not to include them.  For that matter, everything except troubleshooting info adds delicious spice to the well-seasoned dish that the Core Gameplay milestones create.</p>

<h2>Fluff</h2>

<p>It looks like the Fluff category represents additional features that aren&rsquo;t required to make a working game.  The ability to select a seed is probably a new system that requires designing and implementing, much like the UI stuff in the Bookending category.  New Sprites and Death Animation are probably a similar story.</p>

<p>You may argue that music and sound are critical for a completed game.  But if you are not a musically inclined person, the shear amount of work required to get something that sounds like the death-throes of a thousand Gameboys (note: this is not a good thing) could double your production time.  The New Sprites mentioned in the previous paragraph are probably a similar case of requiring too much time that could be more productively devoted elsewhere in the project.</p>

<h2>Closing Thoughts</h2>

<p>This kind of frank openness about game design is unusual to get prior to the publication of a game.  It&rsquo;s really great to see the design documents behind a game, even if it comes out years after release.  It&rsquo;s especially informative to see an in-progress version where the developer is unafraid to lay the goals out there, to show where the project succeeds and possibly falls short.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
