<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-09T11:19:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Persistent Data in Unity]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/persistent-data-in-unity/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T11:09:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/09/persistent-data-in-unity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m interested in having some data remain available, even though I&rsquo;m switching Scenes in Unity.  In other words, I want this data to remain persistent.  As you&rsquo;ll see below I was tempted to use <code>PlayerPrefs</code> to store the data, but, according to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3DJ6FfcJpbPXE">this Unity Live Training on Data Persistence</a>, <code>PlayerPrefs</code> is not the best way to make data persist over multiple Scenes.  <code>PlayerPrefs</code> is an okay place to store non-critical data, like the audio volume, window size, full-screen state&#x2013;you know preferences.  I&rsquo;ll go ahead and show what I believe to be the correct way to store persistent data before talking about <code>PlayerPrefs</code> later.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Persistent data</h2>

<p>To safely and reliably store persistent data, the Unity tutorials suggest that you need to assign a &ldquo;kinda&rdquo; Singleton design patterny script to an empty <code>GameObject</code> that will persist across Scenes.</p>

<pre><code>using UnityEngine;
using System.Collections;

public class GameControl: MonoBehaviour {
  public static GameControl control;

  public float health;
  public float experience;

  void Awake() {
    if(control == null){
      DontDestroyOnLoad(gameObject);
      control = this;
    } else if(control != this) {
      // There can be only one!
      Destroy(gameObject);
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>static</code> reference means that we can just access the values in the <code>GameControl</code> script.</p>

<h2>How to access data in the GameController.</h2>

<pre><code>GameController.control.health = 100;
</code></pre>

<h2>Writing persistent data to a binary file</h2>

<p>The persistent data that&rsquo;s under the control of the <code>GameController</code> is perfectly happy hanging out when your application is running.  It will persist between Scenes when other data is wiped out by Unity&rsquo;s garbage collection.  But what if you want to maintain persistent data when the application is closed.</p>

<p>Ah hah!  Finally, an answer to my nagging question about writing persistent data to plain text files, like <code>PlayerPrefs</code> or simply a file in a local directory.  Wouldn&rsquo;t a player be able to modify the data?</p>

<p>Enter the binary format:</p>

<pre><code>// Add two more libraries
using System;
using System.Runtime.Serialzation.Formatters.Binary;
</code></pre>

<p>Where do we save it?  The persistent data path: <code>Application.persistentDataPath</code>.  We&rsquo;ll need one more library to do some input and output to files:</p>

<pre><code>// Requires one more library and we're ready to get cooking with some
// methods
using System.IO;

public void Save() {
  BinaryFormatter bf = new BinaryFormatter();
  FileStream file = File.Open(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat",
                              FileMode.Open);

  PlayerData data = new PlayerData();
  data.experiencePoints = experiencePoints;
  data.playerLevel = playerLevel;

  bf.Serialize(file, data);
  file.Close();
}

public void Load() {
  if(File.Exists(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat")) {
    BinaryFormatter bf = new BinaryFormatter();
    FileStream file = File.Open(Application.persistentDataPath + "/gameInfo.dat",
                                FileMode.Open);
    PlayerData data = (PlayerData)bf.Deserialize(file);
    file.Close();

    experiencePoints = data.experiencePoints;
    playerLevel = data.playerLevel;
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we need to make the <code>PlayerData</code> class that we will tag with <code>[Serializable]</code> so Unity will know that we want to write this to a binary file at some point in the future.  This affects how Unity stores the data internally, but it doesn&rsquo;t really change how we interact with it.</p>

<pre><code>[Serializable]
class PlayerData {
  // TODO: see about making gets and sets.
  // TODO: automate the generation of this data structure.  See:
  // http://forums.devx.com/showthread.php?170650-How-to-dynamically-add-property-to

  // Add new variables for loading and saving here.
  public int experiencePoints;
  public int playerLevel;
}
</code></pre>

<p>After writing up this article, I came across an older, possibly better article on Unity Gems.  Please check out that write-up and all of the great content on the site.  <a href="http://unitygems.com/saving-data-1-remember-me/">http://unitygems.com/saving-data-1-remember-me/</a></p>

<p>My full <code>GameController</code> data persistence Singleton script is available in <a href="https://gist.github.com/zerosalife/6f6e811b27761d287ea5">this gist</a>.</p>

<p>So, that&rsquo;s the best solution I&rsquo;ve found to date for having persistent data across scenes and play sessions.  I&rsquo;ve included my rough first stabs at the problem below.  Keep in mind that anything following this point is just included just to make my notes available, and it&rsquo;s not meant to be a guide.</p>

<h2>Old notes: PlayerPrefs</h2>

<p>In order to have persistent data between Scenes, I was previously going to make use of Unity&rsquo;s <code>PlayerPrefs</code>, a class that implements persistent data storage for <code>ints</code>, <code>floats</code>, and <code>strings</code>.  Notably absent are useful data types like <code>Vector3</code> to maintain, for example, <code>transform</code> data between Scenes.  Some of the solutions I found may still be helpful for more storing complex data types in <code>PlayerPrefs</code>.</p>

<p>One potential solution is to simply set a <code>GameObject</code>&rsquo;s <code>transform.position</code> to some constant <code>Vector3</code> value in the freshly loaded Scene.  While this is possible in some applications, I&rsquo;m going to assume that eventually you&rsquo;ll want to transfer some dynamic position information between Scenes.</p>

<p>Here are two potentially helpful sources to achieve this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theappguruz.com/tutorial/store-vector3-data-easily-using-json-parsing-possible-using-playerprefs/">http://www.theappguruz.com/tutorial/store-vector3-data-easily-using-json-parsing-possible-using-playerprefs/</a>, based on work by Mehta Dakshil.  While JSON parsing looks interesting, it requires an external <code>.dll</code>, <code>JsonFx.Json.dll</code>.  And I&rsquo;m not interested in external dependencies here.  It may work great for you.</p>

<p><a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title%3DArrayPrefs">&lt;http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php?title=ArrayPrefs></a>, based on work by Mario Madureiera Fontes and Daniel P. Rossi.  (Note: since <code>GetVector3</code> depends on <code>GetFloatArray</code>, there could be some error due to <code>GetFloatArray</code> casting strings to floats.  But the error introduce in the resulting <code>Vector3</code> is unlikely to be noticeable.)</p>

<p>Actually, see a more updated version here: <a href="http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php/ArrayPrefs2">http://wiki.unity3d.com/index.php/ArrayPrefs2</a>, which is based on work by Eric Haines.</p>

<p>According to the text, the script should be placed in the <code>Standard Assets</code> directory, so that it can be accessed from both <code>C#</code> and <code>Boo</code> scripts.</p>

<p>To see a faster implementation for mobile devices, where the data to be saved in PlayerPrefs is cached in memory, see: <a href="http://www.previewlabs.com/writing-playerprefs-fast/">http://www.previewlabs.com/writing-playerprefs-fast/</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Space Is Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-26T11:08:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The cinematically inspired <a href="http://tdlk.itch.io/space-is-red">Space Is Red</a> is not so much a game as it is a visual novel.  Out of the games I tried from the <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">#spacecowboygamejam</a>, it&rsquo;s one that sticks with me.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>On the spectrum of play, these sorts of games are loosely analogous to Choose Your Own Adventure books.  Just as a Choose Your Own Adventure book expects the player to turn to a given page according to the rules laid out at the bottom of the pages to proceed in a consistent, logical fashion, the tropes of a visual novel require the player to interact with the game in order for the story to proceed.  A novel will proceed with the only &lsquo;player&rsquo; interaction consisting of turning to the next page.  I&rsquo;m oversimplifying the difference between <em>real choices</em>, as I would argue, Choose Your Own Adventure Books allow, and <em>mere interactivity</em>, like turning the page of a novel, but you get what I mean.</p>

<p>Visual novels can have real choices and interactivity.  In this case, I&rsquo;d argue that Space Is Red is only interactive.  There are no real choices, short of figuring out the next bit to tap on in order to move the story along.  For me, it&rsquo;s the music that makes the experience gel as something more than an animated e-book.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to be presumptuous in my analysis of Space Is Red&rsquo;s gameplay, don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  I&rsquo;m not interested in arguments about merit simply based on A <strong>is</strong> a game but B <strong>isn&rsquo;t</strong>, so A is better.  I just think it&rsquo;s important to think about these sorts of things when considering the underlying design.</p>

<p>I left the game looping <a href="https://soundcloud.com/postpre">PostPre</a>&rsquo;s driving soundtrack for 15 minutes, even though my first play-through lasted only 2 or 3.  Maybe that&rsquo;s the benefit of interactivity and choices, to extend and prolong the mindshare of some experience or product with the player.  I don&rsquo;t necessarily mean that in a cynical way, although the typical model of play can be subverted for more manipulative means (and, of course, it is!).</p>

<p>For me, Space Is Red hit all the right notes and left me with something to think about.  That is what I call a successful gamejam game.  You can see Space Is Red and the other #spacecowboygamejam entries <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">here</a>.  If you&rsquo;re interested in learning more about Space Is Red&rsquo;s creator <a href="http://toddluke.com/">Todd Luke</a>, you can find an interview <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/TalhaKaya/20140711/220825/Finding_Beauty_in_Imperfection_Interview_with_Todd_Luke.php">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Strength of the Pitch: Jodorowsky's Dune]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/the-strength-of-the-pitch-jodorowskys-dune/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T10:42:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/the-strength-of-the-pitch-jodorowskys-dune</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was fortunate enough to catch a screening of <em><a href="http://jodorowskysdune.com/">Jodorowsky&rsquo;s Dune</a></em>, the documentary about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alejandro_Jodorowsky">visionary director Alejandro Jodorowsky&rsquo;s</a> failed attempt to adapt the science fiction novel <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune_(novel">Dune</a>)</em> to the silver screen.  Having seen a similar <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0308514/">documentary about Terry Gilliam&rsquo;s attempt at adapting Don Quixote</a>, I consider myself a fan of the genre, despite its niche appeal.</p>

<p>One quick note before we go on.  It looks like <em>Jodorowsky&rsquo;s Dune</em> has hit Netflix on DVD, and seems a likely candidate to be available for streaming.  So you can check it out for yourself to see if you agree with my take.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Pitching</h2>

<p>Jodorowsky looks back, with good-natured humor, on a massively overambitious project for its time.  Aside from the amazing concept art and avant-garde stylings, I took away two messages from the documentary that I would like to share.  The first deals with the art of pitching your ideas and the second with locating oneself in close to proximity to the best and the brightest potential collaborators.</p>

<p>Jodorowsky set out to create a huge book&mdash;more of a cinder block.  It&rsquo;s probably what we could call a design bible today, which would be delivered to production companies in order to secure funding.  By creating a book of storyboards and character designs, Jodorowsky wanted to show that the project was large in scope but feasible, because it had been so intricately planned.</p>

<p>Jodorowsky reached out to a variety of concept artists to help with the design of the movie.  To visual and technical artists, Jodorowsky made impassioned pitches, claiming that they would become &ldquo;spiritual warriors&rdquo; for their collective vision, and implored them to come live and work (for little or no pay) in Paris.</p>

<p>What stands out is the strength of Jodorowsky&rsquo;s pitch.  At a time when artists like <a href="http://www.chrisfossart.com/">Chris Foss</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Giraud">Moebius</a>, and <a href="http://www.hrgiger.com/">H.R. Giger</a> were each becoming established in their own rights, Jodorowsky was able, through the sheer strength of an imagined story, to convince them to devote years of effort to the project.  That takes a lot of gumption.  It didn&rsquo;t hurt that Jodorowsky had a strong track record of visually and thematically impressive avant-garde cinema.  Even still, Jodorowsky is great at selling the idea, and that is something that game designers must do, to communicate ideas to others in order to capitalize on the individual talents and assemble a great team.</p>

<h2>Placement</h2>

<p>The second message I took away deals with putting yourself into the right place at the right time.  It&rsquo;s also about leveraging that placement to connect and collaborate.</p>

<p>The documentary showed a curious problem of the movie&rsquo;s mid-Seventies inception.  How do you find people to collaborate with, or even people at all, before the Internet?</p>

<p>The solution: go to Paris.  That&rsquo;s where all the intelligentsia congregate.  This was more or less true for several hundred years before the Internet.  If you want <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvador_Dal%25C3%25AD">Salvador Dali</a> in your movie, playing the <a href="http://dune.wikia.com/wiki/Padishah_Emperor">Emperor of the Known Universe</a>, go to Paris and you&rsquo;ll probably run into Dali.</p>

<p>Now we all live in our decentralized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temporary_Autonomous_Zone">temporary autonomous zones</a>.  But for as much as they can fragment, social media have the ability to connect disparate artists and thinkers.</p>

<p>I think that Twitter is a platform that serves as a modern Paris, for like-minded people to seek each other out and communicate.  Go congregate with the intelligentsia and let your ideas speak for themselves.  Hit me up on the proverbial tweets, and let me hear your ideas and pitches.  I&rsquo;m constantly working on mine&mdash;writing here, trying to refine my skills.  Maybe we are both looking for the talents that we can provide.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playable Call For Papers]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/playable-call-for-papers/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T10:20:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/playable-call-for-papers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.twitter.com/mtrc">Michael Cook</a> made a &ldquo;needlessly interactive&rdquo; <a href="http://www.exag.org/playablecfp/">playable call for papers</a> for the <a href="http://www.exag.org/">Experimental AI in Games conference</a>, taking place in October in Raleigh, NC.  It&rsquo;s a minimally expressive Twine story, with really one simple interactive experience of role-playing the interaction a recipient feels upon receiving yet another CFP email, <em>click</em>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a tricky thing to get right.  While it makes sense for a game-related conference to have a text adventure announcement, I don&rsquo;t want to have to play a game of Frogger to purchase movie tickets from the automated kiosk at the movie theater.  It would be nice if the playable CFP included prominent and consistent links to exit the game, in order to read the ordinary CFP on the conference website.</p>

<p>I believe the motivating idea is sound.  Turning banal daily routine into a playful interactive experience is a worthy goal for game design.  It has the ability to startle the player into paying more attention to mundane activities, which I think is the intended goal&mdash;for a CFP to stand out from piles of other CFP emails.</p>

<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve come across games in strange places.  I don&rsquo;t mean finding a boxed copy of Mario Kart at the flea market&mdash;I mean conceptually strange places.  Hit me up on twitter if you&rsquo;ve got ideas like this to discuss, because I think this approach of creating small play experiences to &ldquo;gamify&rdquo; mundane tasks is an emerging theme of design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why you should start simple]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-07T13:58:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/06/07/why-you-should-start-simple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://twitter.com/hobbygamedev">@HobbyGameDev&rsquo;s</a> long-read <a href="http://www.hobbygamedev.com/beg/incremental-learning/">&ldquo;Reasons for Modest First Projects and Incremental Learning&rdquo;</a> tells the tragic tale of overambitious novice developers.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In a response to a doubting tweeter, HGD advocates starting modestly to slowly build skills, so that you can tackle more complicated projects later on.  Avoiding overambitious projects that are way outside of your comfort zone is one of the stumbling points for novice and hobby game developers, like myself.</p>

<p>In the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">previous post about Hammock Driven Creativity</a>, I highlighted Rich Hickey&rsquo;s suggestion to keep multiple projects going in order to avoid stagnation.  While I agree with this, it&rsquo;s important to judge the scope of those projects with a critical eye.</p>

<p>Far too often, my ideas start, at least in my mind, with ambitious artwork, animation, and multiple complex combinations of mechanics.  I am neither talented nor skilled enough to pull these projects off.  So it&rsquo;s easy to get stuck.</p>

<p>I often find myself implementing some ad-hoc animation system, spending time reinventing the frame-based or skeletal wheel, as it were.  Animation shouldn&rsquo;t take priority, especially considering that my best artwork is derivative and possibly one step above programmer art.  I should focus on creating compelling prototypes, and worry about polish later.</p>

<p>To build your skillset, HGD suggests starting out by remaking historical games.  By implementing tried-and-true mechanics that are necessarily simple in scope given their ancient hardware, you can confront the problems involved in creating a full game rather than a half-finished proof-of-concept.</p>

<p>By half-finished, I&rsquo;m thinking of a time where I completely abandoned a concept because I was hung-up on optimizing a tile-based room system.  Rather than making the actual gameplay fun and complete, I was focusing all of my time figuring out how to make walls.  Walls are nice in a finished game, and you could make the case that they are required constraints to achieve good gameplay, but they are not where the fun is.  As HGD and my previous post point out, you can keep trying to work on these overly ambitious projects, but your productivity will suffer.</p>

<p>Best to reap the rewards that come from continued productivity and, as HGD says, pick a fight you can win.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
