<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: design | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-31T14:18:54-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VGBC: a Video Game Book Club]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/vgbc-a-video-game-book-club/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T12:54:10-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/01/24/vgbc-a-video-game-book-club</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Credit for the original idea for a #VGBC goes to Rick Wolf, who also
coauthored this post.  You can get in touch with Rick at
<a href="https://twitter.com/involvingsalmon">@InvolvingSalmon</a> on Twitter.</p>

<h2>What?</h2>

<p>Your very own #VGBC (one of those newfangled acronyms we hear are all the rage these days).  A <strong>club</strong> devoted to selecting and critically
<strong>discussing video games</strong>. We like the acronym #VGBC, but you can call it
what you feel. It&rsquo;s worth noting that we aren’t reading a book each month (although some game design books would do us well), but we’re calling it a “book” club to emphasize the format that encourages thoughtful discussion.</p>

<p>Each meeting you can discuss any aspect of a video game that strikes your fancy.  Maybe you really like the music or art direction, maybe there&rsquo;s one level that you could play over and over again until you get it perfect, maybe you really like the silent protagonist&rsquo;s haircut.  Let your club know.  Chances are, your thoughts about the video game will evoke some exciting input from others in your club.  You can respond with all those witty retorts you&rsquo;ve been practicing in the mirror.  This is what&rsquo;s known colloquially as a discussion.</p>

<p>But how do I know what to discuss, you ask?  It&rsquo;s simple.  <strong>Take turns picking a topical game that everyone can play</strong>, within reason.  We say within reason because, like a book club, everyone needn&rsquo;t finish the discussion material to weigh in.  Don&rsquo;t expect everyone in your club to buy the latest $60 game.</p>

<p>A rule of thumb can be that the host of the last meeting gets to choose the game for the next meeting.</p>

<h2>Who?</h2>

<p>You, your friends, the cat (If you have one. No catnapping.), <strong>anyone</strong> with interest in critically discussing video games. Maybe, like us, the group consists of people that are interested in game design. Maybe you invite your friends that love games, but haven’t ventured into the realm of formal discussion. The more the people you have with different interests, the more likely you are to get a new take on a game.</p>

<h2>When?</h2>

<p>Pick your favorite periodic adjective.  We&rsquo;d recommend starting with
<strong>monthly</strong> meetings, but you can meet as often as you like.  Really.
We don&rsquo;t mind.  See if we care.  It&rsquo;s not like you invited us.</p>

<p>Anyway. Pick a time that works best for your group.  Sometime in the evening, say around happy hour, with a delicious beverage and snacks sounds good to us.  We&rsquo;d reckon that allowing for <strong>two hours</strong> should be enough discussion.  If a topic is particularly engaging you can always spread it out over multiple meetings.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s up to you to work out a schedule that works for your group.
<strong>Scheduling apps</strong> like <a href="http://doodle.com/">Doodle.com</a> can be helpful for coordinating busy
schedules and finding a time that works for everyone in your group.</p>

<h2>Where?</h2>

<p>In your <strong>home</strong>, in your friends' homes (assuming they&rsquo;re part of the meeting&#x2026;), in your garage, <strong>at a local pub</strong>.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s nice to meet <strong>somewhere with a television</strong> and a <strong>game system</strong> to play the game you will discuss.  Showing video of your favorite parts of the game can be nice too.  If you want to do that, try to plan ahead and get a save near the part you want to discuss or check for video playthroughs on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>If you meet outside your home make sure you check with the establishment beforehand.  Give them a headcount and check if it&rsquo;s ok.  Be sure to spend a little scrilla and tip well.  Be aware of other customers.</p>

<h2>Why?</h2>

<p>Because <strong>video games deserve a critical reading</strong>.  Discussions force all of us to crystallize our views from vague notions of &ldquo;It&rsquo;s good,&rdquo; to &ldquo;The fog of war mechanic in this game vastly improves the strategic elements, strengthening the multiplayer meta-game.&rdquo;  (Your mileage may vary.)</p>

<p>Sometimes you&rsquo;ll get to suggest your favorite game.  Others may deride your choice, but they will get their chance too.  Heck someone may even like the games you suggest, discussing an intriguing aspect that was lost on you.  Then the others in your club will suggest other games.  You never know, you may just find a game that you like.  If you&rsquo;re anything like us, assigning a game and being accountable to comment on it can also help <a href="http://www.backloggery.com/">curb the constant growth of your Steam library</a>.</p>

<p>Maybe one month you&rsquo;ll find that you hated a game. But take a moment and think about why it isn&rsquo;t fun. Do you dislike it because you&rsquo;re bad at puzzle games, or is it unenjoyable because it&rsquo;s a garbage visual novel whose writer has never heard of the three act structure? These reasons are very different, and both are worth considering. We&rsquo;re hoping that reflecting on what makes a game good or bad will make us better designers. We do this with most games that we play, but by doing it with friends we can all get feedback on our thoughts; and we guarantee that will make us grow as designers.</p>

<p>What we&rsquo;ve presented here are a set of guidelines.  There are no hard and fast rules or requirements for hosting your own #VGBC.  Want to talk about knitting?  Cool.  Want to discuss your favorite sporting moments?  Great.  Board games?  Lawn darts?  More power to you.</p>

<p>So start up your own #VGBC and let us know how it goes in the comments or on the twitters <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">@zerosalife</a> or <a href="http://twitter.com/involvingsalmon">@InvolvingSalmon</a>.  When I post about something from #VGBC on the blog, I&rsquo;ll tag it with <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/vgbc/">VGBC</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Procjam review]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T09:33:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking through the entries, I could only spend a minute or two with each entry.  It helped if the game ran in my browser, so HTML and Unity were big.  Here are some of the games that caught my eye.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The top two</h2>

<h2>JET/LAG</h2>

<p>Simple instructions: &ldquo;Click to move. Kill enemies by bashing them.&rdquo;  There may be little to <em><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a></em>, but its excellent stylish visuals set this entry apart for me.  A CRT-like distortion bends the corners of the screen complete with scrolling scan lines, while multi-colored text oscillates above a simple square.  The simple square is your character battering your way through procedurally generated maze-like levels.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no fancy art in this game, all the characters are made from simple shapes.  But that doesn&rsquo;t stop the graphics from impressing.  It&rsquo;s clear that <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> turned the juice up to 11, and it works.  The game feels great.</p>

<p>As a &ldquo;rogue-like like like&rdquo; you may expect it to be deviously hard, and you&rsquo;d be right.  But the controls are responsive and the enemies telegraph their moves, so you feel like you are learning something with each death.  <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> clearly understands some fundamentals of engaging game design and I&rsquo;m excited to see what&rsquo;s coming up next.</p>

<h2>DUNGEN [star]</h2>

<p>A multi-jam entry for <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam</a>, <a href="http://itch.io/jam/paper-jam-1">#paperjam</a>, and <a href="http://7dfps.com/">#7dfps</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a>, this first person shooter uses shuffling to generate a dynamic dungeon with each play-through.  I like the simplicity of the mechanics <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a> has designed.  Stats on a 1-10 scale can be just as interesting as stats in the thousands.  There are even multiple skin options for the protagonist&rsquo;s hand.  That&rsquo;s more advanced than all three <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_%2528series%2529">DOOM</a></em>s.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;m most interested in the literal realization of the procedural generation algorithm.  By shuffling the cards the procedural generation of the dungeon is clear both to designer and player, and this type of randomization has been used for many years in many games with standard and nonstandard sets of cards.  I&rsquo;m interested in seeing how this shuffling mechanic, both literal and metaphorical, can be leveraged to encourage new avenues of play in the future.  I can imagine tuning some aspects of a proc gen algorithm by exposing the contents to the player as a deck of cards, both literally as is typical in CCGs and other tabletop games and as a metaphor for abstraction of systems in a video game.</p>

<h2>Favorite games</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a>

<ul>
<li>Bump or get bumped.  Excellent style and great graphics.  Very
juicy!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://lissar.itch.io/peregrin">Peregrin</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://entropyphi.itch.io/nauticalith">Nauticalith</a>

<ul>
<li>Simple, but really conveys a sense of scale.  Adding some mechanic
like dynamic wind that affects sailing could put this over the
top.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tfurmanskigmailcom.itch.io/forska-web-version">Forska</a>

<ul>
<li>Great shader.  Generate some <em><a href="http://wikipedia.com/wiki/Myst">Myst</a></em>-like puzzles and you&rsquo;ve got a game, here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://8-bit-ape.itch.io/infinity-explorer">Infinity Explorer</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_Carpet_%28video_game%29">Magic Carpet</a></em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN star</a>

<ul>
<li>Print and play games are great.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Favorite generators</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer">http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer</a>

<ul>
<li>Interesting.  Will have to look more into it.  Now that I think
about it, this one deserves an honorable mention for favorite tool
of the jam.  I will revisit it in depth in a later post because the
generation algorithm looks like an idea I&rsquo;ve batted around in my
head.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/">http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful and cool!  Check out <a href="http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora">http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora</a>
for some more background on this space colony generator.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics">http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics</a>

<ul>
<li>Clever tiling textures using diagonal lines that really break up
the patterns to make it more pleasing to the eye.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters">http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters</a>

<ul>
<li>Artistic style.  Simple color palette still allow for a variety of
expressive monsters. Interested in following up on the
procedural tree generation–looks great!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia">https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful world generator with some source code worth digging
into.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla">http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla</a>

<ul>
<li>Really think there&rsquo;s something to explore in pixels-as-stitches
graphics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch">http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch</a>

<ul>
<li>The pet rock generator I always wanted!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator">http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer">http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer</a>

<ul>
<li>Weird hybrid between an AI and a text adventure, but very
  creative and very cool.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026">http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026</a>

<ul>
<li>Great concept, but I need remedial lessons or a tutorial.  One to
revisit when I can really dig into it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cool looking Windows games I couldn&rsquo;t play</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist">http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wonderful_101">Wonderful 101</a></em>–a game I haven&rsquo;t played, but probably should.  Something about the aesthetic of dozens of little flocking characters appeals to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://caseportman.itch.io/riser">http://caseportman.itch.io/riser</a>

<ul>
<li>Looks like it controls well</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[procjam comedown]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T13:26:16-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that two weeks have passed (a geologic era in internet time), I&rsquo;m ready begin to look back on the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a> talks and the entries to the jam that caught my eye.  I&rsquo;ve been very busy lately working on my own submissions <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/">INSceptahdeckwu</a> and <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/patchwerk/">Patchwerk</a>, among other commitments, so this is by no means an exhaustive look at everything in #procjam.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Since I actually have no time at all to write a full retrospective, I&rsquo;ll have to be brief.  This post will have to serve as a collection of links and notes until I get a chance to look back in detail.  It&rsquo;s by no means complete, as I&rsquo;m still looking over all of the great entries to #procjam.  I enjoyed the interactions with the speakers and participants.  Unfortunately other commitments may occupy my time through the end of the year, so don&rsquo;t worry if the blogging is intermittent.  I&rsquo;ll revisit the #procjam talks and the submissions when I find time.</p>

<h2>Great ideas</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824">https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992">https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113">https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1">https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992">https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992</a></p>

<p><a href="http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/">http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js">https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js</a></p>

<p><a href="http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/">http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input">https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input</a></p>

<p><a href="http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner">http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen">https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen</a></p>

<p><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen</a></p>

<h2>Good tutorials</h2>

<p>Some tutorials I came across during the jam:</p>

<p><a href="http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started">http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440">https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440</a></p>

<p><a href="http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/">http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/</a></p>

<h2>Talks</h2>

<p>Here are my notes on the talks that I had a chance to see.  In lieu of writing anything up, I&rsquo;ll post them here for now.</p>

<h3>Overall themes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Meaning over randomness</li>
<li>Scale and direction

<ul>
<li>Layering</li>
<li>Deck metaphor really nice for prototyping.</li>
<li>Great question, how do you make sure the player is not lost in
this huge history.  Player only aware of history of own house,
data is gathered by reading books etc.; there&rsquo;s some context for
the entrance of new bits of history.  Books are populated in
places where it makes sense for them to turn up.</li>
<li>Top-down (designer first) is easier than bottom-up (player first;
shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/gillianmsmith">@gillianmsmith</a> for this formulation).  Callbacks?
How to percolate up from lower elements on tree?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Storytelling as divination</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dariusk/NaNoGenMo">NaNoGenMo</a></li>
<li>Flow in procedural generation

<ul>
<li>Meaning, codifying design principlse</li>
<li><a href="http://artofgamedesign.com/">Art of Game Design by Jesse Schell</a></li>
<li>a feeling of complete and energized focus in an activity, with a
high level of enjoyment and fulfillment

<ul>
<li>clear goals</li>
<li>no distractions

<ul>
<li>How does this figure into open world distraction fests like
triple a sandbox games?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>feedback</li>
<li>continuously challenging</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Frustration vs. boredom, find a balance</li>
<li>Dynamic

<ul>
<li>Scale enemy level to meet player&rsquo;s level</li>
<li>AI director, see when the player is overwhelmed, drop difficulty;
boredom spawn more enemies.  Requires some kind of metric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Static

<ul>
<li>Lock and key</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tcoxon/metazelda">Metazelda</a> calculates difficulty number for each room from desired flow curve.</li>
<li>Love <a href="https://github.com/tcoxon">@tcoxon</a> &rsquo;s thoughts on less backtracking.  Algorithmically respecting players' time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/ToniSala/20131208/206535/Game_Design_Theory_Applied_The_Flow_Channel.php">Gamasutra Toni Sala</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Emotion and interactivity &#x2013; expressivity

<ul>
<li>Workflow, ease of adjustment can be good for designer and exposing
the same tools to the player can be fun</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>itch.io</h2>

<p>It looks like most of the entries are gathered on a <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam itch.io page</a>.  I have no experience with <a href="http://itch.io/">itch.io</a>, but I think setting up an account and exploring what itch.io has to offer couldn&rsquo;t hurt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[INSceptahdeckWU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T08:28:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>#procjam updates</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q%3Dprocjam">#procjam</a> is upon us.  The conference is on and popping, streaming at <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/procjam">http://www.twitch.tv/procjam</a>.  I&rsquo;ll try to precede my #procjam posts with a little update on some of the cool things I&rsquo;ve seen that need pointing out during the jam itself.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/GalaxyKate">@GalaxyKate</a> will be streaming <a href="http://vimeo.com/111272682">some tutorials</a> today, following the conference.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/SudoRossy">@sudorossy</a> is currently streaming some development and modeling at <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/sudorossy">http://www.twitch.tv/sudorossy</a>.  I imagine that sudorossy will continue this throughout the jam.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q%3D7dfps">#7dfps</a> jam is also going on this week.  So, I&rsquo;ve decided to release my third person procedural tweeter.  Or maybe it&rsquo;s a fourth person tweeter, third person once removed.</p>

<h2>Fourth-person tweets</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m at it again, <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks/">making a twitter bot</a> like <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>.  Only this time it&rsquo;s in a completely different language and it&rsquo;s got a completely different corpus.  Corpus is a Latin way of saying text, in case you forgot.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Making the tweets</h2>

<p>The basic algorithm works like this.</p>

<p>The bot creates a huge textfile containing lyrics from Wu Tang Clan songs.  I trim away a lot of the information about verses and choruses, but I keep the punctuation because I like the sense of rhythm it creates.</p>

<p>Based on the relationship between the words in this corpus file, the bot builds a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">markov process</a> to generate the text of the tweets.  To do so, the bot generates a transition matrix using <a href="https://github.com/Janiczek/markov">Janiczek&rsquo;s Clojure markov library</a>.  It then takes random walks through that matrix to produce a string of text with a similar relationship between words to the input lyrics corpus.</p>

<h2>Making it a command line app</h2>

<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve tried to make a command line application in Twitter.  Luckily there are some good tools out there.</p>

<p>I wondered how to deal with multiple options and inputs, and the good news is: it&rsquo;s just as easy as you&rsquo;d think.  You simply add conditionals to deal with the possible behaviors of your program.  The magic of <code>parse-opts</code> handles the rest.  Options with long names automatically become keys to the option dictionary, and if you&rsquo;ve marked them as a <code>:flag</code> you can depend on the truth-value to control the flow of your program.</p>

<p>You may think it&rsquo;s odd that I&rsquo;m using options instead of actions as in the <code>cli</code> example, but hey.  It&rsquo;s my program.  Your program can work the way you want it too.  I&rsquo;m going to make sure to document it so you can use the Rebel INS or build a twitter bot based on this code.</p>

<p>To build the app, I use <code>lein bin</code> from the command line.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m interested in <a href="http://www.rkn.io/2014/02/06/clojure-cookbook-daemons/">daemonizing</a> the application.  That is to say, I&rsquo;m interested in turning it into a persistent process that runs in the background on my computer.  But for now, I&rsquo;ve set up a simple <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron</a> script to tweet every few hours.</p>

<h2>Logging</h2>

<p>When I do tweets from the command line there&rsquo;s some dark magic going on that I don&rsquo;t understand.  Anyway it seems to invoke the <code>Log4j</code>, so I <a href="http://www.bahmanm.com/blogs/how-to-add-logging-to-a-clojure-project">set that up according to this blog post</a>.</p>

<h2>Markov chain text generation</h2>

<p>One of the quirks of the markov package I used is that it stops generating &lsquo;random walks&rsquo; when it reaches states that it has not been trained on.  As you can imagine when using imagery-rich, neologism-laden rap music, there are many words that occur once, even in a very large corpus.  Being unique is kind of a goal of the form, a fact reflected in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ol%2527_Dirty_Bastard">at least one alias</a>.</p>

<p>In order to make more realistic texts, it&rsquo;s common to increase the order of the transition matrix.  That is to say, to determine the probability for a following word from the prior two or more words.  However, given my idiosyncratic corpus, this leads the &lsquo;random walk&rsquo; algorithm to halt, giving me too few words in my output.</p>

<p>Interestingly, in this case, dialing back the order tends to lead to more rhyming and a few recognizable couplets, which I find kinda nice.</p>

<h2>Setting up the twitter account</h2>

<p>I ran into a problem getting an app set up for the bot&rsquo;s twitter account.  I am merely one person, and thus have need for merely one cell phone.  Since twitter requires a unique mobile number for authenticating apps, I was out of luck.  That is, until I found this <a href="http://dghubble.com/blog/posts/twitter-app-write-access-and-bots/">blog post showing how to use the same app on multiple bot clients</a>.</p>

<p>Faithful readers may remember my wildly popular, and yet still somehow deeply underrated, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangsian_fantasy">Bangsian</a> fantasy bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>.  Using <code>twurl</code> I was able to grant access to the <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a> app credentials for the new bot.</p>

<h2>Moving on</h2>

<p>You can find the source code over on <a href="http://github.com/zerosalife/insceptahdeckwu">github.</a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s one of my favorite tweets so far:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>From here the sky&rsquo;s the limit.  I could try analyzing the generated text to try to build lines or stanzas.  I could try to reorder words to reflect the syntax present from the transcription.  I could try to represent individual emcees with unique corpora.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play balance for party vs in-depth fighting games]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/play-balance-for-party-vs-in-depth-fighting-games/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T10:33:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/play-balance-for-party-vs-in-depth-fighting-games</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here I&rsquo;m drawing a comparison between games that are subjectively perceived as party games and games that are more in-depth.  I&rsquo;m avoiding using loaded terms like casual and hardcore, but I think the distinction is likely the same.  Both types of games can be complex, but subtle balancing issues can affect the subjective sense of fun when playing these games.</p>

<p>For discussion I&rsquo;m going to focus on relatively advanced moves in <em><a href="http://www.smashbros.com">Super Smash Bros.</a></em> and <em><a href="http://www.towerfall-game.com/">TowerFall</a></em>: L-canceling and dodge canceling, respectively.  I was inspired to examine this balance issue by a recent tweet by <em>TowerFall</em> creator, and, in the interest of full disclosure, my close personal 3DS friend, <a href="https://twitter.com/MattThorson">@MattThorson</a>.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Thorson previously pointed out an interesting <a href="https://twitter.com/DamianSommer/status/519537228582633473">discussion</a> on the mechanic of L-canceling by <a href="https://twitter.com/DamianSommer/status/519537228582633473">@DamianSommer</a> among others. Sommer wants to focus on how the L-canceling mechanic reflects the design intent of the creators of <em>Super Smash Bros.</em></p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Sonic9jct">@Sonic9jct</a> highlights the dichotomy that I am exploring here.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p><a href="http://supersmashbros.wikia.com/wiki/L-canceling">L-canceling</a> requires extremely precise timing of inputs when the character is in a particular state.  You must press L within 6 frames of landing on the ground while performing an <a href="http://supersmashbros.wikia.com/wiki/Aerial_attack">aerial attack</a>.  Since <em>Super Smash Bros.</em> runs at 60 frames per second, this requires you to press the button within 100 milliseconds of hitting the ground.  To put this in perspective, the average human reaction time is about 250 milliseconds.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/whatisian">@whatisian</a> brilliantly captures the distinction in design that makes this a more difficult, in-depth, technically demanding mechanic.  If there is no drawback, then the execution of the L-cancel is practically mandatory at high levels of play.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at how this differs from <a href="http://steamcommunity.com/sharedfiles/filedetails/?id%3D250779585">dodge canceling</a> in <em>TowerFall</em> a game that Thorson intentionally designed to be welcoming to new players, while still keeping them competitive with skilled players.</p>

<p>Dodge canceling requires similarly herculean inputs to pull off, to perform a dodge cancel you must press the dodge button a second time after initiating a dodge maneuver.  The dodge lasts 367 milliseconds or 22 frames at 60 fps.  This seems like a lot of time to perform the dodge cancel compared to the scant 6 frames for an L-cancel, but there&rsquo;s a catch.  In order to get the most momentum, to carry the most speed through the dodge cancel, you must perform the move on exactly the right frame.</p>

<p>Sounds pretty tough, right?  If you think this would require some impressive technical skills to pull it off, you&rsquo;re right.  But there&rsquo;s a catch, turning or firing from the dodge cancel reduces the character&rsquo;s speed, making the character an easier target.</p>

<p>Thorson&rsquo;s mechanic provides a similar advantage to L-canceling with the addition of the risk of failure.  Dodge cancels could allow the player to zing around the level at will, firing arrows every which way, but Thorson decided to introduce drawbacks for imprecise play that create risks for more advanced players to put them closer to parity with less skilled players.</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>These are just my thoughts on this interesting discussion.  I&rsquo;m not a high-level player of either of these games, so I may have missed some of the subtleties to which Thorson or others refer.  If you think I&rsquo;m off the mark, or you just want to weigh in on the merits of designing for &ldquo;party&rdquo; vs. &ldquo;fighting&rdquo; games, drop me a line in the comments or on <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
