<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: game | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-24T13:01:21-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A proper review of DUNGEN [Star]]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:44:36-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My green fingers sweat on the handle of my pistol as I creep through the door, into the next room.  I found two boxes of ammunition in the previous room so I&rsquo;m well equipped for the next horrible monster I encounter.  My grip on the pistol tightens as a horrible three-legged spherical thing jumps down from the ceiling, pirouetting to land on its feet and shooting a stream of acidic liquid at me.</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Oof,&rdquo; is all I manage to get out, as I feel the Burster&rsquo;s fluid eat into my skin.  Without thinking I fire at it, killing the thing in two shots.</em></p>

<p><em>While reloading my pistol, I notice a glowing jewel on the stone.  If it&rsquo;s what the briefings said, this is the teleport stone that will allow me to phase out of our normal reality just long enough to escape the next deadly monster I encounter in</em> DUNGEN [Star].</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"><img class="center" src="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"></a></p>

<p>(Please excuse my lame attempt at illustrating play with a .gif).</p>

<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/">Last week, I posted an overview of my favorite #procjam games</a>.  I felt remissed when I got a tweet from the designer, asking whether I had actually printed and played the game.  I hadn&rsquo;t and neither had any of the other reviewers who praised it.  So, this week I took some time to cut out the cards on my computer, effectively making a print-and-play game I could play in Illustrator without bothering to print it out.</p>

<p>After the initial time investment, <em><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN [Star]</a></em>, a print-and-play game designed by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@JctWood</a> for the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/paperjam">#paperjam</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/7dfps">#7dfps</a> gamejams, plays quickly.  Especially if you are brave enough to choose the roguelike secret difficulty level of starting with 1HP.  Add to that, the advanced enemy rules, which give the monsters more personality on top of their already evocative illustrations and you&rsquo;ve got a challenging game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of the cartoonish art style of <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>.  The character design does a good job of communicating interesting variety, even though there are few monsters to go up against.</p>

<p><em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> runs out of steam quickly, but I think the intent behind it is clear.  This game does a good job of bringing the feel of a procedural first-person shooter with roguelike elements to the print-and-play market.  I think extending the combat to involve multiple weapons would add some depth to the game.  I would like to see more enemies, particularly ones with more interesting advanced enemy rules.  I&rsquo;d also like to see an overarching goal or theme tying together <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>&rsquo;s dungeoning and star, so you feel more satisfied when you survive the dungeon.  With that criticism said, I still think <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> succeeds as a gamejam game and a great prototype from which to build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Procjam review]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T09:33:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking through the entries, I could only spend a minute or two with each entry.  It helped if the game ran in my browser, so HTML and Unity were big.  Here are some of the games that caught my eye.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The top two</h2>

<h2>JET/LAG</h2>

<p>Simple instructions: &ldquo;Click to move. Kill enemies by bashing them.&rdquo;  There may be little to <em><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a></em>, but its excellent stylish visuals set this entry apart for me.  A CRT-like distortion bends the corners of the screen complete with scrolling scan lines, while multi-colored text oscillates above a simple square.  The simple square is your character battering your way through procedurally generated maze-like levels.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no fancy art in this game, all the characters are made from simple shapes.  But that doesn&rsquo;t stop the graphics from impressing.  It&rsquo;s clear that <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> turned the juice up to 11, and it works.  The game feels great.</p>

<p>As a &ldquo;rogue-like like like&rdquo; you may expect it to be deviously hard, and you&rsquo;d be right.  But the controls are responsive and the enemies telegraph their moves, so you feel like you are learning something with each death.  <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> clearly understands some fundamentals of engaging game design and I&rsquo;m excited to see what&rsquo;s coming up next.</p>

<h2>DUNGEN [star]</h2>

<p>A multi-jam entry for <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam</a>, <a href="http://itch.io/jam/paper-jam-1">#paperjam</a>, and <a href="http://7dfps.com/">#7dfps</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a>, this first person shooter uses shuffling to generate a dynamic dungeon with each play-through.  I like the simplicity of the mechanics <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a> has designed.  Stats on a 1-10 scale can be just as interesting as stats in the thousands.  There are even multiple skin options for the protagonist&rsquo;s hand.  That&rsquo;s more advanced than all three <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_%2528series%2529">DOOM</a></em>s.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;m most interested in the literal realization of the procedural generation algorithm.  By shuffling the cards the procedural generation of the dungeon is clear both to designer and player, and this type of randomization has been used for many years in many games with standard and nonstandard sets of cards.  I&rsquo;m interested in seeing how this shuffling mechanic, both literal and metaphorical, can be leveraged to encourage new avenues of play in the future.  I can imagine tuning some aspects of a proc gen algorithm by exposing the contents to the player as a deck of cards, both literally as is typical in CCGs and other tabletop games and as a metaphor for abstraction of systems in a video game.</p>

<h2>Favorite games</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a>

<ul>
<li>Bump or get bumped.  Excellent style and great graphics.  Very
juicy!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://lissar.itch.io/peregrin">Peregrin</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://entropyphi.itch.io/nauticalith">Nauticalith</a>

<ul>
<li>Simple, but really conveys a sense of scale.  Adding some mechanic
like dynamic wind that affects sailing could put this over the
top.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tfurmanskigmailcom.itch.io/forska-web-version">Forska</a>

<ul>
<li>Great shader.  Generate some <em><a href="http://wikipedia.com/wiki/Myst">Myst</a></em>-like puzzles and you&rsquo;ve got a game, here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://8-bit-ape.itch.io/infinity-explorer">Infinity Explorer</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_Carpet_%28video_game%29">Magic Carpet</a></em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN star</a>

<ul>
<li>Print and play games are great.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Favorite generators</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer">http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer</a>

<ul>
<li>Interesting.  Will have to look more into it.  Now that I think
about it, this one deserves an honorable mention for favorite tool
of the jam.  I will revisit it in depth in a later post because the
generation algorithm looks like an idea I&rsquo;ve batted around in my
head.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/">http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful and cool!  Check out <a href="http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora">http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora</a>
for some more background on this space colony generator.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics">http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics</a>

<ul>
<li>Clever tiling textures using diagonal lines that really break up
the patterns to make it more pleasing to the eye.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters">http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters</a>

<ul>
<li>Artistic style.  Simple color palette still allow for a variety of
expressive monsters. Interested in following up on the
procedural tree generation–looks great!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia">https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful world generator with some source code worth digging
into.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla">http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla</a>

<ul>
<li>Really think there&rsquo;s something to explore in pixels-as-stitches
graphics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch">http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch</a>

<ul>
<li>The pet rock generator I always wanted!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator">http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer">http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer</a>

<ul>
<li>Weird hybrid between an AI and a text adventure, but very
  creative and very cool.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026">http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026</a>

<ul>
<li>Great concept, but I need remedial lessons or a tutorial.  One to
revisit when I can really dig into it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cool looking Windows games I couldn&rsquo;t play</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist">http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wonderful_101">Wonderful 101</a></em>–a game I haven&rsquo;t played, but probably should.  Something about the aesthetic of dozens of little flocking characters appeals to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://caseportman.itch.io/riser">http://caseportman.itch.io/riser</a>

<ul>
<li>Looks like it controls well</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[procjam comedown]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T13:26:16-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that two weeks have passed (a geologic era in internet time), I&rsquo;m ready begin to look back on the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a> talks and the entries to the jam that caught my eye.  I&rsquo;ve been very busy lately working on my own submissions <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/">INSceptahdeckwu</a> and <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/patchwerk/">Patchwerk</a>, among other commitments, so this is by no means an exhaustive look at everything in #procjam.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Since I actually have no time at all to write a full retrospective, I&rsquo;ll have to be brief.  This post will have to serve as a collection of links and notes until I get a chance to look back in detail.  It&rsquo;s by no means complete, as I&rsquo;m still looking over all of the great entries to #procjam.  I enjoyed the interactions with the speakers and participants.  Unfortunately other commitments may occupy my time through the end of the year, so don&rsquo;t worry if the blogging is intermittent.  I&rsquo;ll revisit the #procjam talks and the submissions when I find time.</p>

<h2>Great ideas</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824">https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992">https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113">https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1">https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992">https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992</a></p>

<p><a href="http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/">http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js">https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js</a></p>

<p><a href="http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/">http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input">https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input</a></p>

<p><a href="http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner">http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen">https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen</a></p>

<p><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen</a></p>

<h2>Good tutorials</h2>

<p>Some tutorials I came across during the jam:</p>

<p><a href="http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started">http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440">https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440</a></p>

<p><a href="http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/">http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/</a></p>

<h2>Talks</h2>

<p>Here are my notes on the talks that I had a chance to see.  In lieu of writing anything up, I&rsquo;ll post them here for now.</p>

<h3>Overall themes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Meaning over randomness</li>
<li>Scale and direction

<ul>
<li>Layering</li>
<li>Deck metaphor really nice for prototyping.</li>
<li>Great question, how do you make sure the player is not lost in
this huge history.  Player only aware of history of own house,
data is gathered by reading books etc.; there&rsquo;s some context for
the entrance of new bits of history.  Books are populated in
places where it makes sense for them to turn up.</li>
<li>Top-down (designer first) is easier than bottom-up (player first;
shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/gillianmsmith">@gillianmsmith</a> for this formulation).  Callbacks?
How to percolate up from lower elements on tree?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Storytelling as divination</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dariusk/NaNoGenMo">NaNoGenMo</a></li>
<li>Flow in procedural generation

<ul>
<li>Meaning, codifying design principlse</li>
<li><a href="http://artofgamedesign.com/">Art of Game Design by Jesse Schell</a></li>
<li>a feeling of complete and energized focus in an activity, with a
high level of enjoyment and fulfillment

<ul>
<li>clear goals</li>
<li>no distractions

<ul>
<li>How does this figure into open world distraction fests like
triple a sandbox games?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>feedback</li>
<li>continuously challenging</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Frustration vs. boredom, find a balance</li>
<li>Dynamic

<ul>
<li>Scale enemy level to meet player&rsquo;s level</li>
<li>AI director, see when the player is overwhelmed, drop difficulty;
boredom spawn more enemies.  Requires some kind of metric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Static

<ul>
<li>Lock and key</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tcoxon/metazelda">Metazelda</a> calculates difficulty number for each room from desired flow curve.</li>
<li>Love <a href="https://github.com/tcoxon">@tcoxon</a> &rsquo;s thoughts on less backtracking.  Algorithmically respecting players' time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/ToniSala/20131208/206535/Game_Design_Theory_Applied_The_Flow_Channel.php">Gamasutra Toni Sala</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Emotion and interactivity &#x2013; expressivity

<ul>
<li>Workflow, ease of adjustment can be good for designer and exposing
the same tools to the player can be fun</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>itch.io</h2>

<p>It looks like most of the entries are gathered on a <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam itch.io page</a>.  I have no experience with <a href="http://itch.io/">itch.io</a>, but I think setting up an account and exploring what itch.io has to offer couldn&rsquo;t hurt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Tap Quest: a pachinko RPG]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/16/one-tap-quest-a-pachinko-rpg/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-16T10:39:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/16/one-tap-quest-a-pachinko-rpg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently played <em><a href="http://shimage.net/one-tap-quest/">One Tap Quest</a></em>, a game in which you tap to place an RPG character who marches upward, gaining levels by bumping into enemies, to tackle bigger and badder foes.  What&rsquo;s interesting to me, if you&rsquo;ll bear with me, is that this is a game that amounts to a pachinko RPG.  I&rsquo;ll start by talking about what I liked about <em>One Tap Quest</em>.  <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/23/designing-a-pachinko-rpg/">Next week</a>, I&rsquo;ll get into what I mean by a pachinko RPG.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s rare that I come to a new gameplay experience completely naive these days. The only way I feel I can effectively spend my time with a game is typically after having read some sort of guide because my time is extremely limited.</p>

<p>What the <em>One Tap Quest</em> accomplished so well for me was going from barely being able to read the screen to beating the game over the course of 10 minutes.  Admittedly it&rsquo;s a very short and simple game.  But I felt a sense of accomplishment every time my understanding of the mechanics grew.</p>

<p>Oh, these little critters are stronger than these other little critters, better avoid them.  Oh these are power ups, not critters, better aim for them.  With these skills under my belt it only took a little luck to send my character on a march toward victory.</p>

<p>The place where this idea shines is in the power-ups.  I&rsquo;m not sure whether I&rsquo;ve encountered all of them, but they range from simple buffs that grant free levels to expanding your party into a 3-character-wide enemy-wrecking plow.  For what it&rsquo;s worth, the power-ups were deep enough to keep me interested over 10 minutes of gameplay.  If I were going to engage with this experience over a longer term, I would suggest adding more depth to the power-ups and the enemies, which are as far as I can tell simply harder to kill, and possibly bigger, versions of the puny slimes that move back and forth.  Some of the enemies have variations on the simple random walk style movement of the slimes, but a richer variety of movement and behavior from the enemies would increase the required skill to play the game, and add to replayability.</p>

<p>I think the power-up mechanics add a level of depth and strategy to what otherwise would be a hands-off luck-of-the-draw game.  By aiming for power-ups you have a sense of agency in the action, just like turning the knob controls the velocity at which pachinko balls are launched.  It makes cheering for your lemming-like character(s) more enjoyable: if they could just get a little closer and grab the power-up you aimed at&mdash;no.  Nope, they died.</p>

<p>Go give this great little game a try.  Hopefully it will pique your interest like it piqued mine.  Quirky variations on RPGs seem to be part of the <em>Zeitgeist</em>, with <em><a href="http://www.atlus.com/rollers/">Rollers of the Realm</a></em> and <em><a href="http://zh.monst.wikia.com/wiki/Monster_Strike_%E7%BB%B4%E5%9F%BA">Monster Strike</a></em> blending pinball and console genre gameplay with the potential synergy <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonic_the_Hedgehog_Spinball">Sonic Spinball</a></em> never achieved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Space Is Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-26T11:08:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The cinematically inspired <a href="http://tdlk.itch.io/space-is-red">Space Is Red</a> is not so much a game as it is a visual novel.  Out of the games I tried from the <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">#spacecowboygamejam</a>, it&rsquo;s one that sticks with me.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>On the spectrum of play, these sorts of games are loosely analogous to Choose Your Own Adventure books.  Just as a Choose Your Own Adventure book expects the player to turn to a given page according to the rules laid out at the bottom of the pages to proceed in a consistent, logical fashion, the tropes of a visual novel require the player to interact with the game in order for the story to proceed.  A novel will proceed with the only &lsquo;player&rsquo; interaction consisting of turning to the next page.  I&rsquo;m oversimplifying the difference between <em>real choices</em>, as I would argue, Choose Your Own Adventure Books allow, and <em>mere interactivity</em>, like turning the page of a novel, but you get what I mean.</p>

<p>Visual novels can have real choices and interactivity.  In this case, I&rsquo;d argue that Space Is Red is only interactive.  There are no real choices, short of figuring out the next bit to tap on in order to move the story along.  For me, it&rsquo;s the music that makes the experience gel as something more than an animated e-book.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to be presumptuous in my analysis of Space Is Red&rsquo;s gameplay, don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  I&rsquo;m not interested in arguments about merit simply based on A <strong>is</strong> a game but B <strong>isn&rsquo;t</strong>, so A is better.  I just think it&rsquo;s important to think about these sorts of things when considering the underlying design.</p>

<p>I left the game looping <a href="https://soundcloud.com/postpre">PostPre</a>&rsquo;s driving soundtrack for 15 minutes, even though my first play-through lasted only 2 or 3.  Maybe that&rsquo;s the benefit of interactivity and choices, to extend and prolong the mindshare of some experience or product with the player.  I don&rsquo;t necessarily mean that in a cynical way, although the typical model of play can be subverted for more manipulative means (and, of course, it is!).</p>

<p>For me, Space Is Red hit all the right notes and left me with something to think about.  That is what I call a successful gamejam game.  You can see Space Is Red and the other #spacecowboygamejam entries <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">here</a>.  If you&rsquo;re interested in learning more about Space Is Red&rsquo;s creator <a href="http://toddluke.com/">Todd Luke</a>, you can find an interview <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/TalhaKaya/20140711/220825/Finding_Beauty_in_Imperfection_Interview_with_Todd_Luke.php">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
