<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: game | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-27T09:29:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile Frame Football Association]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/mobile-frame-football-association/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-18T11:35:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/mobile-frame-football-association</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Inspiration</h2>

<p>I asked myself the question, in a universe where mecha are used for primarily for military-industrial applications, how did the technology
get to that point?</p>

<p>Sure, some routes for technical advancement are funded purely by governments, but think of the racing sport&rsquo;s influence on the
automobile industry.</p>

<p>So I asked the question, what if mecha became a dominant technology because of sports applications?</p>

<p>In which kind of sports could mecha thrive?  There have previously been pugilistic representations of robots, but I deemed these as too
costly and too on the nose for the future military application.</p>

<p>Likewise, pure racing, while plausible, seemed to be ground that had
already been explored.</p>

<p>I settled on the possibility that the military-industrial applications mecha technology and piloting ability of the Mobile Frame Zero universe grew out of a pursuit of the world&rsquo;s (universe&rsquo;s?) most popular sport, (Association) Football a.k.a. Soccer.</p>

<p>Thus, the Mobile Frame Football Association, a rules mod for <a href="https://twitter.com/JoshuaACNewman">Joshua AC Newman&rsquo;s</a> <a href="http://mobileframezero.com/mfz/">Mobile Frame Zero</a>, was born.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Football games</h2>

<h3>Duration of play</h3>

<p>Mobile Frame Football Association (MFFA) sanctioned games last 6 turns, consisting of two equal 3-turn halves.  MFFA rules do not allow for the countdown mechanic from the vanilla Mobile Frame Zero (MF0) rules.</p>

<h3>Objective</h3>

<p>When time expires, the player with the highest number of goals scored wins.</p>

<h3>Teams</h3>

<p>Games are played between teams consisting of equal numbers of frames.  Frames may have up to 4 systems installed, with the usual vanilla MF0 benefits for fewer than 4 installed systems (see, e.g., MF0 p. 64).  For more explanation see <em>Dice Systems</em>.</p>

<h3>Field of Play</h3>

<p>The game field should be approximately the size of a normal MF0 table, with goals the size of 1 <em>movement scale</em> on each end of the field.  Lines should be laid out to clearly mark the in bounds/out of bounds boundary.  There should be at least 1" of space on the sidelines, to allow for units to be positioned outside of the field during out of bounds situations.</p>

<p>The size of your available Field of Play can dictate the Movement and Shooting Scales for your game.  The suggested defaults are based on a normal MF0 table, your mileage may vary.</p>

<h2>Deployment</h2>

<p>During the deployment phase, you may place your units anywhere on the field in a legal formation.  Cool your servos, I&rsquo;ll describe the legal formations in just a sec.</p>

<h3>Beginning of play</h3>

<p>At the beginning of the game, at the beginning of the second half, or at a kickoff following a goal, players take turns placing units in bounds, in the half of the field that has been assigned (See: Determining possession).  The player in possession of the ball, the <em>offensive player</em>, goes first.  The ball, represented by a d12, is placed at the center of the field. The offensive player must place a unit next to the ball, this unit is in possession of the ball.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Maintaining possession of the ball</p>

<p>A unit possesses the ball if the ball is in contact with its base (i.e. its legs).  If two opposing units are in contact with the ball the unit in possession of the ball first maintains possession unless the opposing unit steals or tackles.  Similarly if two units on the same side are in contact with the ball, the unit in possession of the ball first maintains possession unless it passes successfully to the second unit.</p></li>
<li><p>Determining possession at kickoff</p>

<p>A coin flip determines possession at the beginning of the game, with the winning player electing to be on offense or defense first.  The losing player gets to determine the side of the field in which to deploy.</p>

<p>At the half, the possession and sides switch.  Following a scored goal, the player who was scored on gains possession of the ball at the kickoff.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>After a dead ball situation</h3>

<p>Play is stopped due to a foul, an out of bounds ball. This is called a <em>dead ball</em> situation.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Out of bounds</p>

<p>Out of bounds balls force a turnover of possession. The ball is placed on the sideline where it went out of bounds.</p>

<p>Both players may redeploy their units, however the offensive player may not place a unit beyond the defensive unit closest to the goal.  The defensive player places first, and must move the unit closest to the goal first, if it will be moved in the redeployment.  Players alternate placing units.  The offensive player must place a unit next to the ball.</p>

<p>After the offensive player redeploys the last unit, play resumes with the unit next to the ball immediately taking its turn, regardless of its initiative roll.  If the unit next to the ball has an initiative die, remove it.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Corner Kicks and Goal Kicks</p>

<p>Corner kicks occur when a defending unit kicks the ball out of bounds on the sideline running on its own &lsquo;goal&rsquo; side of the field.  The ball is placed on the corner sideline on the side it went out of bounds.</p>

<p>Goal kicks occur when an offensive unit kicks the ball out of bounds on the sideline of the defensive units' &lsquo;goal&rsquo; side of the field.  The ball is placed in front of the goal.</p></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p>Fouls</p>

<p>Fouls do not force a turnover of possession.  Redeployment following a foul occurs the same as in the Out of bounds situation.</p></li>
<li><p>Redeployment and units that have already taken turns</p>

<p>Redeployment does not normally reset whether a unit has taken its turn.  If the unit placed next to the ball in a dead ball situation has already taken its turn, it gets a free turn taken immediately following deployment, when play resumes.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Initiative</h2>

<p>For the time being, MFFA uses the older per-unit turn order from MF0 (p. 136).  Enough with the hutching bellyaching, you yabbies.</p>

<p>Players roll 1d10 for each unit, placing the die next to the unit.  Initiative starts at 1 and counts up.  When you reach a unit&rsquo;s initiative roll in the count, remove the initiative die next to the unit, that unit takes its turn.</p>

<p>If two units have the same roll, when their number is reached, reroll the initiative dice. Lowest roll goes first with the next highest reroll going immediately after.  Once all of the rerolled ties have been resolved, the initiative count continues as normal.</p>

<p>In a dead ball situation, the initiative count does not reset.</p>

<h3>Coaching</h3>

<p>Coaching adds a layer of complexity to initiative determination.  It may slow down the game a bit, but it allows for extra tactical decisions.</p>

<p>Coaching allows players to take control of the assignment of initiative to each of their units.  Both players roll a number of initiative dice equal to their units, then take turns assigning to initiative dice to their units. The defensive player chooses first.  After initiatives are assigned, the initiative count starts and counts up as normal.</p>

<h2>Dice systems</h2>

<p>As in MF0, frames have 2 white dice representing the frame chassis plus other dice representing up to 4 additional systems.  Frames get the usual vanilla MF0 benefits for having fewer than 4 installed systems (see, e.g., MF0 p. 64).</p>

<h3>Red dice</h3>

<p>Red dice represent the ability of a frame to shoot or pass the ball on offense.  Unlike the vanilla MF0 rules, there are two legal ranges for red dice on offense: direct and artillery.  Systems granting hand to hand dice are not rolled on offense.</p>

<p>When shooting, you must score a successful hit on the goal using the difficulty table from MF0 to score a goal.  When passing you must score a successful hit on your ally to successfully pass the ball. You must declare the range you will be targeting at the beginning of your turn.</p>

<p>On defense, red dice represent steals (hand to hand range) and slide tackles (direct range).  Systems granting artillery dice are not rolled on defense.</p>

<p>Red dice use a special scale that is different from the movement scale.  See Movement Scale and Shooting Scale</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Passing and shooting</p>

<p>When in range for a shot or a pass, the player must roll a number of <em>hit dice</em> equal to the <em>shot value</em> minus the blue <em>defense value</em> of any units in the line of fire.  Any units in the line of the pass or shot act as cover, using the normal MF0 cover rules.  If there is doubt, consult the MF0 cover rules to determine if a unit is in the line of fire.</p>

<p>If the rolled hit dice successfully <em>score a hit</em>, then the ball goes where the offensive player wants, into the goal or into the possession of another unit.  Use Damage chart 2 from the MF0 rules (Hit target on a 5 or 6) if there is no other unit between the shooter and the target.  Use Damage chart 4 if there is a unit between the shooter and the target. (Hit target on a 6)</p>

<p>Failure to score a hit is called a <em>fumble</em>, and causes the ball to go wide somewhere in the range of the shot at the opposing player&rsquo;s discretion (be reasonable here, it&rsquo;s not going to <em>fly backwards</em>).  This may cause the ball to go out of bounds, into the possession of a unit, into the goal, or into the field of play.</p></li>
<li><p>Stealing and slide tackling</p>

<p>When stealing or slide tackling, <em>scoring a hit</em> results in the ball coming into the stealing or tackling unit&rsquo;s possession.  The stealing or tackling unit&rsquo;s player rolls a number of <em>hit dice</em> equal to its red <em>shot value</em> for the steal or tackle attack minus the blue <em>defense value</em> of the unit in possession of the ball.</p>

<p>Always use Damage chart 2 for stealing and slide tackling. On a roll of 5 or 6, the steal or slide tackle scores a hit.  Possible rule: the player who slide tackles to steal the ball may choose to destroy a system on the opposing player&rsquo;s unit.</p>

<p>Failure to score a hit is a <em>fumble</em>.  Nothing special happens, unless the player rolls a 1 on one of the hit dice.</p>

<p>Rolling a 1 on a hit die during a fumble results in a foul.  See <em>Fouls</em>.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Blue Dice</h3>

<p>Blue dice systems remain the same as blue dice systems in the normal MF0 rules.  However, rather than representing armor, they represent the ability of a unit to gain or maintain control of the ball.</p>

<h3>Yellow Dice and Green Dice</h3>

<p>Yellow and green dice systems remain the same as vanilla MF0.</p>

<h3>Hot rodding</h3>

<p>A player may choose to hotrod a unit&rsquo;s system by sacrificing a system to gain a free action with one of the other systems after the unit has taken its turn.</p>

<h2>Taking a turn</h2>

<p>Taking a turn begins with target declaration.  For the defensive units this will generally be the unit in possession of the ball.  For the offensive unit in possession of the ball, this could be targeting a fellow offensive unit for a pass or targeting the opposing goal.</p>

<p>Attacks don&rsquo;t do anything to units without the ball.  Save that animosity for the war.</p>

<p>The turn proceeds as per the vanilla MF0 rules. Any unit that would be activated with the normal MF0 turn rules, i.e. the target of a steal attempt or a pass, takes its turn as per those rules.</p>

<p>For example: If a unit equipped with a blue system is in the line of fire and has not rolled to determine the blue <em>defense value</em> this turn, defending player must declare a target for the unit, roll all of the unit&rsquo;s dice, and assign a <em>defense value</em>.  The unit takes its turn as normal when its initiative dictates.</p>

<h2>Movement Scale and Shooting Scale</h2>

<p>Normal vanilla MF0 scale is 2".  <em>Shooting scale</em> for MFFA is 2".  <em>Movement scale</em> is double that, 4", to represent the agility of these hot-rodded sportsframes.</p>

<p>Using two different colored rulers (e.g., 1 red for shooting and 1 green for movement) is a good way to distinguish <em>movement scale</em> and <em>shooting scale</em>.</p>

<h2>Licensing note</h2>

<p>This rules expansion for Mobile Frame Zero is made in accordance to the Creative Commons, Non-commercial, Share-Alike license of the original game.</p>

<h2>Playtesting</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in playtesting these rules go for it.  I&rsquo;d love to hear suggestions and reports here in the comments or on <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-27T09:28:58-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An introductory FATE Accelerated Edition (FAE) adventure in the spirit
of Ghostbusters International</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>Dramatis Personae</h1>

<h2>The Library Supervisor</h2>

<p>Has a problem the players need to solve</p>

<h2>The Librarian</h2>

<p>+2 to Poltergeistery, Attacking people with overdue books
-2 to Yelling, doing anything outside of the library</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Summoner</h2>

<p>Andrea Runyon, daughter of Poke Runyon, high priestess of Astarte</p>

<h2>Rock Lions</h2>

<p>+2 to growling
-2 to acid rain</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bat Books</h2>

<p>+2 to flapping around
-2 to preventing combustion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<p>None (first hit takes them out)</p>

<h2>The Lieutenants</h2>

<p>The players will encounter these if the pacing feels a little fast
when they approach the summoning circle in the basement.  Be careful,
because the lieutenants are tough.</p>

<p>First lieutenants of Bael&rsquo;s legion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Clan'thael</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Clancy&rdquo;
Second Lieutenant of the 23rd Legion of Spirits under Bael&rsquo;s rule</p>

<p>+2 to Slurping, phasing between walls
-2 to resisting hunger</p>

<p>Cross between a toad and Slimer.</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h1>At the shop</h1>

<p>Introduce the characters, awarding fate points / discovering aspects
about the setting as appropriate.</p>

<h1>Call to action</h1>

<p>The players get a call to investigate a disturbance at the Library.
The Library Supervisor has ordered the library evacuated because
patrons have reported a ghostly apparition.</p>

<p>The Library Supervisor says</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to help us.  There&rsquo;s no one else to call.  It was horrible.
Books were flying everywhere.  One patron was knocked out.  And those
cries from the office, &lsquo;Overdue&#x2026;. Overdue&#x2026;&rsquo;  They sounded so
menacing&#x2026; I didn&rsquo;t even get my briefcase before evacuating everyone.</p></blockquote>

<h1>Arriving at the library</h1>

<p>Two statues of lions at the front steps of the library come alive.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the players arrive at the library:</p>

<blockquote><p>You pull up at the entrance to the library. Tall marble columns cap
the staircase leading to the door. At the foot of the staircase sit
two marble statues.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players approach the entrance, the statues come to life.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the statues come to life</p>

<blockquote><p>You hear cracking and scraping as the lion statues come to life,
stepping down from their pedestals with a graceful thud. The lions
mouths open as if giving mighty roars but no sounds escape the
statues' throats.</p></blockquote>

<h1>First floor</h1>

<h2>The circulation desk</h2>

<p>The desk is full of books. In closer inspection each book has been
marked overdue. The desk also has overdue stamps all over it as well
as if someone went completely wild stamping everything in sight.</p>

<h2>The office</h2>

<p>Read the following flavor text when the players enter the office</p>

<blockquote><p>The walls are lined with books.  There is a desk with a large office
chair on the far side of the room.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players haven&rsquo;t encountered the Librarian, read this flavor
text</p>

<blockquote><p>The office chair is facing away from the doorway.  It slowly turns
around revealing the wrinkle-creased face of the Librarian.  In an
instant the Librarian&rsquo;s face morphs into a ghastly visage.  You feel
wind blowing as if the Librarian is sucking the energy from the room.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Capturing the Librarian</h3>

<h2>The Stacks</h2>

<p>The library has been evacuated.</p>

<p>If the players don&rsquo;t wander over to the stacks, the characters start
to hear books dropping.  That should entice the players to explore the
stacks.</p>

<p>When the characters arrive, they are attacked by book bats.  If the
pacing feels too fast, increase the challenge by having more books
turn into book bats.</p>

<h3>Book bats</h3>

<h1>The Basement</h1>

<h2>Stairway</h2>

<p>One of the characters becomes paralyzed by a hidden magical circle on
the staircase.  The character who gets paralyzed is left up to the
GM&rsquo;s discretion.</p>

<p>This is a trap set by the Summoner to act as a sort of alarm, alerting
the Summoner to approaching people who may intrude on the summoning.
When the trap is triggered, the Summoner gives up on the invocation
and flees the library.</p>

<p>Read the following flavor text as the characters descend the stairs.</p>

<blockquote><p>As you descend the staircase your limbs grow heavier.  It&rsquo;s as if
you&rsquo;re walking through mud.  Your eyes grow wide as your feet stick to
the floor and your arms freeze.</p></blockquote>

<p>Characters looking for traps on the staircase may notice some markings
on the stairs, but the magical circle that is the source of the
paralysis spell is only visible when you stand on it, ensuring that
the trap will be sprung.</p>

<p>The other characters may attempt to free the paralyzed character by
using some knowledge of the paranormal.</p>

<p>The characters will be released after the Summoner has fled the
Library because the Summoner is no longer able to maintain the spell.</p>

<h2>Hallway</h2>

<h3>Encounter with partially summoned ghost</h3>

<p>The partially summoned ghost slimes the first player, retreating into
the walls of the hallway. As the players move on the spirit comes out
again clinging to the slimes player. The spirit blabbers and cries,
begging for help. The spirit is lost and will be unable to survive if
left alone.</p>

<p>The spirit will become incorporeal if left too long without a human
anchor to reality.  Clancy is on the run from two other lieutenants of
Bael&rsquo;s legion. The lieutenants will kill any malformed spirit and
promote one of their vassals to fill Clancys position</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy then they encounter the lieutenants. If
they do not believe Clancy then it turns out that the spirit was Lying
and then they proceed directly to the summoning circle.</p>

<p>After sliming a character, and clinging to the character, the
partially summoned ghost will reach into any threatening character&rsquo;s
body and pull out a fate token.</p>

<blockquote><p>The toad-like spirit mutters something about being nicer to it.  It
reaches out toward your chest.  To your surprise its hand goes into
your body.  You feel a strange sensation as it pulls out a shining bit
of your energy.  You lose a fate token.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Summoning Circle</h2>

<h3>The interrupted summoning</h3>

<p>Read this flavor text when the characters arrive in the summoning
circle room</p>

<blockquote><p>There is a circle of salt on the ground here.  In the middle you can
see strange symbols that look like they were hastily brushed away,
leaving behind streaks of salt.  The far side of the circle is broken
by footprints heading toward the library&rsquo;s loading dock.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the characters search around they find small amounts of earth, wax,
primrose, and jasmine.  These are elements the summoner was using.
The characters may know purveyors of these items in town.</p>

<p>If the players have befriended Clancy, the partially summoned spirit,
Clancy can make out that the faded symbols are the marking of the
spirit&rsquo;s King, Bael.</p>

<p>The next adventure may involve tracking down where these items come
from, in order to track down the summoner.</p>

<h1>Denouement</h1>

<h2>Character advancement</h2>

<p>If the players capture the Librarian they may gain one minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players gain any information about the summoner the characers
who uncovered the information gain an additional minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy, the player who first encountered
Clancy gets to add Clancy as a free stunt.  This is a significant
milestone.  The player does not have to pay any refresh points, if the
player already has 3 stunts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventurejam reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T13:51:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some of my thoughts on my favorite entries to <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> so far.  Voting ends in a little over two weeks.  So, I&rsquo;m not ruling out the possibility of looking at more games.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/ree-s-ruined-earth-courier-service-shipment-delayed/60572">Ree&rsquo;s Ruined Earth Courier Service: Shipment Delayed</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Amazing graphics.</li>
<li>Loving the dialogue.</li>
<li>I played the Unity version.</li>
</ul>


<p>I find the story, characters, and world-building totally compelling.</p>

<p>Unfortunately interacting with the world is proving difficult.  I could use some indication of when I can walk offscreen.  I think that could help with some pathfinding issues.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d really like to see more work done on this game, and I&rsquo;d like to see more content in the Ree&rsquo;s universe.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/the-endless-night-prelude/58725">The Endless Night</a></h2>

<p>For as much as I wanted to play this game, I couldn&rsquo;t.  The platform restrictions kept me from trying this interesting looking game.  I think the graphics for this game look pretty cool.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/speak-of-the-cloud/60613">Speak of the Cloud</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Sound effects do a good job of situating the experience in a world.</li>
<li>Loving the <em>Dr. Strangelove</em> allusions.</li>
<li>Character animations are impressive, and jive well with the cartoon art style.</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, I couldn&rsquo;t play this game as much as I would have liked.  It&rsquo;s compelling, and the art design really sells intriguing, interactive spaces that make up for the ridiculous pixel-hunting puzzle I encountered.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/walkman/60724">Walkman</a></h2>

<p>Like the animation and the constraint of linear movement.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/cascade/58292">Cascade</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Got chills from this one.</li>
<li>The sparse sound does a great job of communicating atmosphere.</li>
<li>Got the sense that there was more to this game than there actually was (in a good way), I think due to the writing.</li>
</ul>


<p>Nice scoping for a two-week game jam.  I think this is my runner-up, based on the strength of its story.</p>

<h2><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Therapods</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Great art, animation.</li>
<li>Loving the parallax and layering.</li>
<li>Great sound design.</li>
<li>Great overall design, love the inventory and interface.</li>
<li>Great examples of one-screen puzzles.  The puzzles that I&rsquo;ve heard Tim Schafer call donkey and rider puzzles.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Theropods</em> is my favorite game of the jam.  Not only did it scope the game correctly for the development team, it was also playable in a reasonable amount of time.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>So there you have it, go out there and try some of these games.  If you only have time to try one, check out <em><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Theropods</a></em>.  It&rsquo;s groovy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-25T10:31:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Join me as I look back on my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game, <em><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738">Aurion and the Aurochs</a></em>.  You can take a <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">look at the game</a> over on <a href="http://gamejolt.com">gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the sourcecode here</a>.  You can see all of the entries at <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">adventurejam&rsquo;s site</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to look at things that worked, things that didn&rsquo;t, and the lessons I&rsquo;ll take with me moving forward.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What Worked?</h2>

<h3>Pre-planning</h3>

<p>I sketched out the plot using <a href="http://www.lamemage.com/microscope/">Microscope</a> to define events, locations, and potential actions and routes the player could take through the game.  Microscope&rsquo;s 3"x5" index card format made it easy to move ideas around when they weren&rsquo;t working.  And it made it easy to see the overall flow of the game.</p>

<p>Once I got the plot Microscope&rsquo;d to my liking, I transferred it to the <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#microscope">project&rsquo;s readme</a>, using checkmarks and crosses to represent the filled and unfilled circles of Microscope.  Please note, that there be spoilers, so <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">go play the game</a> if you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>

<p>While I wasn&rsquo;t using the circles in the typical way that Microscope proposes, it did help me visualize the potential routes for &ldquo;good&rdquo; and &ldquo;bad&rdquo; alternate endings.</p>

<h3>Twine macros</h3>

<p>I used some <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#created-using-artisanal-macros-from">Twine macros</a> for the first time in this game.  I can see how they add some impressive functionality to Twine.</p>

<p>I reckon, if I find the right macros, I would save a ton of time implementing functionality that has already been better implemented as drop-in macros.</p>

<h2>What Didn&rsquo;t Work?</h2>

<h3>Scope</h3>

<p>I set out to create what I thought at the time would be a relatively simple adventure game.  However, I failed to appreciate the combinatorial proliferation of states that blossomed out as I added more and more items and interactions.</p>

<h3>Timeframe and Pacing</h3>

<p>I found the rigid format of the gamejam to be oppressive and stressful.</p>

<h3>Prose</h3>

<p>Because I was so focused on implementing the game I wanted in the time I had, I feel that the initial creative spark that drove me to design <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> wasn&rsquo;t allowed to grow into the creative prose flamethrower that I wanted to torch raw palceholder text into a fine <em>crème brûlée</em>.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t force that <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">hammock-driven imagination</a>, especially when I feel crunched for time.</p>

<h2>What Will I Improve Next Time?</h2>

<h3>Plotting</h3>

<p>I will definitely continue to use Microscope for brainstorming and outlining plots.  It could be fun to collaborate with multiple people on this process, as Microscope is meant to be a multiplayer experience.</p>

<p>It may be worthwhile to write-up the &ldquo;single-player&rdquo; approach I used for Microscope brainstorming.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also be interested in trying out Tim Schafer&rsquo;s freewriting technique that I came across in the <a href="http://adventure.doublefine.com/">Double Fine Adventure documentaries</a>.  This probably merits its own post in the future.</p>

<h3>Scope and Pacing</h3>

<p>I will think hard about whether I should participate in gamejams with such strict time requirements for submissions.  I refuse to compromise on work and life commitments to participate in what should be a fun, creative hobby.</p>

<p>I feel emotionally and creatively drained from adventurejam, and I&rsquo;d prefer to have steady, fulfilling creative output.</p>

<p>I think the <em>laissez-faire</em> format of <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/make-things-that-make-things-number-procjam-2014/">#procjam</a> was healthier.  I should also note that, although I submitted more things to procjam, the scope of each of those projects was much smaller than my project for #adventurejam.</p>

<p>I think I could have compromised on delivering what was a more or less finished game.  I could have submitted a more prototype-y version that I could work on later.  In fact, I may still refine the prose of <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> if I feel so inclined in the future.</p>

<p>That being said, I&rsquo;m happy with the game I was able to deliver in the constraints of the jam.</p>

<h3>Investigate the Twine macro ecosystem</h3>

<p>Maybe in a future post, I&rsquo;ll look into some of the macros out there.  It&rsquo;d be useful to write simple example code too.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Well, that&rsquo;s it.  I have some good perspective going forward.  In the coming weeks, I&rsquo;m going to look at some of my favorite submissions and finalize my votes for the contest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs is out]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T12:43:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m happy to announce that my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game is finished and released.  I&rsquo;ll do a more in-depth post-mortem next week.  In the coming weeks, before the 30-day voting deadline ends, I want to take a look at some of the <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">other submissions</a> that pique my interest.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">play <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> on gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the source on github</a>.  Please leave me some feedback in the comments here or on twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">@zerosalife</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
