<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: game | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-22T14:33:25-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[procjam comedown]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T14:26:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that two weeks have passed (a geologic era in internet time), I&rsquo;m ready begin to look back on the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a> talks and the entries to the jam that caught my eye.  I&rsquo;ve been very busy lately working on my own submissions <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/">INSceptahdeckwu</a> and <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/patchwerk/">Patchwerk</a>, among other commitments, so this is by no means an exhaustive look at everything in #procjam.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Since I actually have no time at all to write a full retrospective, I&rsquo;ll have to be brief.  This post will have to serve as a collection of links and notes until I get a chance to look back in detail.  It&rsquo;s by no means complete, as I&rsquo;m still looking over all of the great entries to #procjam.  I enjoyed the interactions with the speakers and participants.  Unfortunately other commitments may occupy my time through the end of the year, so don&rsquo;t worry if the blogging is intermittent.  I&rsquo;ll revisit the #procjam talks and the submissions when I find time.</p>

<h2>Great ideas</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824">https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992">https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113">https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1">https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992">https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992</a></p>

<p><a href="http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/">http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js">https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js</a></p>

<p><a href="http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/">http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input">https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input</a></p>

<p><a href="http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner">http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen">https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen</a></p>

<p><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen</a></p>

<h2>Good tutorials</h2>

<p>Some tutorials I came across during the jam:</p>

<p><a href="http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started?utm_content%3Dbuffera3b27&amp;utm_medium%3Dsocial&amp;utm_source%3Dtwitter.com&amp;utm_campaign%3Dbuffer">&lt;http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started?utm_content=buffera3b27&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer></a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440">https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440</a></p>

<p><a href="http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/">http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/</a></p>

<h2>Talks</h2>

<p>Here are my notes on the talks that I had a chance to see.  In lieu of writing anything up, I&rsquo;ll post them here for now.</p>

<h3>Overall themes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Meaning over randomness</li>
<li>Scale and direction

<ul>
<li>Layering</li>
<li>Deck metaphor really nice for prototyping.</li>
<li>Great question, how do you make sure the player is not lost in
this huge history.  Player only aware of history of own house,
data is gathered by reading books etc.; there&rsquo;s some context for
the entrance of new bits of history.  Books are populated in
places where it makes sense for them to turn up.</li>
<li>Top-down (designer first) is easier than bottom-up (player first;
shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/gillianmsmith">@gillianmsmith</a> for this formulation).  Callbacks?
How to percolate up from lower elements on tree?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Storytelling as divination</li>
<li>NanoGenMo</li>
<li>Flow in procedural generation

<ul>
<li>Meaning, codifying design principlse</li>
<li>Art of Game Design by Jesse Schell</li>
<li>a feeling of complete and energized focus in an activity, with a
high level of enjoyment and fulfillment

<ul>
<li>clear goals</li>
<li>no distractions

<ul>
<li>How does this figure into open world distraction fests like
triple a sandbox games?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>feedback</li>
<li>continuously challenging</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Frustration vs. boredom, find a balance</li>
<li>Dynamic

<ul>
<li>Scale enemy level to meet player&rsquo;s level</li>
<li>AI director, see when the player is overwhelmed, drop difficulty;
boredom spawn more enemies.  Requires some kind of metric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Static

<ul>
<li>Lock and key</li>
<li>Metazelda calculates difficulty number for each room from
desired flow curve.</li>
<li>Love <a href="https://github.com/tcoxon">@tcoxon</a> &rsquo;s thoughts on less backtracking.  Algorithmically respecting players' time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Gamasutra Toni Sala</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Emotion and interactivity &#x2013; expressivity

<ul>
<li>Workflow, ease of adjustment can be good for designer and exposing
the same tools to the player can be fun</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>itch.io</h2>

<p>It looks like most of the entries are gathered on a <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam itch.io page</a>.  I have no experience with <a href="http://itch.io/">itch.io</a>, but I think setting up an account and exploring what itch.io has to offer couldn&rsquo;t hurt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Tap Quest: a pachinko RPG]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/16/one-tap-quest-a-pachinko-rpg/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-16T11:39:34-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/16/one-tap-quest-a-pachinko-rpg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently played <em><a href="http://shimage.net/one-tap-quest/">One Tap Quest</a></em>, a game in which you tap to place an RPG character who marches upward, gaining levels by bumping into enemies, to tackle bigger and badder foes.  What&rsquo;s interesting to me, if you&rsquo;ll bear with me, is that this is a game that amounts to a pachinko RPG.  I&rsquo;ll start by talking about what I liked about <em>One Tap Quest</em>.  <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/08/23/designing-a-pachinko-rpg/">Next week</a>, I&rsquo;ll get into what I mean by a pachinko RPG.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s rare that I come to a new gameplay experience completely naive these days. The only way I feel I can effectively spend my time with a game is typically after having read some sort of guide because my time is extremely limited.</p>

<p>What the <em>One Tap Quest</em> accomplished so well for me was going from barely being able to read the screen to beating the game over the course of 10 minutes.  Admittedly it&rsquo;s a very short and simple game.  But I felt a sense of accomplishment every time my understanding of the mechanics grew.</p>

<p>Oh, these little critters are stronger than these other little critters, better avoid them.  Oh these are power ups, not critters, better aim for them.  With these skills under my belt it only took a little luck to send my character on a march toward victory.</p>

<p>The place where this idea shines is in the power-ups.  I&rsquo;m not sure whether I&rsquo;ve encountered all of them, but they range from simple buffs that grant free levels to expanding your party into a 3-character-wide enemy-wrecking plow.  For what it&rsquo;s worth, the power-ups were deep enough to keep me interested over 10 minutes of gameplay.  If I were going to engage with this experience over a longer term, I would suggest adding more depth to the power-ups and the enemies, which are as far as I can tell simply harder to kill, and possibly bigger, versions of the puny slimes that move back and forth.  Some of the enemies have variations on the simple random walk style movement of the slimes, but a richer variety of movement and behavior from the enemies would increase the required skill to play the game, and add to replayability.</p>

<p>I think the power-up mechanics add a level of depth and strategy to what otherwise would be a hands-off luck-of-the-draw game.  By aiming for power-ups you have a sense of agency in the action, just like turning the knob controls the velocity at which pachinko balls are launched.  It makes cheering for your lemming-like character(s) more enjoyable: if they could just get a little closer and grab the power-up you aimed at&mdash;no.  Nope, they died.</p>

<p>Go give this great little game a try.  Hopefully it will pique your interest like it piqued mine.  Quirky variations on RPGs seem to be part of the <em>Zeitgeist</em>, with <em><a href="http://www.atlus.com/rollers/">Rollers of the Realm</a></em> and <em><a href="http://zh.monst.wikia.com/wiki/Monster_Strike_%E7%BB%B4%E5%9F%BA">Monster Strike</a></em> blending pinball and console genre gameplay with the potential synergy <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonic_the_Hedgehog_Spinball">Sonic Spinball</a></em> never achieved.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Space Is Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-26T12:08:44-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/07/26/space-is-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The cinematically inspired <a href="http://tdlk.itch.io/space-is-red">Space Is Red</a> is not so much a game as it is a visual novel.  Out of the games I tried from the <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">#spacecowboygamejam</a>, it&rsquo;s one that sticks with me.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>On the spectrum of play, these sorts of games are loosely analogous to Choose Your Own Adventure books.  Just as a Choose Your Own Adventure book expects the player to turn to a given page according to the rules laid out at the bottom of the pages to proceed in a consistent, logical fashion, the tropes of a visual novel require the player to interact with the game in order for the story to proceed.  A novel will proceed with the only &lsquo;player&rsquo; interaction consisting of turning to the next page.  I&rsquo;m oversimplifying the difference between <em>real choices</em>, as I would argue, Choose Your Own Adventure Books allow, and <em>mere interactivity</em>, like turning the page of a novel, but you get what I mean.</p>

<p>Visual novels can have real choices and interactivity.  In this case, I&rsquo;d argue that Space Is Red is only interactive.  There are no real choices, short of figuring out the next bit to tap on in order to move the story along.  For me, it&rsquo;s the music that makes the experience gel as something more than an animated e-book.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t mean to be presumptuous in my analysis of Space Is Red&rsquo;s gameplay, don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  I&rsquo;m not interested in arguments about merit simply based on A <strong>is</strong> a game but B <strong>isn&rsquo;t</strong>, so A is better.  I just think it&rsquo;s important to think about these sorts of things when considering the underlying design.</p>

<p>I left the game looping <a href="https://soundcloud.com/postpre">PostPre</a>&rsquo;s driving soundtrack for 15 minutes, even though my first play-through lasted only 2 or 3.  Maybe that&rsquo;s the benefit of interactivity and choices, to extend and prolong the mindshare of some experience or product with the player.  I don&rsquo;t necessarily mean that in a cynical way, although the typical model of play can be subverted for more manipulative means (and, of course, it is!).</p>

<p>For me, Space Is Red hit all the right notes and left me with something to think about.  That is what I call a successful gamejam game.  You can see Space Is Red and the other #spacecowboygamejam entries <a href="http://itch.io/jam/space-cowboy-jam">here</a>.  If you&rsquo;re interested in learning more about Space Is Red&rsquo;s creator <a href="http://toddluke.com/">Todd Luke</a>, you can find an interview <a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/TalhaKaya/20140711/220825/Finding_Beauty_in_Imperfection_Interview_with_Todd_Luke.php">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[styx_ebooks]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-19T15:05:03-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And now for something completely different: a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain#Markov_text_generators">markov chain text generation</a> twitter bot.  Styx_ebooks tweets random text generated from a corpus of Bangsian fantasy novels.  Its name comes from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Kendrick_Bangs">John Kendrick Bangs</a>&lsquo; novel <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_House-Boat_on_the_Styx">A House-boat on the Styx</a></em> and the general <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/horse_ebooks">twitter ebooks meme</a>.</p>

<p>I forked it from an earlier project by <a href="https://github.com/jiko">@jiko</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jiko/lovecraft_ebooks">lovecraft_ebooks</a>.  There were some minor implementation hurdles, mainly related to Twitter&rsquo;s API and oauth.  Reading the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/twitter">python <code>twitter</code> package</a> <code>twitter.oauth</code> docstring set me straight.  You can check out the code in <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/styx_ebooks">my fork on github</a>.</p>

<p>This sort of text generation algorithm isn&rsquo;t just useful for making annoying twitter bots.  You could alter some of the in-game text or dialog based on a corpus fed into a markov chain text generator. Especially in the case of a Lovecraftian horror game, I can see how this text could serve a thematic purpose in the story.</p>

<p>Say you&rsquo;ve got a Lovecraftian horror game in which the player is an investigator who is trying to figure out what is happening to citizens of Innsmouth.  By interacting with NPCs, the player encounters hand written dialog, with occasional markov-generated gibberish thrown in. The amount of gibberish depends on how corrupted the individual denizens of Innsmouth are becoming.  If the player is not clever enough to determine who is corrupt, the player will be killed.  If the player determines the source of the corruption, the player wins.</p>

<p>Along the same line of reasoning, the concept I&rsquo;m describing here mimics the game <a href="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/634905">ALZ</a>, a touching short, playable in 2 or 3 minutes, which uses glitchy graphics to convey a sense of what it&rsquo;s like to live with Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease to the player.  I came across Dylan Carter&rsquo;s ALZ in a <a href="http://www.animalnewyork.com/2014/making-alz-glitch-fueled-game-alzheimers/">post on the ANIMAL blog</a>.  This approach of literally altering the player&rsquo;s experience of the game world to mimic the subjective experience of characters in the game is ripe for exploration.  I&rsquo;d love to hear about more examples.</p>

<p>You can check out my bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>, on twitter, happily tweeting the day away.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Twine Tutorial in Twine]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/03/29/a-twine-tutorial-in-twine/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-29T11:04:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/03/29/a-twine-tutorial-in-twine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ryanscasey.com/">Ryan S. Casey</a> incepted a Twine tutorial in a Twine game.  Awesome.  Take a look at it <a href="http://ryanscasey.com/twine/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
