<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: game | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-27T09:44:05-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Library]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-27T09:28:58-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2016/02/27/the-library</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An introductory FATE Accelerated Edition (FAE) adventure in the spirit
of Ghostbusters International</p>

<!--more-->


<h1>Dramatis Personae</h1>

<h2>The Library Supervisor</h2>

<p>Has a problem the players need to solve</p>

<h2>The Librarian</h2>

<p>+2 to Poltergeistery, Attacking people with overdue books
-2 to Yelling, doing anything outside of the library</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>The Summoner</h2>

<p>Andrea Runyon, daughter of Poke Runyon, high priestess of Astarte</p>

<h2>Rock Lions</h2>

<p>+2 to growling
-2 to acid rain</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Bat Books</h2>

<p>+2 to flapping around
-2 to preventing combustion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<p>None (first hit takes them out)</p>

<h2>The Lieutenants</h2>

<p>The players will encounter these if the pacing feels a little fast
when they approach the summoning circle in the basement.  Be careful,
because the lieutenants are tough.</p>

<p>First lieutenants of Bael&rsquo;s legion</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h2>Clan'thael</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Clancy&rdquo;
Second Lieutenant of the 23rd Legion of Spirits under Bael&rsquo;s rule</p>

<p>+2 to Slurping, phasing between walls
-2 to resisting hunger</p>

<p>Cross between a toad and Slimer.</p>

<h3>Stress</h3>

<ul>
<li>[ ]</li>
<li>[ ]</li>
</ul>


<h1>At the shop</h1>

<p>Introduce the characters, awarding fate points / discovering aspects
about the setting as appropriate.</p>

<h1>Call to action</h1>

<p>The players get a call to investigate a disturbance at the Library.
The Library Supervisor has ordered the library evacuated because
patrons have reported a ghostly apparition.</p>

<p>The Library Supervisor says</p>

<blockquote><p>You have to help us.  There&rsquo;s no one else to call.  It was horrible.
Books were flying everywhere.  One patron was knocked out.  And those
cries from the office, &lsquo;Overdue&#x2026;. Overdue&#x2026;&rsquo;  They sounded so
menacing&#x2026; I didn&rsquo;t even get my briefcase before evacuating everyone.</p></blockquote>

<h1>Arriving at the library</h1>

<p>Two statues of lions at the front steps of the library come alive.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the players arrive at the library:</p>

<blockquote><p>You pull up at the entrance to the library. Tall marble columns cap
the staircase leading to the door. At the foot of the staircase sit
two marble statues.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players approach the entrance, the statues come to life.</p>

<p>Read the following text when the statues come to life</p>

<blockquote><p>You hear cracking and scraping as the lion statues come to life,
stepping down from their pedestals with a graceful thud. The lions
mouths open as if giving mighty roars but no sounds escape the
statues' throats.</p></blockquote>

<h1>First floor</h1>

<h2>The circulation desk</h2>

<p>The desk is full of books. In closer inspection each book has been
marked overdue. The desk also has overdue stamps all over it as well
as if someone went completely wild stamping everything in sight.</p>

<h2>The office</h2>

<p>Read the following flavor text when the players enter the office</p>

<blockquote><p>The walls are lined with books.  There is a desk with a large office
chair on the far side of the room.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the players haven&rsquo;t encountered the Librarian, read this flavor
text</p>

<blockquote><p>The office chair is facing away from the doorway.  It slowly turns
around revealing the wrinkle-creased face of the Librarian.  In an
instant the Librarian&rsquo;s face morphs into a ghastly visage.  You feel
wind blowing as if the Librarian is sucking the energy from the room.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Capturing the Librarian</h3>

<h2>The Stacks</h2>

<p>The library has been evacuated.</p>

<p>If the players don&rsquo;t wander over to the stacks, the characters start
to hear books dropping.  That should entice the players to explore the
stacks.</p>

<p>When the characters arrive, they are attacked by book bats.  If the
pacing feels too fast, increase the challenge by having more books
turn into book bats.</p>

<h3>Book bats</h3>

<h1>The Basement</h1>

<h2>Stairway</h2>

<p>One of the characters becomes paralyzed by a hidden magical circle on
the staircase.  The character who gets paralyzed is left up to the
GM&rsquo;s discretion.</p>

<p>This is a trap set by the Summoner to act as a sort of alarm, alerting
the Summoner to approaching people who may intrude on the summoning.
When the trap is triggered, the Summoner gives up on the invocation
and flees the library.</p>

<p>Read the following flavor text as the characters descend the stairs.</p>

<blockquote><p>As you descend the staircase your limbs grow heavier.  It&rsquo;s as if
you&rsquo;re walking through mud.  Your eyes grow wide as your feet stick to
the floor and your arms freeze.</p></blockquote>

<p>Characters looking for traps on the staircase may notice some markings
on the stairs, but the magical circle that is the source of the
paralysis spell is only visible when you stand on it, ensuring that
the trap will be sprung.</p>

<p>The other characters may attempt to free the paralyzed character by
using some knowledge of the paranormal.</p>

<p>The characters will be released after the Summoner has fled the
Library because the Summoner is no longer able to maintain the spell.</p>

<h2>Hallway</h2>

<h3>Encounter with partially summoned ghost</h3>

<p>The partially summoned ghost slimes the first player, retreating into
the walls of the hallway. As the players move on the spirit comes out
again clinging to the slimes player. The spirit blabbers and cries,
begging for help. The spirit is lost and will be unable to survive if
left alone.</p>

<p>The spirit will become incorporeal if left too long without a human
anchor to reality.  Clancy is on the run from two other lieutenants of
Bael&rsquo;s legion. The lieutenants will kill any malformed spirit and
promote one of their vassals to fill Clancys position</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy then they encounter the lieutenants. If
they do not believe Clancy then it turns out that the spirit was Lying
and then they proceed directly to the summoning circle.</p>

<p>After sliming a character, and clinging to the character, the
partially summoned ghost will reach into any threatening character&rsquo;s
body and pull out a fate token.</p>

<blockquote><p>The toad-like spirit mutters something about being nicer to it.  It
reaches out toward your chest.  To your surprise its hand goes into
your body.  You feel a strange sensation as it pulls out a shining bit
of your energy.  You lose a fate token.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Summoning Circle</h2>

<h3>The interrupted summoning</h3>

<p>Read this flavor text when the characters arrive in the summoning
circle room</p>

<blockquote><p>There is a circle of salt on the ground here.  In the middle you can
see strange symbols that look like they were hastily brushed away,
leaving behind streaks of salt.  The far side of the circle is broken
by footprints heading toward the library&rsquo;s loading dock.</p></blockquote>

<p>If the characters search around they find small amounts of earth, wax,
primrose, and jasmine.  These are elements the summoner was using.
The characters may know purveyors of these items in town.</p>

<p>If the players have befriended Clancy, the partially summoned spirit,
Clancy can make out that the faded symbols are the marking of the
spirit&rsquo;s King, Bael.</p>

<p>The next adventure may involve tracking down where these items come
from, in order to track down the summoner.</p>

<h1>Denouement</h1>

<h2>Character advancement</h2>

<p>If the players capture the Librarian they may gain one minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players gain any information about the summoner the characers
who uncovered the information gain an additional minor milestone</p>

<p>If the players befriend Clancy, the player who first encountered
Clancy gets to add Clancy as a free stunt.  This is a significant
milestone.  The player does not have to pay any refresh points, if the
player already has 3 stunts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventurejam reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T13:51:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some of my thoughts on my favorite entries to <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> so far.  Voting ends in a little over two weeks.  So, I&rsquo;m not ruling out the possibility of looking at more games.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/ree-s-ruined-earth-courier-service-shipment-delayed/60572">Ree&rsquo;s Ruined Earth Courier Service: Shipment Delayed</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Amazing graphics.</li>
<li>Loving the dialogue.</li>
<li>I played the Unity version.</li>
</ul>


<p>I find the story, characters, and world-building totally compelling.</p>

<p>Unfortunately interacting with the world is proving difficult.  I could use some indication of when I can walk offscreen.  I think that could help with some pathfinding issues.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d really like to see more work done on this game, and I&rsquo;d like to see more content in the Ree&rsquo;s universe.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/the-endless-night-prelude/58725">The Endless Night</a></h2>

<p>For as much as I wanted to play this game, I couldn&rsquo;t.  The platform restrictions kept me from trying this interesting looking game.  I think the graphics for this game look pretty cool.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/speak-of-the-cloud/60613">Speak of the Cloud</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Sound effects do a good job of situating the experience in a world.</li>
<li>Loving the <em>Dr. Strangelove</em> allusions.</li>
<li>Character animations are impressive, and jive well with the cartoon art style.</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, I couldn&rsquo;t play this game as much as I would have liked.  It&rsquo;s compelling, and the art design really sells intriguing, interactive spaces that make up for the ridiculous pixel-hunting puzzle I encountered.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/walkman/60724">Walkman</a></h2>

<p>Like the animation and the constraint of linear movement.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/cascade/58292">Cascade</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Got chills from this one.</li>
<li>The sparse sound does a great job of communicating atmosphere.</li>
<li>Got the sense that there was more to this game than there actually was (in a good way), I think due to the writing.</li>
</ul>


<p>Nice scoping for a two-week game jam.  I think this is my runner-up, based on the strength of its story.</p>

<h2><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Therapods</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Great art, animation.</li>
<li>Loving the parallax and layering.</li>
<li>Great sound design.</li>
<li>Great overall design, love the inventory and interface.</li>
<li>Great examples of one-screen puzzles.  The puzzles that I&rsquo;ve heard Tim Schafer call donkey and rider puzzles.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Theropods</em> is my favorite game of the jam.  Not only did it scope the game correctly for the development team, it was also playable in a reasonable amount of time.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>So there you have it, go out there and try some of these games.  If you only have time to try one, check out <em><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Theropods</a></em>.  It&rsquo;s groovy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-25T10:31:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Join me as I look back on my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game, <em><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738">Aurion and the Aurochs</a></em>.  You can take a <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">look at the game</a> over on <a href="http://gamejolt.com">gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the sourcecode here</a>.  You can see all of the entries at <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">adventurejam&rsquo;s site</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to look at things that worked, things that didn&rsquo;t, and the lessons I&rsquo;ll take with me moving forward.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What Worked?</h2>

<h3>Pre-planning</h3>

<p>I sketched out the plot using <a href="http://www.lamemage.com/microscope/">Microscope</a> to define events, locations, and potential actions and routes the player could take through the game.  Microscope&rsquo;s 3"x5" index card format made it easy to move ideas around when they weren&rsquo;t working.  And it made it easy to see the overall flow of the game.</p>

<p>Once I got the plot Microscope&rsquo;d to my liking, I transferred it to the <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#microscope">project&rsquo;s readme</a>, using checkmarks and crosses to represent the filled and unfilled circles of Microscope.  Please note, that there be spoilers, so <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">go play the game</a> if you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>

<p>While I wasn&rsquo;t using the circles in the typical way that Microscope proposes, it did help me visualize the potential routes for &ldquo;good&rdquo; and &ldquo;bad&rdquo; alternate endings.</p>

<h3>Twine macros</h3>

<p>I used some <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#created-using-artisanal-macros-from">Twine macros</a> for the first time in this game.  I can see how they add some impressive functionality to Twine.</p>

<p>I reckon, if I find the right macros, I would save a ton of time implementing functionality that has already been better implemented as drop-in macros.</p>

<h2>What Didn&rsquo;t Work?</h2>

<h3>Scope</h3>

<p>I set out to create what I thought at the time would be a relatively simple adventure game.  However, I failed to appreciate the combinatorial proliferation of states that blossomed out as I added more and more items and interactions.</p>

<h3>Timeframe and Pacing</h3>

<p>I found the rigid format of the gamejam to be oppressive and stressful.</p>

<h3>Prose</h3>

<p>Because I was so focused on implementing the game I wanted in the time I had, I feel that the initial creative spark that drove me to design <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> wasn&rsquo;t allowed to grow into the creative prose flamethrower that I wanted to torch raw palceholder text into a fine <em>crème brûlée</em>.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t force that <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">hammock-driven imagination</a>, especially when I feel crunched for time.</p>

<h2>What Will I Improve Next Time?</h2>

<h3>Plotting</h3>

<p>I will definitely continue to use Microscope for brainstorming and outlining plots.  It could be fun to collaborate with multiple people on this process, as Microscope is meant to be a multiplayer experience.</p>

<p>It may be worthwhile to write-up the &ldquo;single-player&rdquo; approach I used for Microscope brainstorming.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also be interested in trying out Tim Schafer&rsquo;s freewriting technique that I came across in the <a href="http://adventure.doublefine.com/">Double Fine Adventure documentaries</a>.  This probably merits its own post in the future.</p>

<h3>Scope and Pacing</h3>

<p>I will think hard about whether I should participate in gamejams with such strict time requirements for submissions.  I refuse to compromise on work and life commitments to participate in what should be a fun, creative hobby.</p>

<p>I feel emotionally and creatively drained from adventurejam, and I&rsquo;d prefer to have steady, fulfilling creative output.</p>

<p>I think the <em>laissez-faire</em> format of <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/make-things-that-make-things-number-procjam-2014/">#procjam</a> was healthier.  I should also note that, although I submitted more things to procjam, the scope of each of those projects was much smaller than my project for #adventurejam.</p>

<p>I think I could have compromised on delivering what was a more or less finished game.  I could have submitted a more prototype-y version that I could work on later.  In fact, I may still refine the prose of <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> if I feel so inclined in the future.</p>

<p>That being said, I&rsquo;m happy with the game I was able to deliver in the constraints of the jam.</p>

<h3>Investigate the Twine macro ecosystem</h3>

<p>Maybe in a future post, I&rsquo;ll look into some of the macros out there.  It&rsquo;d be useful to write simple example code too.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Well, that&rsquo;s it.  I have some good perspective going forward.  In the coming weeks, I&rsquo;m going to look at some of my favorite submissions and finalize my votes for the contest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs is out]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T12:43:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m happy to announce that my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game is finished and released.  I&rsquo;ll do a more in-depth post-mortem next week.  In the coming weeks, before the 30-day voting deadline ends, I want to take a look at some of the <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">other submissions</a> that pique my interest.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">play <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> on gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the source on github</a>.  Please leave me some feedback in the comments here or on twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">@zerosalife</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math Team Hearts]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-14T14:14:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Math Team Hearts is a speedy modification to Hearts that ironically involves less math than the vanilla game.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From <a href="http://www.crcpress.com/product/isbn/9781482217162">Game Design Workshop</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/kinojabber">Tracy Fullerton</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>One good way to train yourself in the design of game mechanics is to challenge yourself with controlled design exercises in which you take an existing game system, set a new player experience goal, and make changes to the system to meet that goal.</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Goal</h2>

<p>We needed a game that played quickly, without a defined endpoint (e.g. when one player reaches 100 points in normal <em>Hearts</em>) because this game was played in free time waiting for school to start or waiting for the bus.  There was no time to spend tallying up scores, counting hearts and doing awkward math.</p>

<p>The rules also modify the risk-reward value of shooting the moon to make it more attractive.  We found the game to be more interesting when multiple parties were invested in shooting the moon with less drawback from accumulating hearts.</p>

<h2>The Rules</h2>

<p>The game plays like normal <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hearts">Hearts</a></em>, except taking <strong>hearts</strong> no longer gives you points.</p>

<ul>
<li>Taking any number of <strong>hearts</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you 0 points.</li>
<li>Taking no <strong>hearts</strong> in a round gives you 1 point.</li>
<li><strong>Shooting the moon</strong> gives you 2 points.</li>
<li>Taking the <strong>queen of spades</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you -1 point.</li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>player</strong> with the most points at the end of play wins.</p>

<p>For more variety, use <strong>dealer</strong>&rsquo;s choice drafting rules.  Each round, the <strong>dealer</strong> decides on how players will pass cards prior to play.
<strong>Players</strong> take turns dealing.</p>

<h2>Tweaks</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m working from memory, so I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve got the point values exactly right.  Perhaps there should be more of a penalty for taking the Queen without shooting the moon.  That would create a more exciting risk-reward trade-off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
