<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: game | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/game/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-11T08:43:00-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math Team Hearts]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-14T14:14:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/14/math-team-hearts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Math Team Hearts is a speedy modification to Hearts that ironically involves less math than the vanilla game.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>From <a href="http://www.crcpress.com/product/isbn/9781482217162">Game Design Workshop</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/kinojabber">Tracy Fullerton</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>One good way to train yourself in the design of game mechanics is to challenge yourself with controlled design exercises in which you take an existing game system, set a new player experience goal, and make changes to the system to meet that goal.</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Goal</h2>

<p>We needed a game that played quickly, without a defined endpoint (e.g. when one player reaches 100 points in normal <em>Hearts</em>) because this game was played in free time waiting for school to start or waiting for the bus.  There was no time to spend tallying up scores, counting hearts and doing awkward math.</p>

<p>The rules also modify the risk-reward value of shooting the moon to make it more attractive.  We found the game to be more interesting when multiple parties were invested in shooting the moon with less drawback from accumulating hearts.</p>

<h2>The Rules</h2>

<p>The game plays like normal <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hearts">Hearts</a></em>, except taking <strong>hearts</strong> no longer gives you points.</p>

<ul>
<li>Taking any number of <strong>hearts</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you 0 points.</li>
<li>Taking no <strong>hearts</strong> in a round gives you 1 point.</li>
<li><strong>Shooting the moon</strong> gives you 2 points.</li>
<li>Taking the <strong>queen of spades</strong> without <strong>shooting the moon</strong> gives you -1 point.</li>
</ul>


<p>The <strong>player</strong> with the most points at the end of play wins.</p>

<p>For more variety, use <strong>dealer</strong>&rsquo;s choice drafting rules.  Each round, the <strong>dealer</strong> decides on how players will pass cards prior to play.
<strong>Players</strong> take turns dealing.</p>

<h2>Tweaks</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m working from memory, so I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;ve got the point values exactly right.  Perhaps there should be more of a penalty for taking the Queen without shooting the moon.  That would create a more exciting risk-reward trade-off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WuXingRPS: Elemental Rock Paper Scissors]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/02/28/wuxingrps-elemental-rock-paper-scissors/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-28T10:13:28-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/02/28/wuxingrps-elemental-rock-paper-scissors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/assets/WuXing-screenshot.png"></p>

<p><a href="http://zerosalife.itch.io/wuxingrps">WuXingRPS</a> is a prototype 5-way rock paper scissors game.  The eventual purpose for the prototype is to serve as a minigame to teach elemental interactions in an RPG battle system.</p>

<p>I chose WuXing elements because they provide a nontraditional (in terms of typical RPGs) series of interesting interactions.</p>

<h2>The Five Elements</h2>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/assets/WuXing-interactions.png"></p>

<p>The five elements are Earth (yellow), Metal (silver), Water (black), Wood (green), and Fire (red).  They have two levels of interactions that you can look at anytime by pressing the <code>?</code> button in the bottom right corner.</p>

<p>The <strong>Destruction</strong> interaction, indicated by red arrows, shows that, for example, Metal chops Wood.  So Metal beats Wood.</p>

<p>The <strong>Generation</strong> interaction shows that, for example, Water grows Wood.  So Wood &ldquo;eats&rdquo; Water.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all there is to it.  Click those element disks and try to get more points than the computer.</p>

<h2>Surprise: iteration to find mechanics</h2>

<p>In an earlier version of the prototype the player and enemy choices that resulted in a generation relationship interaction led to a draw.  This meant that 3/5 interactions were draws.  The prototype was less exciting than the current version.  This iteration was critical in achieving a sense of fun in this prototype, as well as fleshing out the goals of an eventual RPG battle system using the elemental mechanic.</p>

<p>So making this prototype led to unexpected value.  Let that be a lesson to keep it simple, because <em>sometimes the simple things that are achievable within your current skillset can lead to surprising results</em>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m really interested in feedback, so <a href="http://zerosalife.itch.io/wuxingrps">give the game a try</a> and tell me what you think in the comments or on <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.  If you&rsquo;re an artist interested in gussying up my shameful attempts at UI and UX, please please please reach out to me.  I&rsquo;d love to improve this prototype.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A proper review of DUNGEN [Star]]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:44:36-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My green fingers sweat on the handle of my pistol as I creep through the door, into the next room.  I found two boxes of ammunition in the previous room so I&rsquo;m well equipped for the next horrible monster I encounter.  My grip on the pistol tightens as a horrible three-legged spherical thing jumps down from the ceiling, pirouetting to land on its feet and shooting a stream of acidic liquid at me.</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Oof,&rdquo; is all I manage to get out, as I feel the Burster&rsquo;s fluid eat into my skin.  Without thinking I fire at it, killing the thing in two shots.</em></p>

<p><em>While reloading my pistol, I notice a glowing jewel on the stone.  If it&rsquo;s what the briefings said, this is the teleport stone that will allow me to phase out of our normal reality just long enough to escape the next deadly monster I encounter in</em> DUNGEN [Star].</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"><img class="center" src="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"></a></p>

<p>(Please excuse my lame attempt at illustrating play with a .gif).</p>

<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/">Last week, I posted an overview of my favorite #procjam games</a>.  I felt remissed when I got a tweet from the designer, asking whether I had actually printed and played the game.  I hadn&rsquo;t and neither had any of the other reviewers who praised it.  So, this week I took some time to cut out the cards on my computer, effectively making a print-and-play game I could play in Illustrator without bothering to print it out.</p>

<p>After the initial time investment, <em><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN [Star]</a></em>, a print-and-play game designed by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@JctWood</a> for the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/paperjam">#paperjam</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/7dfps">#7dfps</a> gamejams, plays quickly.  Especially if you are brave enough to choose the roguelike secret difficulty level of starting with 1HP.  Add to that, the advanced enemy rules, which give the monsters more personality on top of their already evocative illustrations and you&rsquo;ve got a challenging game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of the cartoonish art style of <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>.  The character design does a good job of communicating interesting variety, even though there are few monsters to go up against.</p>

<p><em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> runs out of steam quickly, but I think the intent behind it is clear.  This game does a good job of bringing the feel of a procedural first-person shooter with roguelike elements to the print-and-play market.  I think extending the combat to involve multiple weapons would add some depth to the game.  I would like to see more enemies, particularly ones with more interesting advanced enemy rules.  I&rsquo;d also like to see an overarching goal or theme tying together <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>&rsquo;s dungeoning and star, so you feel more satisfied when you survive the dungeon.  With that criticism said, I still think <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> succeeds as a gamejam game and a great prototype from which to build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Procjam review]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T09:33:47-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking through the entries, I could only spend a minute or two with each entry.  It helped if the game ran in my browser, so HTML and Unity were big.  Here are some of the games that caught my eye.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The top two</h2>

<h2>JET/LAG</h2>

<p>Simple instructions: &ldquo;Click to move. Kill enemies by bashing them.&rdquo;  There may be little to <em><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a></em>, but its excellent stylish visuals set this entry apart for me.  A CRT-like distortion bends the corners of the screen complete with scrolling scan lines, while multi-colored text oscillates above a simple square.  The simple square is your character battering your way through procedurally generated maze-like levels.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no fancy art in this game, all the characters are made from simple shapes.  But that doesn&rsquo;t stop the graphics from impressing.  It&rsquo;s clear that <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> turned the juice up to 11, and it works.  The game feels great.</p>

<p>As a &ldquo;rogue-like like like&rdquo; you may expect it to be deviously hard, and you&rsquo;d be right.  But the controls are responsive and the enemies telegraph their moves, so you feel like you are learning something with each death.  <a href="https://twitter.com/JakeCataford">@JakeCataford</a> clearly understands some fundamentals of engaging game design and I&rsquo;m excited to see what&rsquo;s coming up next.</p>

<h2>DUNGEN [star]</h2>

<p>A multi-jam entry for <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam</a>, <a href="http://itch.io/jam/paper-jam-1">#paperjam</a>, and <a href="http://7dfps.com/">#7dfps</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a>, this first person shooter uses shuffling to generate a dynamic dungeon with each play-through.  I like the simplicity of the mechanics <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@jctwood</a> has designed.  Stats on a 1-10 scale can be just as interesting as stats in the thousands.  There are even multiple skin options for the protagonist&rsquo;s hand.  That&rsquo;s more advanced than all three <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_%2528series%2529">DOOM</a></em>s.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;m most interested in the literal realization of the procedural generation algorithm.  By shuffling the cards the procedural generation of the dungeon is clear both to designer and player, and this type of randomization has been used for many years in many games with standard and nonstandard sets of cards.  I&rsquo;m interested in seeing how this shuffling mechanic, both literal and metaphorical, can be leveraged to encourage new avenues of play in the future.  I can imagine tuning some aspects of a proc gen algorithm by exposing the contents to the player as a deck of cards, both literally as is typical in CCGs and other tabletop games and as a metaphor for abstraction of systems in a video game.</p>

<h2>Favorite games</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://svblm.itch.io/jet-lag">JET/LAG</a>

<ul>
<li>Bump or get bumped.  Excellent style and great graphics.  Very
juicy!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://lissar.itch.io/peregrin">Peregrin</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://entropyphi.itch.io/nauticalith">Nauticalith</a>

<ul>
<li>Simple, but really conveys a sense of scale.  Adding some mechanic
like dynamic wind that affects sailing could put this over the
top.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tfurmanskigmailcom.itch.io/forska-web-version">Forska</a>

<ul>
<li>Great shader.  Generate some <em><a href="http://wikipedia.com/wiki/Myst">Myst</a></em>-like puzzles and you&rsquo;ve got a game, here.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://8-bit-ape.itch.io/infinity-explorer">Infinity Explorer</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_Carpet_%28video_game%29">Magic Carpet</a></em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN star</a>

<ul>
<li>Print and play games are great.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Favorite generators</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer">http://nihilocrat.itch.io/nodemancer</a>

<ul>
<li>Interesting.  Will have to look more into it.  Now that I think
about it, this one deserves an honorable mention for favorite tool
of the jam.  I will revisit it in depth in a later post because the
generation algorithm looks like an idea I&rsquo;ve batted around in my
head.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/">http://diaspora-colonies.herokuapp.com/</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful and cool!  Check out <a href="http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora">http://ptychomancer.itch.io/diaspora</a>
for some more background on this space colony generator.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics">http://eduardo.itch.io/procedural-fabrics</a>

<ul>
<li>Clever tiling textures using diagonal lines that really break up
the patterns to make it more pleasing to the eye.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters">http://ibol17.itch.io/procedural-pixel-monsters</a>

<ul>
<li>Artistic style.  Simple color palette still allow for a variety of
expressive monsters. Interested in following up on the
procedural tree generation–looks great!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia">https://github.com/cutgarnetgames/gaia</a>

<ul>
<li>Beautiful world generator with some source code worth digging
into.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla">http://gillianms.itch.io/hoopla</a>

<ul>
<li>Really think there&rsquo;s something to explore in pixels-as-stitches
graphics.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch">http://aerique.itch.io/rocks-bitch</a>

<ul>
<li>The pet rock generator I always wanted!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator">http://playcrafts.itch.io/palette-generator</a>

<ul>
<li>Useful.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer">http://tccoxon.itch.io/dreamer</a>

<ul>
<li>Weird hybrid between an AI and a text adventure, but very
  creative and very cool.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026">http://itch.io/jam/procjam/rate/14026</a>

<ul>
<li>Great concept, but I need remedial lessons or a tutorial.  One to
revisit when I can really dig into it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Cool looking Windows games I couldn&rsquo;t play</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist">http://crabowitz.itch.io/key-geist</a>

<ul>
<li>Reminds me of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wonderful_101">Wonderful 101</a></em>–a game I haven&rsquo;t played, but probably should.  Something about the aesthetic of dozens of little flocking characters appeals to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://caseportman.itch.io/riser">http://caseportman.itch.io/riser</a>

<ul>
<li>Looks like it controls well</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[procjam comedown]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T13:26:16-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/22/procjam-comedown</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that two weeks have passed (a geologic era in internet time), I&rsquo;m ready begin to look back on the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a> talks and the entries to the jam that caught my eye.  I&rsquo;ve been very busy lately working on my own submissions <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/">INSceptahdeckwu</a> and <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/patchwerk/">Patchwerk</a>, among other commitments, so this is by no means an exhaustive look at everything in #procjam.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Since I actually have no time at all to write a full retrospective, I&rsquo;ll have to be brief.  This post will have to serve as a collection of links and notes until I get a chance to look back in detail.  It&rsquo;s by no means complete, as I&rsquo;m still looking over all of the great entries to #procjam.  I enjoyed the interactions with the speakers and participants.  Unfortunately other commitments may occupy my time through the end of the year, so don&rsquo;t worry if the blogging is intermittent.  I&rsquo;ll revisit the #procjam talks and the submissions when I find time.</p>

<h2>Great ideas</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824">https://twitter.com/PNJeffries/status/531592288733261824</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992">https://twitter.com/redblobgames/status/527485845616340992</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113">https://twitter.com/mtthwcmpbll/status/527881936178778113</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1">https://twitter.com/DragonXVI/status/531078933161476096/photo/1</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992">https://twitter.com/TomNullpointer/status/531108417096916992</a></p>

<p><a href="http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/">http://chrismwaite.github.io/procjam/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js">https://github.com/chrismwaite/procjam/blob/gh-pages/app.js</a></p>

<p><a href="http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/">http://renderingpipeline.com/2013/01/adding-analog-inputs-to-your-graphics-app/</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input">https://github.com/keijiro/unity-midi-input</a></p>

<p><a href="http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner">http://cgaudino.itch.io/tailgunner</a></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen">https://github.com/civilframe/node-spacegame-ship-gen</a></p>

<p><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen</a></p>

<h2>Good tutorials</h2>

<p>Some tutorials I came across during the jam:</p>

<p><a href="http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started">http://procjam.tumblr.com/post/99689402659/procedural-generation-tutorials-getting-started</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440">https://twitter.com/alexjc/status/531077005815869440</a></p>

<p><a href="http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/">http://samatkins.co.uk/blog/2014/11/08/procjam-procedural-building-generation/</a></p>

<h2>Talks</h2>

<p>Here are my notes on the talks that I had a chance to see.  In lieu of writing anything up, I&rsquo;ll post them here for now.</p>

<h3>Overall themes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Meaning over randomness</li>
<li>Scale and direction

<ul>
<li>Layering</li>
<li>Deck metaphor really nice for prototyping.</li>
<li>Great question, how do you make sure the player is not lost in
this huge history.  Player only aware of history of own house,
data is gathered by reading books etc.; there&rsquo;s some context for
the entrance of new bits of history.  Books are populated in
places where it makes sense for them to turn up.</li>
<li>Top-down (designer first) is easier than bottom-up (player first;
shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/gillianmsmith">@gillianmsmith</a> for this formulation).  Callbacks?
How to percolate up from lower elements on tree?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Storytelling as divination</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dariusk/NaNoGenMo">NaNoGenMo</a></li>
<li>Flow in procedural generation

<ul>
<li>Meaning, codifying design principlse</li>
<li><a href="http://artofgamedesign.com/">Art of Game Design by Jesse Schell</a></li>
<li>a feeling of complete and energized focus in an activity, with a
high level of enjoyment and fulfillment

<ul>
<li>clear goals</li>
<li>no distractions

<ul>
<li>How does this figure into open world distraction fests like
triple a sandbox games?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>feedback</li>
<li>continuously challenging</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Frustration vs. boredom, find a balance</li>
<li>Dynamic

<ul>
<li>Scale enemy level to meet player&rsquo;s level</li>
<li>AI director, see when the player is overwhelmed, drop difficulty;
boredom spawn more enemies.  Requires some kind of metric</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Static

<ul>
<li>Lock and key</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tcoxon/metazelda">Metazelda</a> calculates difficulty number for each room from desired flow curve.</li>
<li>Love <a href="https://github.com/tcoxon">@tcoxon</a> &rsquo;s thoughts on less backtracking.  Algorithmically respecting players' time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="http://www.gamasutra.com/blogs/ToniSala/20131208/206535/Game_Design_Theory_Applied_The_Flow_Channel.php">Gamasutra Toni Sala</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Emotion and interactivity &#x2013; expressivity

<ul>
<li>Workflow, ease of adjustment can be good for designer and exposing
the same tools to the player can be fun</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>itch.io</h2>

<p>It looks like most of the entries are gathered on a <a href="http://itch.io/jam/procjam">#procjam itch.io page</a>.  I have no experience with <a href="http://itch.io/">itch.io</a>, but I think setting up an account and exploring what itch.io has to offer couldn&rsquo;t hurt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
