<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: adventurejam | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/adventurejam/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-30T12:11:56-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adventurejam reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-02T13:51:55-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/05/02/adventurejam-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some of my thoughts on my favorite entries to <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> so far.  Voting ends in a little over two weeks.  So, I&rsquo;m not ruling out the possibility of looking at more games.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/ree-s-ruined-earth-courier-service-shipment-delayed/60572">Ree&rsquo;s Ruined Earth Courier Service: Shipment Delayed</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Amazing graphics.</li>
<li>Loving the dialogue.</li>
<li>I played the Unity version.</li>
</ul>


<p>I find the story, characters, and world-building totally compelling.</p>

<p>Unfortunately interacting with the world is proving difficult.  I could use some indication of when I can walk offscreen.  I think that could help with some pathfinding issues.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d really like to see more work done on this game, and I&rsquo;d like to see more content in the Ree&rsquo;s universe.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/the-endless-night-prelude/58725">The Endless Night</a></h2>

<p>For as much as I wanted to play this game, I couldn&rsquo;t.  The platform restrictions kept me from trying this interesting looking game.  I think the graphics for this game look pretty cool.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/speak-of-the-cloud/60613">Speak of the Cloud</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Sound effects do a good job of situating the experience in a world.</li>
<li>Loving the <em>Dr. Strangelove</em> allusions.</li>
<li>Character animations are impressive, and jive well with the cartoon art style.</li>
</ul>


<p>Unfortunately, I couldn&rsquo;t play this game as much as I would have liked.  It&rsquo;s compelling, and the art design really sells intriguing, interactive spaces that make up for the ridiculous pixel-hunting puzzle I encountered.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/walkman/60724">Walkman</a></h2>

<p>Like the animation and the constraint of linear movement.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/cascade/58292">Cascade</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Got chills from this one.</li>
<li>The sparse sound does a great job of communicating atmosphere.</li>
<li>Got the sense that there was more to this game than there actually was (in a good way), I think due to the writing.</li>
</ul>


<p>Nice scoping for a two-week game jam.  I think this is my runner-up, based on the strength of its story.</p>

<h2><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Therapods</a></h2>

<ul>
<li>Great art, animation.</li>
<li>Loving the parallax and layering.</li>
<li>Great sound design.</li>
<li>Great overall design, love the inventory and interface.</li>
<li>Great examples of one-screen puzzles.  The puzzles that I&rsquo;ve heard Tim Schafer call donkey and rider puzzles.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Theropods</em> is my favorite game of the jam.  Not only did it scope the game correctly for the development team, it was also playable in a reasonable amount of time.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>So there you have it, go out there and try some of these games.  If you only have time to try one, check out <em><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/theropods/58684/">Theropods</a></em>.  It&rsquo;s groovy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs Post-mortem]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-25T10:31:42-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/25/aurion-and-the-aurochs-post-mortem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Join me as I look back on my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game, <em><a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738">Aurion and the Aurochs</a></em>.  You can take a <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">look at the game</a> over on <a href="http://gamejolt.com">gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the sourcecode here</a>.  You can see all of the entries at <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">adventurejam&rsquo;s site</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to look at things that worked, things that didn&rsquo;t, and the lessons I&rsquo;ll take with me moving forward.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What Worked?</h2>

<h3>Pre-planning</h3>

<p>I sketched out the plot using <a href="http://www.lamemage.com/microscope/">Microscope</a> to define events, locations, and potential actions and routes the player could take through the game.  Microscope&rsquo;s 3"x5" index card format made it easy to move ideas around when they weren&rsquo;t working.  And it made it easy to see the overall flow of the game.</p>

<p>Once I got the plot Microscope&rsquo;d to my liking, I transferred it to the <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#microscope">project&rsquo;s readme</a>, using checkmarks and crosses to represent the filled and unfilled circles of Microscope.  Please note, that there be spoilers, so <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">go play the game</a> if you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>

<p>While I wasn&rsquo;t using the circles in the typical way that Microscope proposes, it did help me visualize the potential routes for &ldquo;good&rdquo; and &ldquo;bad&rdquo; alternate endings.</p>

<h3>Twine macros</h3>

<p>I used some <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion#created-using-artisanal-macros-from">Twine macros</a> for the first time in this game.  I can see how they add some impressive functionality to Twine.</p>

<p>I reckon, if I find the right macros, I would save a ton of time implementing functionality that has already been better implemented as drop-in macros.</p>

<h2>What Didn&rsquo;t Work?</h2>

<h3>Scope</h3>

<p>I set out to create what I thought at the time would be a relatively simple adventure game.  However, I failed to appreciate the combinatorial proliferation of states that blossomed out as I added more and more items and interactions.</p>

<h3>Timeframe and Pacing</h3>

<p>I found the rigid format of the gamejam to be oppressive and stressful.</p>

<h3>Prose</h3>

<p>Because I was so focused on implementing the game I wanted in the time I had, I feel that the initial creative spark that drove me to design <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> wasn&rsquo;t allowed to grow into the creative prose flamethrower that I wanted to torch raw palceholder text into a fine <em>crème brûlée</em>.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t force that <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/05/31/hammock-driven-creativity/">hammock-driven imagination</a>, especially when I feel crunched for time.</p>

<h2>What Will I Improve Next Time?</h2>

<h3>Plotting</h3>

<p>I will definitely continue to use Microscope for brainstorming and outlining plots.  It could be fun to collaborate with multiple people on this process, as Microscope is meant to be a multiplayer experience.</p>

<p>It may be worthwhile to write-up the &ldquo;single-player&rdquo; approach I used for Microscope brainstorming.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also be interested in trying out Tim Schafer&rsquo;s freewriting technique that I came across in the <a href="http://adventure.doublefine.com/">Double Fine Adventure documentaries</a>.  This probably merits its own post in the future.</p>

<h3>Scope and Pacing</h3>

<p>I will think hard about whether I should participate in gamejams with such strict time requirements for submissions.  I refuse to compromise on work and life commitments to participate in what should be a fun, creative hobby.</p>

<p>I feel emotionally and creatively drained from adventurejam, and I&rsquo;d prefer to have steady, fulfilling creative output.</p>

<p>I think the <em>laissez-faire</em> format of <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/01/make-things-that-make-things-number-procjam-2014/">#procjam</a> was healthier.  I should also note that, although I submitted more things to procjam, the scope of each of those projects was much smaller than my project for #adventurejam.</p>

<p>I think I could have compromised on delivering what was a more or less finished game.  I could have submitted a more prototype-y version that I could work on later.  In fact, I may still refine the prose of <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> if I feel so inclined in the future.</p>

<p>That being said, I&rsquo;m happy with the game I was able to deliver in the constraints of the jam.</p>

<h3>Investigate the Twine macro ecosystem</h3>

<p>Maybe in a future post, I&rsquo;ll look into some of the macros out there.  It&rsquo;d be useful to write simple example code too.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Well, that&rsquo;s it.  I have some good perspective going forward.  In the coming weeks, I&rsquo;m going to look at some of my favorite submissions and finalize my votes for the contest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aurion and the Aurochs is out]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-18T12:43:49-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/18/aurion-and-the-aurochs-is-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m happy to announce that my <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> game is finished and released.  I&rsquo;ll do a more in-depth post-mortem next week.  In the coming weeks, before the 30-day voting deadline ends, I want to take a look at some of the <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam/games">other submissions</a> that pique my interest.</p>

<p>You can <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/aurion-and-the-aurochs/60738/">play <em>Aurion and the Aurochs</em> on gamejolt</a> and you can <a href="https://github.com/zerosalife/aurion">view the source on github</a>.  Please leave me some feedback in the comments here or on twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/zerosalife">@zerosalife</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Midway through adventurejam I'm attending Midwest Gaming Classic]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/11/midway-through-adventurejam-im-attending-midwest-gaming-classic/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-11T08:22:57-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/11/midway-through-adventurejam-im-attending-midwest-gaming-classic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Quick update on #adventurejam</h2>

<p>I feel like my game is on track to finish next Friday.  I&rsquo;m happy to say it&rsquo;s feature complete.  I&rsquo;ll spend the next week polishing, various flavors of bughunting (maybe even some bugfishing and bugtrapping), and, most important of all, prosifying.  My goal is to come up with a little game that&rsquo;s compelling to play, rather than just a series of links to click.</p>

<h2>Midwest Gaming Classic</h2>

<p>Instead of a normal blog post, I want to take this time to shout out the <a href="http://twitter.com/MGC_gaming">@MGC_gaming</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/mgc_gaming">Midwest Gaming Classic</a>.  I&rsquo;ll be attending today.  So if you&rsquo;re there hit me up <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">@zerosalife</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deploying Twine games to Game Jolt]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/04/deploying-twine-games-to-game-jolt/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-04T13:57:39-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/04/04/deploying-twine-games-to-game-jolt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://jams.gamejolt.io/adventurejam">#adventurejam</a> started last night.  It lasts two weeks, until April 17.  I&rsquo;ll be covering my participation on here the blog under the <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/adventurejam/">adventurejam</a> tag.</p>

<p>Today, I&rsquo;m going to deploy small prototype Twine game to <a href="http://gamejolt.com">Game Jolt</a>.  I made this game a while back.  It&rsquo;s a complete prototype, but it&rsquo;s still got some display flaws.  I&rsquo;m putting it out there in all of its buggy glory.  The game served its purpose of familiarizing me with some of the ins and outs of Twine, as well as the build process I <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2015/03/28/building-twine-games-from-the-command-line/">described last week</a>.</p>

<h2><em>The Age of the Flying Boat</em></h2>

<p>I made a small prototype game based off of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hayao_Miyazaki">Hayao Miyazaki</a>&rsquo;s comic that was turned into the movie <em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0104652/">Porco Rosso</a></em>.  You must figure out how to fuel-up and start your airplane to respond to a desperate call for help.</p>

<p>You can play it <a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/the-age-of-the-flying-boat/58040/">here on Game Jolt</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Deploying a Twine game to Game Jolt</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what it took for me to deploy my first game on Game Jolt.</p>

<h3>Play by the rules</h3>

<p>First, I had to agree to the rules.</p>

<h3>Title, links, and copy</h3>

<p>Next up, I had to enter some information about my game.</p>

<h3>Thumbnail and maturity rating</h3>

<p>Then, I had a couple of necessary things to do: uploading a thumbnail and setting a surprisingly detailed maturity rating for my game.  There were several optional steps that I skipped for this game prototype.</p>

<p>There were a lot of headaches with the &ldquo;thumbnail&rdquo;.  It must be 16:9 and it must be at least 588 pixels tall.  Sounds like a full screenshot, to me.  But, this constraint is necessary because Game Jolt uses a bunch of different dimensions to display the thumbnail on the website.</p>

<h3>Game Distribution</h3>

<p>For my next trick, I uploaded a Game Distribution of the HTML persuasion.  I needed to upload a zip file containing my twine-generated <code>index.html</code>.</p>

<h3>Unhiding so people can play your game</h3>

<p>Now, here&rsquo;s the critical part.  Pay attention.</p>

<p>There were two (2) final steps to make my game available on the site:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>First, I had to unhide my game&rsquo;s profile when I was satisfied with information I entered.</p></li>
<li><p>Second, and most importantly, I had to specifically unhide the <code>html</code> we uploaded as a Game Distribution in the Distributions tab.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Whew!</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve followed along this far, we did it!  We uploaded a game to Game Jolt.  It&rsquo;s a surprisingly detailed process, but that amount of detail gives you a lot of tools make your game&rsquo;s presentation shine.</p>

<p>Go check out <em><a href="http://gamejolt.com/games/adventure/the-age-of-the-flying-boat/58040/">The Age of the Flying Boat</a></em> and let me know what you think in the comments or on <a href="http://twitter.com/zerosalife">twitter</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
