<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 7dfps | zero's a life]]></title>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/categories/7dfps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-28T17:22:56-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[zerosalife]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A proper review of DUNGEN [Star]]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-06T09:44:36-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/12/06/a-proper-review-of-dungen-star</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My green fingers sweat on the handle of my pistol as I creep through the door, into the next room.  I found two boxes of ammunition in the previous room so I&rsquo;m well equipped for the next horrible monster I encounter.  My grip on the pistol tightens as a horrible three-legged spherical thing jumps down from the ceiling, pirouetting to land on its feet and shooting a stream of acidic liquid at me.</em></p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Oof,&rdquo; is all I manage to get out, as I feel the Burster&rsquo;s fluid eat into my skin.  Without thinking I fire at it, killing the thing in two shots.</em></p>

<p><em>While reloading my pistol, I notice a glowing jewel on the stone.  If it&rsquo;s what the briefings said, this is the teleport stone that will allow me to phase out of our normal reality just long enough to escape the next deadly monster I encounter in</em> DUNGEN [Star].</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"><img class="center" src="/images/assets/DUNGENStar.gif"></a></p>

<p>(Please excuse my lame attempt at illustrating play with a .gif).</p>

<p><a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/procjam-review/">Last week, I posted an overview of my favorite #procjam games</a>.  I felt remissed when I got a tweet from the designer, asking whether I had actually printed and played the game.  I hadn&rsquo;t and neither had any of the other reviewers who praised it.  So, this week I took some time to cut out the cards on my computer, effectively making a print-and-play game I could play in Illustrator without bothering to print it out.</p>

<p>After the initial time investment, <em><a href="http://jctwood.itch.io/dungen">DUNGEN [Star]</a></em>, a print-and-play game designed by <a href="https://twitter.com/JctWood">@JctWood</a> for the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/paperjam">#paperjam</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/procjam">#procjam</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/7dfps">#7dfps</a> gamejams, plays quickly.  Especially if you are brave enough to choose the roguelike secret difficulty level of starting with 1HP.  Add to that, the advanced enemy rules, which give the monsters more personality on top of their already evocative illustrations and you&rsquo;ve got a challenging game.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a fan of the cartoonish art style of <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>.  The character design does a good job of communicating interesting variety, even though there are few monsters to go up against.</p>

<p><em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> runs out of steam quickly, but I think the intent behind it is clear.  This game does a good job of bringing the feel of a procedural first-person shooter with roguelike elements to the print-and-play market.  I think extending the combat to involve multiple weapons would add some depth to the game.  I would like to see more enemies, particularly ones with more interesting advanced enemy rules.  I&rsquo;d also like to see an overarching goal or theme tying together <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em>&rsquo;s dungeoning and star, so you feel more satisfied when you survive the dungeon.  With that criticism said, I still think <em>DUNGEN [Star]</em> succeeds as a gamejam game and a great prototype from which to build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[INSceptahdeckWU]]></title>
    <link href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T08:28:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/11/08/insceptahdeckwu</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>#procjam updates</h2>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q%3Dprocjam">#procjam</a> is upon us.  The conference is on and popping, streaming at <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/procjam">http://www.twitch.tv/procjam</a>.  I&rsquo;ll try to precede my #procjam posts with a little update on some of the cool things I&rsquo;ve seen that need pointing out during the jam itself.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/GalaxyKate">@GalaxyKate</a> will be streaming <a href="http://vimeo.com/111272682">some tutorials</a> today, following the conference.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/SudoRossy">@sudorossy</a> is currently streaming some development and modeling at <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/sudorossy">http://www.twitch.tv/sudorossy</a>.  I imagine that sudorossy will continue this throughout the jam.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q%3D7dfps">#7dfps</a> jam is also going on this week.  So, I&rsquo;ve decided to release my third person procedural tweeter.  Or maybe it&rsquo;s a fourth person tweeter, third person once removed.</p>

<h2>Fourth-person tweets</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m at it again, <a href="http://zerosalife.github.io/blog/2014/04/19/styx-ebooks/">making a twitter bot</a> like <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>.  Only this time it&rsquo;s in a completely different language and it&rsquo;s got a completely different corpus.  Corpus is a Latin way of saying text, in case you forgot.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Making the tweets</h2>

<p>The basic algorithm works like this.</p>

<p>The bot creates a huge textfile containing lyrics from Wu Tang Clan songs.  I trim away a lot of the information about verses and choruses, but I keep the punctuation because I like the sense of rhythm it creates.</p>

<p>Based on the relationship between the words in this corpus file, the bot builds a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">markov process</a> to generate the text of the tweets.  To do so, the bot generates a transition matrix using <a href="https://github.com/Janiczek/markov">Janiczek&rsquo;s Clojure markov library</a>.  It then takes random walks through that matrix to produce a string of text with a similar relationship between words to the input lyrics corpus.</p>

<h2>Making it a command line app</h2>

<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve tried to make a command line application in Twitter.  Luckily there are some good tools out there.</p>

<p>I wondered how to deal with multiple options and inputs, and the good news is: it&rsquo;s just as easy as you&rsquo;d think.  You simply add conditionals to deal with the possible behaviors of your program.  The magic of <code>parse-opts</code> handles the rest.  Options with long names automatically become keys to the option dictionary, and if you&rsquo;ve marked them as a <code>:flag</code> you can depend on the truth-value to control the flow of your program.</p>

<p>You may think it&rsquo;s odd that I&rsquo;m using options instead of actions as in the <code>cli</code> example, but hey.  It&rsquo;s my program.  Your program can work the way you want it too.  I&rsquo;m going to make sure to document it so you can use the Rebel INS or build a twitter bot based on this code.</p>

<p>To build the app, I use <code>lein bin</code> from the command line.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m interested in <a href="http://www.rkn.io/2014/02/06/clojure-cookbook-daemons/">daemonizing</a> the application.  That is to say, I&rsquo;m interested in turning it into a persistent process that runs in the background on my computer.  But for now, I&rsquo;ve set up a simple <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">cron</a> script to tweet every few hours.</p>

<h2>Logging</h2>

<p>When I do tweets from the command line there&rsquo;s some dark magic going on that I don&rsquo;t understand.  Anyway it seems to invoke the <code>Log4j</code>, so I <a href="http://www.bahmanm.com/blogs/how-to-add-logging-to-a-clojure-project">set that up according to this blog post</a>.</p>

<h2>Markov chain text generation</h2>

<p>One of the quirks of the markov package I used is that it stops generating &lsquo;random walks&rsquo; when it reaches states that it has not been trained on.  As you can imagine when using imagery-rich, neologism-laden rap music, there are many words that occur once, even in a very large corpus.  Being unique is kind of a goal of the form, a fact reflected in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ol%2527_Dirty_Bastard">at least one alias</a>.</p>

<p>In order to make more realistic texts, it&rsquo;s common to increase the order of the transition matrix.  That is to say, to determine the probability for a following word from the prior two or more words.  However, given my idiosyncratic corpus, this leads the &lsquo;random walk&rsquo; algorithm to halt, giving me too few words in my output.</p>

<p>Interestingly, in this case, dialing back the order tends to lead to more rhyming and a few recognizable couplets, which I find kinda nice.</p>

<h2>Setting up the twitter account</h2>

<p>I ran into a problem getting an app set up for the bot&rsquo;s twitter account.  I am merely one person, and thus have need for merely one cell phone.  Since twitter requires a unique mobile number for authenticating apps, I was out of luck.  That is, until I found this <a href="http://dghubble.com/blog/posts/twitter-app-write-access-and-bots/">blog post showing how to use the same app on multiple bot clients</a>.</p>

<p>Faithful readers may remember my wildly popular, and yet still somehow deeply underrated, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangsian_fantasy">Bangsian</a> fantasy bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a>.  Using <code>twurl</code> I was able to grant access to the <a href="https://twitter.com/styx_ebooks">@styx_ebooks</a> app credentials for the new bot.</p>

<h2>Moving on</h2>

<p>You can find the source code over on <a href="http://github.com/zerosalife/insceptahdeckwu">github.</a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s one of my favorite tweets so far:</p>

<p><div class='embed tweet'>Tweet could not be processed</div></p>

<p>From here the sky&rsquo;s the limit.  I could try analyzing the generated text to try to build lines or stanzas.  I could try to reorder words to reflect the syntax present from the transcription.  I could try to represent individual emcees with unique corpora.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
